<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <ecda:hyperDiv>
         <ecda:notes>
            <note type="ecda">
               <interpGrp type="commType">
                  <interp xml:id="flora">plants (flora)</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="fauna">animals (fauna)</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="food">food and other consumable items (incl. drinks, seasonings,
                     etc.)</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="medical">medical or medicinal items (including references to folk
                     medicine)</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="textile">sartorial and textile references</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="currency">references to money or currency</interp>
               </interpGrp>
               <interpGrp type="productionPhase">
                  <interp xml:id="plant">planting</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="cultivation">cultivation</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="harvest">harvesting</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="refine">refining</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="production">production (non plant-based commodities)</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="transport">transport</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="sale">sale</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="circulation">circulation of commodities, such as through
                     gift-giving or theft</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="use">use of commodities</interp>
               </interpGrp>
               <interpGrp>
                  <interp xml:id="punishment">References to scenes of punishment or the enforcement
                     of colonial rule</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="military">References to the material conditions, social
                     institutions or actual events of warfare</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="abolition">References to the abolition of slavery or abolitionist
                     movement</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="disease">References to ailment and disease, specifically in
                     people</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="poison">References to poison</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="obeah">References to Obeah</interp>
                  <interp xml:id="performance">References to performance (esp. John Canoe)</interp>
               </interpGrp>
            </note>
         </ecda:notes>
      </ecda:hyperDiv>


      <front>
         <titleBlock>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart/>
            </docTitle>

         </titleBlock>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="prefatory">

            <p>THE following interesting narrative is a convenient supplement to the history of Mary
               Prince. It is given, like hers, as nearly as possible in the narrator’s words, with
               only so much correction as was necessary to connect the story, and render it
               grammatical. The concluding passage in inverted commas, is entirely his own. While
               Mary’s narrative shews the disgusting character of colonial slavery, this little tale
               explains with equal force the horrors in which it originates.</p>
            <p>It is necessary to explain that Louis came to this country about five year ago, in a
               French vessel called the Pearl. She had lost her reckoning, and was driven by stress
               of weather into the port of St Ives, in Cornwall. Louis and his four companions were
               brought to London upon a writ of Habeas Corpus at the instance of Mr George Stephen;
               and, after some trifling opposition on the part of the master of the vessel, were
               discharged by Lord Wynford. Two of his unfortunate fellow-sufferers died of the
               measles at Hampstead; the other two returned to Sierra Leone; but poor Louis, when
               offered the choice of going back to Africa, replied, ‘Me no father, no mother now; me
               stay with you.’ And here he has ever since remained; conducting himself in a way to
               gain the good will and respect of all who know him. He is remarkably intelligent ,
               understands our language perfectly, and can read and write well. The last sentences
               of the following narrative will seem almost too peculiar to be his own; but it is not
               the first time that in conversation with Mr George Stephen, he has made similar
               remarks. On one occasion in particular, he was heard saying to himself in the
               kitchen, while sitting by the fire apparently in deep thought, ‘Me think,--me
               think--’ A fellow-servant inquired what he meant; and he added, ‘Me think what a good
               thing I came to England! Here, I know what God is, and read my Bible; in my country
               they have no God, no Bible.’</p>
            <p>How severe and just a reproof of the guilty wretches who visit his country only with
               fire and sword! How deserved a censure upon the not less guilty men, who dare to
               vindicate the state of slavery, on the lying pretext, that its victims are of an
               inferior nature! And scarcely less deserving of reprobation are those who have it in
               their power to prevent these crimes, but who remain inactive from indifference, or
               are dissuaded from throwing the shield of British power over the victim of
               oppression, by the sophistry, and the clamour, and the avarice of the oppressor. It
               is the reproach and the sin of England. May God avert from our country the ruin which
               this national guilt deserves! </p>
            <p>We lament to add, that the Pearl which brought these negroes to our shore, was
               restored to its owners at the instance of the French Government, instead of being
               condemned as a prize to Lieut. Rye who, on his own responsibility, detained her, with
               all her manacles and chains and other detestable proofs of her piratical occupation
               on board. We trust it is not yet too late to demand investigation into the reasons
               for restoring her.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head> The Negro Boy's Narrative</head>
            <p>My father's name was Clashoquin; mine is Asa-Asa. He lived in a country called Bycla,
               near Egie, a large town. Egie is as latge as Brighton; it was some way from the sea.
               I had five brothers and sisters. We all lived together with my father and mother; he
               kept a horse, and was respectable, but not one of the great men. My uncle was one of
               the great men at Egie: he could make men come and work for him: his name was Otou. He
               had a great deal of land and cattle. My father sometimes worked on his own land, and
               used to make charcoal. I was too little to work; my eldest brother used to work on
               the land; and we were all very happy.</p>
            <p> A great many people, whom we called Adiny[insert]s, set fire to Egie in the morning
               before daybreak; there were some thousands of them. They killed a great many, and
               burnt all their houses. They staid two days, and then carried all the people whom
               they did not kill.</p>
            <p>They came again every now and then for a month, as long as they could find people to
               carry away. They used to tie them by the feet, except when they were taking them off,
               and then they let them loose; but if they offered to run away, the would shoot them.
               I lost a great many friends and relations at Egie; about a dozen. They sold all they
               carried away, to be slaves. I know this because I afterwards saw them as slaves on
               the other side of the sea. They took away brothers, and sisters, and husbands, and
               wives; they did not care about this. They were sod for cloth or gunpowder, sometimes
               for salt or guns; sometimes they got four or five guns for a man: they were English
               guns, made like my master's that I clean for his shooting. The Adiny{insert] burnt a
               great many places besides Egie. They burnt all the country wherever they found
               villages; they used to shoot men, women, and children, if they ran away.</p>
            <p>They came to us about eleven o'clock one day, and directly they came they set our
               house on fire. All of us had run away. We kept together, and went into the woods, and
               stopped there two days. The Adiny[insert]s then went away, and we returned home and
               found everything burnt. We tried to build a little shed, and were beginning to get
               comfortable again. We found several of our neighbours lying around wounded; they had
               been shot. I saw the bodies of four or five little children whom they had killed with
               blows on the head. They had carried away their fathers and mothers, but the children
               were too small for slaves, so they killed them. They kad killed severl others, but
               these were all tht I saw. I saw them lying in the street like dead dogs.</p>
            <p> In about a week after we got back, the Adiny[insert[s returned, and burnt all the
               sheds and houses they had left standing. We all ran away again; we went to the woods
               as we had done before.--They followed us the next day. We went farther into the
               woods, and staid there four days and nights; we were half starved; we only got a few
               potatoes. My uncle Otou was with us. At the end of this time, the Adiny[insert[s
               found us. We ran away. They called my uncle to go to them; but he refused, and they
               shot him immediately: they killed him. The rest of us ran on, and they did not get at
               us till the next day. I ran up into a tree: they followed me and brought me down.
               They tied my feet. I do not know if they found my father and mother, and brothers and
               sisters: they had run faster than me, and were half a mile further when I got up into
               the tree: I have never seen them since. --There was man who ran up into the tree with
               me: I believe they shot him, for I never saw him again.</p>
            <p>They carried away about twenty besides me. They carried us to the sea. They did not
               beat us: they only killed one man, who ws very ill and too weak to carry his load:
               they made all of us carry chickens and meat for our food; but this poor man could not
               carry his load, and they ran him through the body with a sword. -- He was a neighbour
               of ours. When we got to the sea they sold all of us, but not to the same person. The
               sold us for money; and I was sold six times over, sometimes for money, sometimes for
               cloth, and sometimes for a gun. I was about thirteen years old. It was about half a
               year from the time I waas taken, before I saw the white people.</p>
            <p>We were taken in a boat from place to place, and sold at every place we stopped at.
               In about six months we got to a ship, in which we first saw white people: they were
               French. They bought us. We found here a great many other slaves; there were about
               eighty, including women and children. The Frenchmen sent away all but five of us into
               another very large ship. We five staid on board till we got to England, which was
               about five or six months. The slaves we saw on board the ship were chained together
               by the legs below deck, so close they could not move. They were flogged very cruelly:
               I saw one of them flogged till he diedl we could not tell wat for. They gave them
               enough to eat. The place they were confined in below deck was so hot and nasty I
               could not bear to be in it. A great many of the slaves were ill, ut they were not
               attended to. They used to flog me very bad on board the ship: the captain cut my head
               very bad one time. </p>
            <p>'I am very happy to be in England, as far as I am very well;--but I have no friend
               belonging to me, but God, who will take care of me as he has done already. I am very
               glad I have come to England, to know who God is. I should lke much to see my friends
               again, but I do not now wish to go back to the,: for if I go back to my own country,
               I might be taken as a slave again. I would rather stay here, where I am free, than go
               back to my country to be sold. I shall stay in England as long as (please God) I
               shall live. I wish the King of England could know all I have told you. I wish it that
               he my see how cruelly we are used. We had no king in our country, or he would have
               stopt it. I think the king of England might stop it, and this is why I wish him to
               know it all. I have heard say he is good; and if he is, he will stop it if he can. I
               am well of f myself, for I am well taken care of, and have good bed and good clothes;
               but I wish my own people to be as comfortable.'</p>





         </div>


      </body>

   </text>
</TEI>
