<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <tagsDecl>
                <!-- put any rend defaults here -->
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <ecda:hyperDiv>
            <ecda:notes>
                <note type="ecda">
                    <interpGrp type="commType">
                        <interp xml:id="flora">plants (flora)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="fauna">animals (fauna)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="food">food and other consumable items (incl. drinks, seasonings, etc.)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="medical">medical or medicinal items (including references to folk medicine)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="textile">sartorial and textile references</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="currency">references to money or currency</interp>
                    </interpGrp>
                    <interpGrp type="productionPhase">
                        <interp xml:id="plant">planting</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="cultivation">cultivation</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="harvest">harvesting</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="refine">refining</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="production">production (non plant-based commodities)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="transport">transport</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="sale">sale</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="circulation">circulation of commodities, such as through gift-giving or theft</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="use">use of commodities</interp>
                    </interpGrp>
                    <interpGrp>
                        <interp xml:id="punishment">References to scenes of punishment or the enforcement of colonial rule</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="military">References to the material conditions, social institutions or actual events of warfare</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="abolition">References to the abolition of slavery or abolitionist movement</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="disease">References to ailment and disease, specifically in people</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="poison">References to poison</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="obeah">References to Obeah</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="performance">References to performance (esp. John Canoe)</interp>
                    </interpGrp>
                </note>
                <note rend="place-outside">
                    <ab><placeName>Senegal</placeName> and 
                        the Countries 
                        of <placeName>Walo</placeName> and 
                        <placeName>Cayor</placeName>, or 
                        <placeName>Demel</placeName>.
                    </ab>
                    <ab><persName>John Barnes</persName>,
                        Esquire.
                    </ab>
                </note> <!-- I think we need a specific @type value for these "notes." They function more like running heads than anything else -->
            </ecda:notes>
        </ecda:hyperDiv>
        
        
        <front>
            <titleBlock>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart><hi rend="allcaps">Report</hi>
                        of
                        The Lords of the <orgName>Committee of Council</orgName>
                        appointed for the Consideration of all Matters
                        relating to Trade and Foreign Plantations;
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart rend="allcaps">Submitting to His Majesty's Consideration</titlePart>
                    <titlePart>The Evidence and Information they have collected
                        in consequence of his Majesty's Order in Council,
                        dated the <date when="1788-02-11">11th of February 1788</date>, concerning the
                        present State of the Trade to <placeName rend="smallcaps">Africa</placeName>, and particularly
                        the Trade in <distinct>Slaves</distinct>; and concerning the Effects and
                        Consequences of this Trade, as well in <placeName rend="smallcaps">Africa</placeName> and
                        the <placeName rend="smallcaps">West Indies</placeName>, as to the general Commerce of this
                        Kindgom.
                    </titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docDate when="1789">1789.</docDate>
            </titleBlock>
        </front>
        
        <body>
            <div>
                <head rend="allcaps">At the
                    Council Chamber, <placeName rend="italic">Whitehall</placeName>,
                    the <date when="1789-03-28">18th of <mcr rend="italic">March</mcr> 1789</date>.
                </head>
                <byline>By the Right Honourable the Lords of the 
                    Committee of Council appointed for the
                    Consideration of all Matters relating to
                    Trade and Foreign Plantations.
                </byline>
                <ab>Your Majesty having been pleased by your Order in Council,
                    bearing date the <date when="1788-02-11">11th of February 1788</date>, to direct that this
                    Committee should forthwith take into their Consideration the present State of
                    The <rs type="properAdjective">African</rs> Trade, particularly as far as relates to the Practice and
                    Manner of purchasing or obtaining Slaves on the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and
                    the Importation and Sale thereof, either in the <rs type="properAdjective">British</rs> Colonies and
                    Settlements, or in the Foreign Colonies and Settlements of <placeName>America</placeName> or
                    <placeName>West Indies</placeName>; and also, as far as relates to the Effects and
                    Consequences of this Trade both in <placeName>Africa</placeName> and in the said <rs type="place">Colonies</rs> and
                    Settlements, and to the general Commerce of this Kindgom; and should
                    repot to your Majesty in the Council the Result of their Inquiries, with such
                    Observations as they might have to offer thereupon:
                </ab>
                <ab>The Committee, in obedience to your Majesty's said Order of Reference, 
                    proceeded immediately to investigate the Subject so referred, and
                    examined such Persons as either offered themselves, or such as they
                    thought proper to summon, being in the Judgment of the Committee
                    likely to convey useful Information thereupon; and they applied to the
                    Agents for the several British Islands in the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>; and to your
                    Majesty's Governors and the Councils and Assemblies of the said Islands;
                    and also to the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts,
                    for Anwers to such Questions as appeared in the Committee to be calculated
                    to produce Information on the several parts of this extensive
                    Subject. The Committee thought proper likewise to apply to your
                    Majesty's Ministers at Foreign Courts for such Information as they might
                    be able to procure concerning the State of the <rs type="properAdjective">African</rs> Trade as carried
                    on by Foreign Countries, and concerning the Manner of transporting
                    Slaves to their respective Colonies, and the Treatment of them there.
                </ab>
                
                <pb/>
                <fw type="pageNum">4</fw>
                
                <ab>And the Committee also caused the Books of the late Board of Trade
                    to be searched for all the Information to be found therein respecting
                    this Subject. They also called for, and obtained from the Public 
                    Offices and other Sources, such Accounts as appeared to them to be
                    likely to throw light upon any of the Heads of this Inquiry, and 
                    particularly upon the Extent and Value of this Trade in all its Branches,
                    and the Effects and Consequences of it upon the general Commerce of this
                    Kingdom.
                </ab>
                <ab>And the Committee having been employed for upwards of Twelve
                    Months in collecting Information upon several Points before mentioned,
                    and conceiving it may be your Majesty's Intention to order this Report to
                    be laid as soon as possible before Parliament, have thought it right,
                    without any further Delay, or waiting for any additional Information, to
                    direct that the Information already collected be arranged as nearly as may
                    be found practicable, according to the following plan:
                </ab>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label rend="nobreak">First.</label>
                        <ab>The Evidence that the Committee has obtained of the
                            present state of those Parts of <placeName>Africa</placeName> from whence Slaves have been exported,
                            taking each Country that lies upon the Coast separately, beginning from
                            the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName>, and descending southward to the last of the <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs>
                            Settlements on the said Coast, with such information as has been obtained
                            of the interior Countries, situated behind each of the said Countries
                            on the Coast respectively; comprehending under this Head,
                            <list>
                                <item><label>1st</label>, The Government of each Country.</item>
                                <item><label>2d</label>, The Religion.</item>
                                <item><label>3d</label>, The Customs, Manners, &amp;c.</item>
                                <item><label>4th</label>, The Manner in which Slaves are made, or become so. For
                                    example:
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Whether they are born Slaves, or made Captives in War,
                                            or kidnapped.
                                        </item>
                                        <item>Whether condemned to be Slaves for Crimes, and for what
                                            Crimes.
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item><label>5th</label>, Whether they are brought from other Countries in the
                                    interior Parts of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and from what Countries, &amp;c.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>6th</label>,The Treatment of Slaves in the Country from whence they
                                    are brought.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>7th</label>, The Manner in which <name>Europeans</name> purchase Slaves, whether
                                    with Money or by Merchandise, and at what Prices; or whether
                                    they ever obtain them by Fraud, or in any improper Way whatsoever?
                                </item>
                                <item><label>8th</label>, The Behaviour of Slaves at the Time and Place of Sale, or
                                    in consequence of being sold.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>9th</label>, The Numbers carried annually from each Country on the
                                    Coast by the different <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs> Nations; and the Proportion of
                                    Males, Females, and Children.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>10th</label>, How the Slaves offered for Sale, when not purchased, are 
                                    disposed of.
                                </item>
                                
                                <pb/>
                                <fw type="pageNum">5</fw>
                                
                                <item><label>11th</label>, The Produce of each Country in Africa in which any
                                    other Commerce is at present carried on: the Extent of such
                                    Commerce, and the Information that has been obtained of any
                                    Prospect there may be of increasing the Trade with Africa in any
                                    such Articles of Produce, or of creating new Branches of Commerce
                                    in other Articles of Produce, by giving Encouragement
                                    for that Purpose.
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>To this Head is annexed an Account of the Charters and Statutes,
                            under the Authority and Protection of which the African Trade first
                            began, and has continued to the present Time; and of the most 
                            material Proceedings that have been had in the House of Commons 
                            relative thereto.
                        </ab>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Second.</label> The evidence that has been obtained concerning the
                        Manner of carrying Slaves to the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, under the following Heads:
                        <list>
                            <item>The Size or Tonnage of the Ships.</item>
                            <item>The Manner of sitting up the Ships.</item>
                            <item>The Provisions taken on board.</item>
                            <item>The Medicines.</item>
                            <item>The Officers of the Ship, such as Masters, Surgeons, &amp;c.</item>
                            <item>The Number of Slaves usually carried per Ton from the different
                                Countries on the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>.
                            </item>
                            <item>The general Treatment of Slaves while on board, either in Health
                                or in Sickness.
                            </item>
                            <item>The Mortality of Slaves, and the Causes of it.</item>
                            <item>The Mortality of Seamen, and the Causes of it.</item>
                            <item>The Manner in which the Slaves are sold when landed in the 
                                <placeName>West Indies</placeName>.
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Third.</label>
                        <ab rend="nobreak">The Treatment of the Slaves in the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, and all
                            Circumstances relating thereto, arranged in the Manner stated in <ref type="goTo">Paper A.
                            in the Appendix</ref>, as will appear in that Part of the Report where the Evidence
                            on this Subject is given.
                        </ab>
                        <ab>To this Head is annexed a general View of the Laws respecting
                            <rs type="properAdjective">Negro</rs> Slaves in most of the Islands, followed by a Statement at large of
                            such of the said Laws as now subsist in each Island, arranged under different
                            Titles, as prepared by <persName>Mr. Reeves</persName>, Law Clerk to this Committee;
                            and there is also Information on this Subject in the Answers of some of
                            the Governors and Legislatures of the Islands to the Questions transmitted
                            to them by the Order of this Committee.
                        </ab>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Fourth.</label> The Accounts hat have been called for to shew the 
                        extend ot the Trade in all its Branches, and the Number of the Free 
                        Inhabitants and Slaves of each of the Islands in the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, according
                        to a Plan stated in <ref type="goTo">Paper B. of the Appendix</ref>, so far as the Accounts
                        could be procured, as will appear in that Part of the Report where these
                        Accounts are given.
                    </item>
                    
                    <pb/>
                    <fw type="pageNum">6</fw>
                    
                    <item><label>Fifth.</label> All the Information that has been obtainedrelating to the
                        Advantages, which the <placeName>French West India Islands</placeName> are supposed at present
                        to enjoy over the <rs type="place">British Islands</rs>, and the Reasons and Circumstances on
                        which these superior Advantages appear to be funded, according to a 
                        Plan stated in <ref type="goTo">Paper C. in the Appendix</ref>.
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Sixth.</label> All the Information that has been obtained concerning the 
                        Extent of the Trade of other <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs> Nations to <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and the
                        Manner in which the same is carried on; and concerning the Treatment
                        of Slaves in the Foreign Islands or Colonies in America and the
                        <placeName>West Indies</placeName>; and concerning the Trade in Slaves carried on in the interior
                        Parts of that Country as connected therewith, either by <name>Europeans</name>,
                        or by the different People of <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Africa</placeName>.
                    </item>
                </list>
                <ab>All the Information and Matter collected by the Committe, has, in
                    pursuance of their Orders, been arranged under the foregoing Heads by
                    the Gentlement belonging to the Office for Trade; and the <distinct type="dialect" rend="italic">vivâ voce</distinct>
                    Evidence upon each Head is stated as nearly as possible in the very Words
                    in which the same was given. If it should be wished to see the whole
                    Evidence exactly as it was taken before the Committee, a Copy thereof
                    <distinct rend="italic">verbatim</distinct> is ready to be produced; but the Committee think it their
                    Duty to submit to your Majesty's Consideration, how far it may be
                    Proper to make publicall the Information received respecting the present
                    State of the Forts on the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>; and also some Circumstances
                    respecting the Share which your Majesty's Subjects have in the Foreign
                    Trade carried on upon the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName> for the Supply of Slaves to
                    the Foreign Islands and Settlements in <placeName>America</placeName> and the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>.
                    These, for reasons respecting the Public as well as Individuals, it may
                    not perhaps be so prudent to wholly divulge.
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <ab>View of the <mcr rend="smallcaps">Evidence</mcr> that the Committee has
                        obtained from the present State of those Parts of 
                        <placeName rend="smallcaps">Africa</placeName> from whence <mcr rend="smallcaps">Slaves</mcr> have been
                        exported, taking each Country that lies upon the
                        Coast separately, beginning from the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName>,
                        and descending Southward to the last of the 
                        <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs> Settlements on the said Coast; with
                        such Information as has been obtained of the
                        interior Countries situated behind each of the said
                        Countries on the Coast respectively.
                    </ab>
                </div>
                
                <pb/>
                <!-- more pbs here -->
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head rend="italic">Government, Religion, Manners, and Customs.</head>
                    <div type="subsection" xml:id="a001" corresp="#n001">
                        <p><persName>John Barnes</persName>, Esquire, was resident at <placeName>Senegal</placeName> near Eight Years, the last Three
                            Years as Governor, the first Five Years as a Merchant; has been at other Places on the
                            Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, but was never in the Service of the <orgName>African Company</orgName> upon any toher Part
                            of the Coast. The Nature of his Commerce upon the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName> was chiefly the gumm
                            Trade.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Countries immediately round <placeName>Senegal</placeName> are the Country of <placeName>Walo</placeName>, and the Country of
                            <placeName>Cayor</placeName> or <placeName>Demel</placeName>; the Nature of the Government in these Countries (which are of considerable
                            Extent) is Monarchy, absolute in some Respects, but limited in others, and hereditary in the 
                            Female Line. <!-- interesting things about gender? -->
                        </p>
                        <p>As to the Religion of these Countries, great Part of the Inhabitants are Mahometans, but
                            very imperfect. The Government is greatly under the Influence and Countroul of the Moorish
                            Tribes inhabiting the Desert on the North Side of the River; this Desert extends from the
                            North Side of the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName> to the Southern Declivity of <placeName>Mount Atlas</placeName>. The Extent is
                            about Ten Degrees from North to South, and the Borders of it to the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName> or
                            Mount Atlas are alone inhabited
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
