<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <tagsDecl>
                <!-- put any rend defaults here -->
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <ecda:hyperDiv>
            <ecda:notes>
                <note type="ecda">
                    <interpGrp type="commType">
                        <interp xml:id="flora">plants (flora)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="fauna">animals (fauna)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="food">food and other consumable items (incl. drinks, seasonings, etc.)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="medical">medical or medicinal items (including references to folk medicine)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="textile">sartorial and textile references</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="currency">references to money or currency</interp>
                    </interpGrp>
                    <interpGrp type="productionPhase">
                        <interp xml:id="plant">planting</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="cultivation">cultivation</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="harvest">harvesting</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="refine">refining</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="production">production (non plant-based commodities)</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="transport">transport</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="sale">sale</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="circulation">circulation of commodities, such as through gift-giving or theft</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="use">use of commodities</interp>
                    </interpGrp>
                    <interpGrp>
                        <interp xml:id="punishment">References to scenes of punishment or the enforcement of colonial rule</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="military">References to the material conditions, social institutions or actual events of warfare</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="abolition">References to the abolition of slavery or abolitionist movement</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="disease">References to ailment and disease, specifically in people</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="poison">References to poison</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="obeah">References to Obeah</interp>
                        <interp xml:id="performance">References to performance (esp. John Canoe)</interp>
                    </interpGrp>
                </note>
            </ecda:notes>
        </ecda:hyperDiv>
        
        
        <front>
            <titleBlock>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart><hi rend="allcaps">Report</hi>
                        of
                        The Lords of the <orgName>Committee of Council</orgName>
                        appointed for the Consideration of all Matters
                        relating to Trade and Foreign Plantations;
                    </titlePart>
                    <titlePart rend="allcaps">Submitting to His Majesty's Consideration</titlePart>
                    <titlePart>The Evidence and Information they have collected
                        in consequence of his Majesty's Order in Council,
                        dated the <date when="1788-02-11">11th of February 1788</date>, concerning the
                        present State of the Trade to <placeName rend="smallcaps">Africa</placeName>, and particularly
                        the Trade in <distinct>Slaves</distinct>; and concerning the Effects and
                        Consequences of this Trade, as well in <placeName rend="smallcaps">Africa</placeName> and
                        the <placeName rend="smallcaps">West Indies</placeName>, as to the general Commerce of this
                        Kindgom.
                    </titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docDate when="1789">1789.</docDate>
            </titleBlock>
        </front>
        
        <body>
            <div>
                <head rend="allcaps">At the
                    Council Chamber, <placeName rend="italic">Whitehall</placeName>,
                    the <date when="1789-03-28">18th of <mcr rend="italic">March</mcr> 1789</date>.
                </head>
                <byline>By the Right Honourable the Lords of the 
                    Committee of Council appointed for the
                    Consideration of all Matters relating to
                    Trade and Foreign Plantations.
                </byline>
                <ab>Your Majesty having been pleased by your Order in Council,
                    bearing date the <date when="1788-02-11">11th of February 1788</date>, to direct that this
                    Committee should forthwith take into their Consideration the present State of
                    The <rs type="properAdjective">African</rs> Trade, particularly as far as relates to the Practice and
                    Manner of purchasing or obtaining Slaves on the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and
                    the Importation and Sale thereof, either in the <rs type="properAdjective">British</rs> Colonies and
                    Settlements, or in the Foreign Colonies and Settlements of <placeName>America</placeName> or
                    <placeName>West Indies</placeName>; and also, as far as relates to the Effects and
                    Consequences of this Trade both in <placeName>Africa</placeName> and in the said <rs type="place">Colonies</rs> and
                    Settlements, and to the general Commerce of this Kindgom; and should
                    repot to your Majesty in the Council the Result of their Inquiries, with such
                    Observations as they might have to offer thereupon:
                </ab>
                <ab>The Committee, in obedience to your Majesty's said Order of Reference, 
                    proceeded immediately to investigate the Subject so referred, and
                    examined such Persons as either offered themselves, or such as they
                    thought proper to summon, being in the Judgment of the Committee
                    likely to convey useful Information thereupon; and they applied to the
                    Agents for the several British Islands in the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>; and to your
                    Majesty's Governors and the Councils and Assemblies of the said Islands;
                    and also to the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts,
                    for Anwers to such Questions as appeared in the Committee to be calculated
                    to produce Information on the several parts of this extensive
                    Subject. The Committee thought proper likewise to apply to your
                    Majesty's Ministers at Foreign Courts for such Information as they might
                    be able to procure concerning the State of the <rs type="properAdjective">African</rs> Trade as carried
                    on by Foreign Countries, and concerning the Manner of transporting
                    Slaves to their respective Colonies, and the Treatment of them there.
                </ab>
                
                <pb/>
                <fw type="pageNum">4</fw>
                
                <ab>And the Committee also caused the Books of the late Board of Trade
                    to be searched for all the Information to be found therein respecting
                    this Subject. They also called for, and obtained from the Public 
                    Offices and other Sources, such Accounts as appeared to them to be
                    likely to throw light upon any of the Heads of this Inquiry, and 
                    particularly upon the Extent and Value of this Trade in all its Branches,
                    and the Effects and Consequences of it upon the general Commerce of this
                    Kingdom.
                </ab>
                <ab>And the Committee having been employed for upwards of Twelve
                    Months in collecting Information upon several Points before mentioned,
                    and conceiving it may be your Majesty's Intention to order this Report to
                    be laid as soon as possible before Parliament, have thought it right,
                    without any further Delay, or waiting for any additional Information, to
                    direct that the Information already collected be arranged as nearly as may
                    be found practicable, according to the following plan:
                </ab>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label rend="nobreak">First.</label>
                        <ab>The Evidence that the Committee has obtained of the
                            present state of those Parts of <placeName>Africa</placeName> from whence Slaves have been exported,
                            taking each Country that lies upon the Coast separately, beginning from
                            the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName>, and descending southward to the last of the <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs>
                            Settlements on the said Coast, with such information as has been obtained
                            of the interior Countries, situated behind each of the said Countries
                            on the Coast respectively; comprehending under this Head,
                            <list>
                                <item><label>1st</label>, The Government of each Country.</item>
                                <item><label>2d</label>, The Religion.</item>
                                <item><label>3d</label>, The Customs, Manners, &amp;c.</item>
                                <item><label>4th</label>, The Manner in which Slaves are made, or become so. For
                                    example:
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Whether they are born Slaves, or made Captives in War,
                                            or kidnapped.
                                        </item>
                                        <item>Whether condemned to be Slaves for Crimes, and for what
                                            Crimes.
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item><label>5th</label>, Whether they are brought from other Countries in the
                                    interior Parts of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and from what Countries, &amp;c.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>6th</label>,The Treatment of Slaves in the Country from whence they
                                    are brought.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>7th</label>, The Manner in which <name>Europeans</name> purchase Slaves, whether
                                    with Money or by Merchandise, and at what Prices; or whether
                                    they ever obtain them by Fraud, or in any improper Way whatsoever?
                                </item>
                                <item><label>8th</label>, The Behaviour of Slaves at the Time and Place of Sale, or
                                    in consequence of being sold.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>9th</label>, The Numbers carried annually from each Country on the
                                    Coast by the different <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs> Nations; and the Proportion of
                                    Males, Females, and Children.
                                </item>
                                <item><label>10th</label>, How the Slaves offered for Sale, when not purchased, are 
                                    disposed of.
                                </item>
                                
                                <pb/>
                                <fw type="pageNum">5</fw>
                                
                                <item><label>11th</label>, The Produce of each Country in Africa in which any
                                    other Commerce is at present carried on: the Extent of such
                                    Commerce, and the Information that has been obtained of any
                                    Prospect there may be of increasing the Trade with Africa in any
                                    such Articles of Produce, or of creating new Branches of Commerce
                                    in other Articles of Produce, by giving Encouragement
                                    for that Purpose.
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>To this Head is annexed an Account of the Charters and Statutes,
                            under the Authority and Protection of which the African Trade first
                            began, and has continued to the present Time; and of the most 
                            material Proceedings that have been had in the House of Commons 
                            relative thereto.
                        </ab>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Second.</label> The evidence that has been obtained concerning the
                        Manner of carrying Slaves to the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, under the following Heads:
                        <list>
                            <item>The Size or Tonnage of the Ships.</item>
                            <item>The Manner of sitting up the Ships.</item>
                            <item>The Provisions taken on board.</item>
                            <item>The Medicines.</item>
                            <item>The Officers of the Ship, such as Masters, Surgeons, &amp;c.</item>
                            <item>The Number of Slaves usually carried per Ton from the different
                                Countries on the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>.
                            </item>
                            <item>The general Treatment of Slaves while on board, either in Health
                                or in Sickness.
                            </item>
                            <item>The Mortality of Slaves, and the Causes of it.</item>
                            <item>The Mortality of Seamen, and the Causes of it.</item>
                            <item>The Manner in which the Slaves are sold when landed in the 
                                <placeName>West Indies</placeName>.
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Third.</label>
                        <ab rend="nobreak">The Treatment of the Slaves in the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, and all
                            Circumstances relating thereto, arranged in the Manner stated in <ref type="goTo">Paper A.
                            in the Appendix</ref>, as will appear in that Part of the Report where the Evidence
                            on this Subject is given.
                        </ab>
                        <ab>To this Head is annexed a general View of the Laws respecting
                            <rs type="properAdjective">Negro</rs> Slaves in most of the Islands, followed by a Statement at large of
                            such of the said Laws as now subsist in each Island, arranged under different
                            Titles, as prepared by <persName>Mr. Reeves</persName>, Law Clerk to this Committee;
                            and there is also Information on this Subject in the Answers of some of
                            the Governors and Legislatures of the Islands to the Questions transmitted
                            to them by the Order of this Committee.
                        </ab>
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Fourth.</label> The Accounts hat have been called for to shew the 
                        extend ot the Trade in all its Branches, and the Number of the Free 
                        Inhabitants and Slaves of each of the Islands in the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, according
                        to a Plan stated in <ref type="goTo">Paper B. of the Appendix</ref>, so far as the Accounts
                        could be procured, as will appear in that Part of the Report where these
                        Accounts are given.
                    </item>
                    
                    <pb/>
                    <fw type="pageNum">6</fw>
                    
                    <item><label>Fifth.</label> All the Information that has been obtainedrelating to the
                        Advantages, which the <placeName>French West India Islands</placeName> are supposed at present
                        to enjoy over the <rs type="place">British Islands</rs>, and the Reasons and Circumstances on
                        which these superior Advantages appear to be funded, according to a 
                        Plan stated in <ref type="goTo">Paper C. in the Appendix</ref>.
                    </item>
                    <item><label>Sixth.</label> All the Information that has been obtained concerning the 
                        Extent of the Trade of other <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs> Nations to <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and the
                        Manner in which the same is carried on; and concerning the Treatment
                        of Slaves in the Foreign Islands or Colonies in America and the
                        <placeName>West Indies</placeName>; and concerning the Trade in Slaves carried on in the interior
                        Parts of that Country as connected therewith, either by <name>Europeans</name>,
                        or by the different People of <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Africa</placeName>.
                    </item>
                </list>
                <ab>All the Information and Matter collected by the Committe, has, in
                    pursuance of their Orders, been arranged under the foregoing Heads by
                    the Gentlement belonging to the Office for Trade; and the <distinct type="dialect" rend="italic">vivâ voce</distinct>
                    Evidence upon each Head is stated as nearly as possible in the very Words
                    in which the same was given. If it should be wished to see the whole
                    Evidence exactly as it was taken before the Committee, a Copy thereof
                    <distinct rend="italic">verbatim</distinct> is ready to be produced; but the Committee think it their
                    Duty to submit to your Majesty's Consideration, how far it may be
                    Proper to make publicall the Information received respecting the present
                    State of the Forts on the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>; and also some Circumstances
                    respecting the Share which your Majesty's Subjects have in the Foreign
                    Trade carried on upon the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName> for the Supply of Slaves to
                    the Foreign Islands and Settlements in <placeName>America</placeName> and the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>.
                    These, for reasons respecting the Public as well as Individuals, it may
                    not perhaps be so prudent to wholly divulge.
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
                <label>I.</label>
                <div type="section">
                    <ab>View of the <mcr rend="smallcaps">Evidence</mcr> that the Committee has
                        obtained from the present State of those Parts of 
                        <placeName rend="smallcaps">Africa</placeName> from whence <mcr rend="smallcaps">Slaves</mcr> have been
                        exported, taking each Country that lies upon the
                        Coast separately, beginning from the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName>,
                        and descending Southward to the last of the 
                        <rs type="properAdjective">European</rs> Settlements on the said Coast; with
                        such Information as has been obtained of the
                        interior Countries situated behind each of the said
                        Countries on the Coast respectively.
                    </ab>
                </div>
                
                <pb/>
                <!-- more pbs here -->
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head rend="italic">Government, Religion, Manners, and Customs.</head>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Senegal</placeName> and 
                            the Countries 
                            of <placeName>Walo</placeName> and 
                            <placeName>Cayor</placeName>, or 
                            <placeName>Demel</placeName>.
                        </head> 
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>John Barnes</persName>,
                             Esquire.</byline>
                        <p><persName>John Barnes</persName>, Esquire, was resident at <placeName>Senegal</placeName> near Eight Years, the last Three
                            Years as Governor, the first Five Years as a Merchant; has been at other Places on the
                            Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, but was never in the Service of the <orgName>African Company</orgName> upon any toher Part
                            of the Coast. The Nature of his Commerce upon the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName> was chiefly the gumm
                            Trade.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Countries immediately round <placeName>Senegal</placeName> are the Country of <placeName>Walo</placeName>, and the Country of
                            <placeName>Cayor</placeName> or <placeName>Demel</placeName>; the Nature of the Government in these Countries (which are of considerable
                            Extent) is Monarchy, absolute in some Respects, but limited in others, and hereditary in the 
                            Female Line. <!-- interesting things about gender? -->
                        </p>
                        <p>As to the Religion of these Countries, great Part of the Inhabitants are <name>Mahometans</name>, but
                            very imperfect. The Government is greatly under the Influence and Countroul of the Moorish
                            Tribes inhabiting the Desert on the North Side of the River; this Desert extends from the
                            North Side of the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName> to the Southern Declivity of <placeName>Mount Atlas</placeName>. The Extent is
                            about Ten Degrees from North to South, and the Borders of it to the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName> or
                            <placeName>Mount Atlas</placeName> are alone inhabited.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Goree</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, and
                            Countries Adjoining.
                        </head>    
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>Mr.
                            Dalrymple</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Hught Dalrymple</persName>, Esquire, served as First Lieutenant of Grenadiers in the <persName>Prince 
                            of Wales's</persName> or 75th Regiment, at the Reduction of <placeName>Goree</placeName> in <date when="1779">1779</date>; remained on that Part of
                            the Coast from the Beginning of May to the End of September or the Beginning of October in
                            the same Year, and made frequent Excuresions to the adjacent Continent (from whence the
                            <placeName>Island of Goree</placeName> is distant only Two or Three Miles) for several Leagues inland as well as along
                            Shore on both Sides of <placeName>Cape Verd</placeName>.
                        </p>
                        <p>This Country is under one Government; the Nature of the Government is monarchical
                            but of a very uncertain Kind; someties very arbitary and at others not so.
                        </p>
                        <p>The better Sort of People are the <name>Mahometans</name>; the common People have all Sorts of
                            Superstition; they in general worship Trees.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection"> 
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Goree</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, and
                            Countries Adjoining.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>Mr. Poplett</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Thomas Poplett</persName>, Esquire, an Officer in the <orgName><rs type="properAdjective">African</rs> Corps</orgName>, was at <placeName>Goree</placeName> and
                            <placeName>Gambia</placeName> near Four Years, from <date from="1779" to="1783">1779 to 1783</date>: He has been up the <placeName>River Gambia</placeName> to the
                            Distance of 300 or 400 Miles; but never was up the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName>; had no Concern in
                            Trade himself, but had Opportunities of seeing the Manner in which it was carried on.
                        </p>
                        <p><persName>Mr. Poplett</persName> being asked, If he knew any Thing of the Nature of Government in these
                            Countries, gave the following account:
                        </p>
                        <quote> <!-- NOTE: I am assuming this is a quote because of context, but there is no rendition to indicate such. Should discuss at a meeting. -->
                            <p>The Nature of the Government of these Countries, viz. the Kingdom of <placeName>Demel</placeName>, <placeName>Tin</placeName>,
                                <placeName>Barbessin</placeName>, and <placeName>Barra</placeName>, on the North Side of the <placeName>River Gambia</placeName> (which Countries run from
                                the <placeName>River Senegal</placeName> to the <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, and extend upwards of 200 miles) are all absolute
                                Monarchies, and are in fact governed more by the Caprice of the Monarch, than by any 
                                fixed System of Government; they have a council, consisting of the Alcaide or Governor,
                                the Gerouff or Mayor, the Marabou or Priest, and some of the Elders of the Village, the
                                whole Council being from Seven to Nine in Number; These consult and advise the King,
                                but he is not obliged to follow their Advice, nor does he ever do so, unless it consists with his
                                own Opinion or Interest, or that he apprehends they will have Force sufficient to resist him,
                                which they frequently do.
                            </p>
                            <p>To furnish the Revenues of these Kingdoms, every Village pays a regular Custom to the
                                King, consisting of Two Parts; the one annual, which is fixed by the King; the other, in
                                proportion to the Trade of the Ships.
                            </p>
                            <p>This Revenue or Custom is paid in Slaves, Powder, Shot, Brandy, Tobacco, and other
                                Merchandize brought from <placeName>Europe</placeName>. When this Custom is paid regularly, the King
                                first gives Notice to pay it, and if not then paid within a certain Time, he comes down with
                                
                                <pb/>
                                
                                Force and <distinct rend="italic">breaks the Village</distinct>; that is, he takes a great Number of Inhabitants Prisoners,
                                whom he detains for some Time as Pledges: If the Duties are paid, he restores the Prisoners;
                                if not, they are sold for Slaves. The Kings <emph>never</emph> break a Village without some such
                                Pretence; they are understood to be Masters of the Lives of their Subjects; but they use
                                this Power with very great Lenity; only when any of their Subjects are represented by the
                                Alcaide, or Chief of the Village, to be incorrigible, the King makes no Scruple of cutting
                                off their Heads without any Form of Trial.
                            </p>
                            <p>The People upon the Coast are wholly Mahometans; next to them, internally, there is
                                a Country containing a People called the Sierrieurs, who believe in a Supreme Being, and 
                                testify such Belief by shewing great Marks of Joy and Gratitude on occasion of any Behefits
                                received: they have no Idols, nor any Form of Worship; their principal Tenet is, that
                                they are to be happy in this World, and they endeavour to make themselves so, by every Species
                                of licentious Enjoyment, which they even pursue under Allfiction. The Countries beyond
                                these are chiefly Pagan. The Country of the Sierrieurs is more populous, in proportion to
                                its Extent, than the Mahometan Countries; the Sierrieurs are governed by a Number of
                                independent Chiefs, but they have no Kings. These People are Wanderers, like the Moors,
                                but they wander only within the Limits of their own Country.
                            </p>
                            <p>The Language of these Counties (except the Sierrieurs) is what is called Wolloff; and it 
                                is written in the <rs type="properAdjective">Arabic</rs> Character.
                            </p>
                            <p>The Black <name>Mahometans</name> upon the Coast are strong and robust, very handsome and
                                remarkably tall; they have woolly Heads, acquiline noses, and thin Lips.
                            </p>
                            <p>The Barras are short and think, with thick Lips, flat Noses, and wooly Heads: They
                                speak the Mundingo Language.
                            </p>
                            <p>The Sierrieurs have Noses quite flat, they think it a Beauty, and press down the Noses of
                                their Children accordingly; they are wooly-headed, strong, short and thinck, and their Faces
                                are tattood; they are fond of War, and are very artful People.
                            </p>
                            <p>The Wolloffs are a sensible, hospitable, and civil People, but jealous and vindictive.</p>
                            <p>The People of Tin are serious in their Disposition, much oppressed by their King, and 
                                naturally jealous and vindictive.
                            </p>
                            <p>The Barbessins and the Barras are an artful People, much accustomed to Chicanery in
                                Trade, and perfidious in their Dealings; they are lively, jealous, and vindictive.
                            </p>
                            <p>The People in general are very indolent; the Men do nothing but smoke, shoot, and fish;
                                the Women do all the Work in the Field, as well as of the House. Every Man is allowed
                                to take as many Wives as he pleases, if he can satisfly the Marabou or Priest that he is
                                able to maintain them. The Wives are in general Slaves to the Husbands, and work very
                                hard.
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Goree</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>the River
                            Gambia</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>Captain 
                            Hills</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>John Hills</persName>, Esquire, Captain in the Navy, commanded his Majesty's Sloop <ecda:shipName>Zephyr</ecda:shipName>
                            at <placeName>Goree</placeName>, and in the <placeName>River Gambia</placeName>, in the latter End of the Year <date when="1781">1781</date> and the Beginning
                            of 1782; was upon these Stations about Five Months in the whole.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Nature of the Government, as far as <persName>Captain Hills</persName> could judge, is most despotic, as
                            the King of <placeName>Demel</placeName> seemed to have a Power of Making his Subjects Slaves and selling them.
                            The Religion of this Part of the Coast is in general Mahometan.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>River 
                            Gambia</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>.
                        </head>        
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>Mr. Harry
                            Gandy</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Mr. Harry Gandy</persName>, one of the People calling themselves <name>Quakers</name>, lived nearly Thirty
                            Years in the <placeName>West Indies</placeName>, in the Danish Islands, and made Two Voyages to the Coast of 
                            <placeName>Africa</placeName> in the Years <date when="1758">1758</date> and <date when="1762">1762</date>, as Master of a Vessel; went to the <placeName>River Gambia</placeName> and
                            to <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>; has been more than 200 miles up the <placeName>River Gambia</placeName>; but not above 30
                            Miles up the <placeName>River Sierra Leone</placeName>.
                        </p>
                        <p><persName>Mr. Gandy</persName> can give no Account of the Government of these Countries; the Religion is
                            <name>Mahometanism</name>.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>River
                            Gambia</placeName>.
                        </head>   
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>Captain
                            Heatley</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Captain Heatley</persName> has been concerned in the <rs type="properAdjective">African</rs> Trade from the Year <date when="1763">1763</date> to
                            the last Year, was employed as Captain in that Trade on his ownAccount and for other People;
                            remained Five Years at one Time, and Three Years at another, on the <placeName>River Gambia</placeName>,
                            and was 230 Leagues up the River. He spoke the Mundingo Language, which is the general
                            Language of the Country. The Motive that induced him to go so far up the River
                            was to trade for Slaves, and for Ivory and Wax occasionally.
                        </p>
                        
                        <pb/>
                        
                        <p>The <placeName>River Gambia</placeName> may be navigated in Vessels that draw Ten Feet Water; that is, in
                            Vessels from 70 to 150 Tons: The Tide flows as far as 230 Leagues, or perhaps 320 Leagues
                            in dry Seasons,but not in the rainy Seasons: And in the Part of its Course which he speaks
                            of, passes through a great number of Kingdoms and Governments.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Nature of the Governments on each Side the River is so various, that he knows not
                            how to give an Account of them, but they are in general Monarchies with Powers variously
                            limited. The Sovereigns have Princes under them, who frequentlyact very independently
                            of the Sovereigns.
                        </p>
                        <p>Upon the Entrance at about Ten Leagues up the River, Vessels are called upon to pay
                            Custom to the King of Barra, which amounts in proportion to the Tonnage of the Vessel;
                            110 Leagues up the River at <placeName>Yanamaroo</placeName>, which is a trading Place, another Custom is paid,
                            and as the Ships pass through different Kingdoms in going up the River, if they trade, they 
                            pay Custom at them all.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Traders are in general <name>Mahometans</name>; but the Kings, Princes, and People are <name>Pagans</name>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Senegal</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, and
                            other Parts of
                            the Coast, to
                            <placeName>Prampram</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>Sir George
                            Yonge</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Sir George Yonge</persName> has been on the Coast of <placeName>Africa</placeName> Four several Times, between the
                            Years <date corresp="1767">1767</date>, <date when="1768">1768</date>, and <date when="1772">1772</date>, as well as he recollects; in the first Two Voyages he served
                            as a Lieutenant, in the last Two as Captain of the <ecda:shipName>Weazle</ecda:shipName>, under <persName>Captain Fielding</persName> and
                            <persName>Captain Collingwood</persName>.
                        </p>
                        <p>In Two Voyages, he was at <placeName>Senegal</placeName>, and remained Three Weeks on Shore with <persName>Governor
                            O'Hara</persName>; from thence, he went to <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, where he remained a short Time;
                            from <placeName>Gambia</placeName> to <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName> for Refreshments, and from thence to <placeName>Cape Appollonia</placeName>, and
                            most of the Forts upon the Gold Coast, the lowest Part of which was Prampram in Latitude
                            3, or thereabouts.
                        </p>
                        <p>Speaking of the several Governments on these Parts of the Coast, <persName>Sir George Yonge</persName>
                            informed of the Committee, that the King of <placeName>Bursilam</placeName> at <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, is a very powerful Monarch
                            and has very extensive Dominions. The greatest Part of the Coast, however where <persName>Sir
                            George Yonge</persName> was, is divided into petty States, but all the Sovereigns are absolute, and have
                            Power of Life and Death; they consider their Subjects as Slaves, and treat them accordingly.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Rivers Susa</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Sangarea</placeName>, 
                            <placeName>Dembia</placeName>, <placeName>Rio
                            Pongeos</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-outside"><persName>Mr. Thomas
                            Eldrid</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Mr. Thomas Eldrid</persName>, a Native of <placeName>Rhode Island</placeName>, has been employed in the 
                            Merchants Service between Three and Four Years as Second and Chief Mate of an <rs type="properAdjective">African</rs> Ship,
                            was upon the Slaving Trade in the Year <date when="1765">1765</date>, <date when="1766">1766</date>, <date when="1767">1767</date>, and <date when="1768">1768</date>, from <placeName>Senegal</placeName> down 
                            to <placeName>Ammanboe</placeName>; left the Trade because he did not like it, conceiving it to be unlawful, and
                            has never been to <placeName>Africa</placeName> since the Year <date when="1768">1768</date>.
                        </p>
                        <p><persName>Mr. Eldrid</persName> was on Shore about Four of Five Months in the whole of the Time he was on 
                            the Coast, but he never lived on Shore for more than Three or Four Nights at a Time; was up
                            the <placeName>Rivers Susa</placeName>, <placeName>Sangarea</placeName>, <placeName>Dembia</placeName>, <placeName>Rio Pongoes</placeName>, and <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>, in Boats, for near a
                            Twelvemonth, but never had occasion to observe any Thing very particularly of the Government
                            of these Countries. If any Dispute or <distinct rend="italic">Palavers</distinct> arose between Two or more Persons,
                            they called a Council of the head Men, where Persons were tried: He has frequently been
                            at those Trials, and understood the <rs type="properAdjective">Susa</rs> Language, which Country is between <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>
                            and <placeName>Gambia</placeName>.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Sentence was pronounced by the King, with the Advice of the head Men; and the
                            Punishment was, sometimes to be sold as Slaves, sometimes to get a Slave in their room.
                            The Crimes for which these People were in general accused and tried, were Adultery the
                            greater Part, and some for Theft.
                        </p>
                        <p><persName>Mr. Eldrid</persName> knows nothing of the Nature of the general Government of these Countries,
                            but does not believe they have any regular Form of Government.
                        </p>
                        <p>The People in general ar <name>Pagans</name>; they make their own Fetiches or Idols. They belive,
                            however, that there is an invisible God. As far as <persName>Mr. Eldrid</persName> knows of the Coast, he does
                            not believe they ever make human Sacrifices, but he knows nothing of the interior
                            Country.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Isles De Los</placeName>,
                            and <placeName>River
                            Kissey</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-outside">
                            <persName>James Penny</persName>,
                            Esquire.</byline>
                        <p><persName>James Penny</persName>, Esq. African Merchant, and one of the Gentlemen delegated from
                            <placeName>Liverpool</placeName> on account of the African and the West India Trade, as far as that Town is
                            concerned.
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Penny commanded a Ship in the African Trade, was in the Trade Eighteen Years,
                            and made Eleven Voyages as a Captain, and Two as First and Second Mate; went Five
                            
                            <pb/>
                            
                            Voyages to Bonny, Four to Congo and Angola, and the rest to the Windward Coast: Mr. Penny
                            resided in the Isles de Los and the River Kissey on the Windward Coast about Two Years,
                            from 1768 to 1770, as Factor, and quitted the Trade in 1784.
                        </p>
                        <p>In the Parts opposite to the Isles de Los, and the Neighbourhood to the Northward
                            of <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>, where Mr. Penny has been, the Country is divided into a Number of petty
                            States, ruled by Kings or head Men, whose Districts are very small. The Power of these 
                            Kings or head Men is not absolute and arbitrary; and they generally call a Council consisting of
                            head Men, who are Relations of the Princes, in which all Matters, civil or military, are
                            decided. The religious Institutions of these petty States are principally Pagan; there
                            are some Mahometans, and on the Northern Rivers a few black Christians, made such by 
                            the Portuguese when they were established among them.
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Penny being aksed, Whether the Black Cristians, or the Mahometans, make any Converts?
                            replied, the Mahometans make a great many by force: There is a large warlike
                            Mahometan Country to the North-east of Sierra Leone, called Fula, whose Inhabitants are
                            descended from Arabs; though of a darker colour, they have Arab Features. The Poers
                            of this Country is employed in making Converts to Mahometanism; they have made a great
                            Progress in converting the People of the Susa Country, which is a Part of the Coast. The
                            Princes on the Rivers Kissey and Malachurry, which are also a Part of this Coast, are Tributaries
                            to the Fula King;  and in thes Two last Countries great Progress has been made in
                            Mahometansim, and is still making. The Black Christians do not attempt to make any
                            Converts; they are an obscure Sort of People, and mix Paganism with the Christian Religion.
                            The King of Sierra Leone sent on of his Sons in 1769 to the Fula Country to learn
                            Mahometanism, and another to Lancaster to learn the Christian Relgion; the latter turned out very
                            profligate. Mr. Penny has seen in that Country several Arabian Teachers come down with
                            Transcripts from the Khoran, to whom they pay great Respect. These Men are sometimes
                            employed in instructing the Youth of the Country in the Arabic Language and in the Mahometan 
                            Religion, and with great Success, and they are in general devout; but notwithstanding
                            their Devotion, the Europeans do not find either their Lives or Properties so safe in the
                            Mahometan Towns as in those where Paganism prevails. The Pagans are humble and submissive;
                            the Mahometans are proud and insolent.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head>
                            <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-inside">
                            <persName>Mr. John
                            Matthews</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Mr. John Mathews</persName> (who was added afterwards to the Delegates from the Town of
                            <placeName>Liverpool</placeName>) is a Lieutenant in the Navy, and has been concerned in the Trade to <placeName>Africa</placeName>, at
                            Sierra Leone which is a Part of the Windward Coast; and was resident there, as Agent for a 
                            Merchant in the City of London, Two Years and upwards: He carried on the Trade for him.
                            and not upon his own Account.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Country upon the Windward Coast is formed into a Number of little Independent States:
                            the Governors are chosen by the People, and there is one head Governor to each of these 
                            States; their Power is not absolute, but on the contrary extremely limited.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Natives are Pagans, but there are also a great Number of Mahometans. They have
                            so fixed and Object of Worship, but a great Number of Amulets, which they call Gregories: they
                            believe in a God; and Mr. Mathes concludes, from the Manner of burying their Dead, they
                            have some Notion of a future State, for they bury in the Ground, and hang round the Grave
                            those Things of which the deceased in his Lifetime was most fond.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-outside">
                            <placeName>Sherbo
                            River</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline><persName>Reverend
                            Mr. Newton</persName>.</byline>
                        <p>The Reverend John Newton, Rector of St. Mary Wolnoth, lived in Africa, some
                            Years ago, during Eighteen Moths, and left it in the Year 1748; has since commanded a
                            Ship in the African Trade, for Three Voyages; but has seen nothing of Africa since the Year
                            1754.
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Newton has been about Fifty Miles up the Country, through the Woods on the Sherbro
                            River. Being asked if the Natives have any Civil Government?—said—<said rend="prequotes" xml:id="s001" next="#s002">The Government of
                            the Purrah is excellent Government; by their Civil Institutions they may sell their Slaves,
                            but must not draw Blood from them.</said>
                        </p>
                        <said xml:id="s002" prev="#s001">
                            <p>They have some Religious Institutions that answer to our old Druids. The Purrah is a Sort of
                                High Priest.
                            </p>
                            <p>They have Laws respecting Property, and the Convicts for Theft lose their Liberty.</p>
                        </said>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-inside">
                            <placeName>Windward
                            Coast</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-inside">
                            <persName>Mr.
                            Norris</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Robert Norris</persName>, Esq. Carolina Merchant, another of the Delegates from Liverpool.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Norris was employed as Captain of a Vessel in the Slave Trade, in Five Voyages, and is
                            particularly acquainted with the Windward and Gold Coast;—and being asked, what is the
                            
                            <pb/>
                            
                            Nature of the Government on these Parts of the Coast, replied—There are various Governments
                            in that comprehensive Tract, from the most absolute Monarchy, to others less oppressive to the
                            Subjects: Some are Monarchies, some Republics. He speaks of a Tract of Country extending
                            about 1500 Miles upon the Coast, and upon the Gold Coast 130 Miles inland from Whyday.
                            Mr. Norris is not certain as to the Number of Miles; but the Extend he is able to speak of is,
                            from Sierra Leone River to Benin.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Country on the Windward Coast, from Cape Mount to Cape Palmas, is divided into
                            Petty States and Governments, and governed by the old Men in each Village.
                        </p>
                        <p>The People are Pagans; they wear Tygers Teeth, and different Amulets, suspended on their
                            Necks, for which they have a religious Veneration.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head rend="place-inside">
                            <placeName>Windward
                            Coast</placeName>.
                        </head>
                        <byline rend="place-inside">
                            <persName>Mr.
                            Falconbridge</persName>.</byline>
                        <p><persName>Mr. Alexander Falconbridge</persName> made Give Yoages to the Coast of Africa, as
                            Surgeon to a British Slave Ship. The first Voyage was to the Windward or Grain Coast, and
                            Angola: In this Voyage he was taken by a French Man of War. The second Voyage was to
                            the Windward Cost, when he was driven off the Coast by a French Man of War, and went to
                            Angola. The two last Voyages were to Bonny.
                        </p>
                        <p>The Government on the Windward Coast is a Sort of Aristocracy.</p>
                        <p>The Gold Coast is divided into small States in general.—Mr. Norris being asked, Whether
                            the People of this country enjoy any Protection from any Civil Rights they have?—Replied—
                            <said>We must distinguish the Countries: In the Fantyn Nation</said> (by which he meant, from Caoe
                            Three Points to Accra), <said>which includes various States, of which the Fantyn is the chief, and
                            whose Manners and Governments are nearly similar, about five Days Journey inland, where 
                            the Europeans have been longest settled, and possess the greates Number of Forts, Civilization
                            has improved beyond any thing he has discovered in any other Country of Africa, and the
                            People have Civil Rights arising from traditionary Laws and Customs; but, even in this
                            Coutnry, much remains to be done towards Civilization. The Bussou and Craba, the confidential
                            Man and favourate Woman, of every Person of Distinction are usually put to Death
                            and interred him.: The imputed Crime of Witchcraft is still believed there, and is
                            punished with Transportation.</said>—By Transportation, Mr. Norris means, selling them to the White
                            Traders, which is represented in this Nation as the greatest Evil that can befal them, in order
                            to deter them from Crimes. The superior State of Civilization in this Country, Mr. Norris
                            imputes to their Intercourse with Europeans; and added—Report says, that formerly a much
                            greater Number were but to Death, and interred with their deceased Lords.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paganism is universal.—By Paganism, Mr. Norris means, the Worship of those Objects which
                            strike the Senses.—At Whyday, a Snake is the principal Object of their Worship; and, besides
                            this, Trees, Caversn, and Amulets round their Necks which are furnished by their Priests.
                            At Cape Coast, the Rocks on which the Fort is built is their Tutelar Deity. A Tyger is the
                            immediate Object of the King of Dahomey's Worship.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
