<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Obi;or, The history of Threefingered Jack.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Worcester: Printed by <persName>Isaiah Thomas</persName>, Jun. Sold by him, and
                    by <name>Thomas&amp;Whipple</name>, <placeName>Newburyport</placeName>.
                        <date>1804</date>.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>In a Series of Letters from a resident in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> to his
                    friend in <placeName>England</placeName></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <ecda:hyperDiv>
            <ecda:notes>
                <note xml:id="n001" target="#a001">For your information I shall subjoin notes,
                    explanatory of such African words as may occur.—Mansa a King</note>
                <note xml:id="n002" target="#a002">A watering place where shepherds kept their
                    cattle</note>
                <note xml:id="n003" target="#a003">An unconverted native, one who drinks strong
                    liquors, a drunkard</note>
                <note xml:id="n004" target="#a004">A dish prepared from boiled corn</note>
                <note xml:id="n005" target="#a005">Vegetable butter</note>
                <note xml:id="n006" target="#a006">A skin for containing water</note>
                <note xml:id="n007" target="#a007">A sort of an apartment purposely for
                    strangers</note>
                <note xml:id="n008" target="#a008">Revenge is supposed by several nations of Africa,
                    particularly the Feloops, to be a god who presides at their birth, and gifts
                    them with power, if the father is virtuous and injured; for then, the son is
                    bound to revenge</note>
                <note xml:id="n009" target="#a009">An amulet or charm, a scrap of paper written on
                    by a Mahomedan Priest, is enclosed in a horn, and sold at a high price to the
                    natives. A Bushreen, (Mussulman, or Kafir) a pagan native, believe in the
                    virtues of the Saphie, though they deny the religion.</note>
                <note xml:id="n010" target="#a010">A caravan of slaves, from the interior of the
                    country.</note>
                <note xml:id="n011" target="#a011">Free black merchants, who trade in slaves, and
                    with a small troop, well armed, march to the interior, either to purchase
                    prisoners of war, or, if they fail in this, lay in ambush and take inhabitants
                    from their houses when asleep. Wars in Africa are much encouraged by the
                    Europeans, and particularly the Duth and English, and the number of slaves
                    annually exported, are said to exceed 150,000 of those miserable people.</note>
                <note xml:id="n012" target="#a012">It was the custom, though now, we believe, it is
                    altered, for a planter to purchase one or two lots of slaves, and so round
                    according to the bulk of the vessel and demand for slaves: The lot being made,
                    the purchaser was obliged to abide by his chance traffic.</note>
                <note xml:id="a013" corresp="#n013">It is the general belief of African slaves that,
                    when they die, they return to their own country.</note>
            </ecda:notes>
        </ecda:hyperDiv>
        <front>
            <titleBlock>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Obi;or, The history of Threefingered Jack</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
            </titleBlock>
            <div type="prefatory">
                <lg>
                    <l>Oh! ye who at your ease</l>
                    <l>Sip the blood sweetened beverage! thoughts like these</l>
                    <l>Haply ye scorn: I thank thee, gracious God!</l>
                    <l>That I do feel upon my cheek the glow</l>
                    <l>Of indignation, when beneath the rod</l>
                    <l>A sable brother writhes in silent woe.......<persName>Southey</persName>.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Hear him! ye Senates! hear this truth sublime,</l>
                    <l>He who allows oppression shares the crime.....<persName>Darwin</persName></l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prefatory">
                <head>Advertisement.</head>
                <p>I have published these letters, which accidentally fell into my hands, with a
                    view to commemorate the name of <persName>Jack</persName>, and place upon the
                    list of heroes, one who, had he shone in a higher sphere, would have proved as
                    bright a luminary as ever graced the Roman annals, or ever boldly asserted the
                    rights of a Briton. His cause was great and noble, for to private wrongs he
                    added the liberty of his countrymen, and stood alone a bold and daring defender
                    of the Rights of Man. To him who shall applaud <persName>Jack</persName> through
                    the varied scenes of his life; to him, whose heart shall sympathize in his
                    misfortunes, who shall smile upon his deeds, at the same time that he laments
                    their cause, I dedicate the following pages. <persName>W.E.J</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <pb/>
            <head>Obi, Or, The History of Threefingered Jack</head>
            <div type="letter">
                <head>
                    <emph rend="caps">Letter I.</emph>
                </head>
                <opener><salute>Dear <persName>Charles</persName></salute>,
                            <dateline><placeName>Jamaica</placeName></dateline>.</opener>
                <p>A whole week has your letter been lying open on my desk, ready for me to answer—a
                    whole week have the above two words been written, as you may perceive by the
                    difference in the shade of the ink and the cutting of my pen; for, three times
                    has the dried standish been replenished, and twenty times, at least, have I
                    dipped into it, sometimes with a new pen, sometimes with a mended one—and still
                    at this moment am I at a loss what to say to you in reply to your queries.</p>
                <p>Now, you will think that, because I have written the above long sentence, my mind
                    is wholly and exclusively engrossed by your business, and that I shall be able
                    to go on in a regular steady way; but I tell you, <persName>Charles</persName>,
                    it is no such thing; for at the end of that very sentence, I stopped a full
                    hour, unable to proceed—and now again do I stop short.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>Try what I may, it will not do—but what is the matter? you will say.
                        <persName>Jack</persName>!!! and his cursed three fingers!!!</p>
                <p>I'll tell you what, <persName>Charles</persName>—I have just read your letter for
                    the hundred and first time, and upoin my soul, cannot see that the business it
                    is about is of such great importance; so, with or without your leave, I shall
                    put off answering it, until I have eased myself of my insufferable burthen, by
                    dispatching <persName>Jack</persName>, his three fingers, and his
                        <name>Obi</name>, and all that belongs to him; for, positively, I can think
                    of nothing else.</p>
                <p>And so it is with every body in the Island; go wherever I will the name of
                        <persName>Jack</persName> is perpetually buzzed in my ears. If I meet a
                    friend in the street, it is no longer "<said>How d'ye do</said>?" but
                        "<said>Well, what news of <persName>Jack</persName></said>?" if any of my
                    neighbors, calling his servant, says,; "<said><persName>Jack</persName>, come
                        here</said>," I start and stare about, in expectation of seeing the
                    threefingered one make his appearance. Nay, there is not a thing called
                        <persName>Jack</persName>, whether a smokejack, a boot jack, or any other
                    jack, but acts as a spell upon my senses and sets me on the fret at the bare
                    mention of it. By heavens! it is too much, and I wish...</p>
                <p>Nay, I do not—I cannot find in my heart to form the same wish that most of the
                    inhab—</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>itants here express every day. Jck is a noble fellow, and in spite of every cruel
                    hard hearted planter, I shall repeat the same to the last hour of my life.
                            "<said><persName>Jack</persName> is a Negro</said>," say they.
                            "<said><persName>Jack</persName> is a Man</said>," say I.</p>
                <p>—"<said>He is a slave</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>Man cannot be a slave to Man</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>He is my property</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>How did you acquire that property</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>By paying for it</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>Paying! Paying whom</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>Him who brought him from Africa</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>How did he get possession of him</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>He caught him there</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>Caught! what? Like a wild beast</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>No, but he contrived means to convey him into his ship</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>Contrived! Then he brought him without his consent</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>Very likely</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>And what has become of that robber</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>Robber! He is a very respectable man, who has left off trade, has married
                        the daughter of a rich planter, and now lives very comfortably, after the
                        fatigues of an industrious life</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>What! Do they hang a poor hard-laboring man, who, driven by despair at
                        the sight of his numerous family ready to starve</said></p>
                <pb/>
                <p><said>for want of a bit of bread, takes advantage of a dark night, goes on the
                        highway and frightens teh traveller out of a few pieces of gold and shall a
                        daring ruffian, who is openly guilty of a crime more heinous in its nature
                        and baneful in its effects, get respected by every body and pass his days in
                        the peaceable enjoyment of riches acquired by such infamous
                    means</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>I don't understand you. I never heard that the traffic was infamous. Is
                        it not authorised by all the nations of Europe, Asia and America? Have not
                        regulations been made concerning it by all governments</said>?"</p>
                <p>—"<said>Very true, but that does not make it more honorable. Prostitution is
                        authorised, yes, for it is more than tolerated, by governments, many of
                        which have also made regulations concerning it, but that does make it less
                        infamous</said>."</p>
                <p>—"<said>Nay, you are going too far, and this is widely different</said>.</p>
                <p>—"<said>Different !—By heavens ! you will drive me mad</said>."</p>

                <p>And such, my dear <persName>Charles</persName>, is the daily altercation I have
                    with the greatest part of the planters here, and what you have just read is a
                    specimen of the various arguments brought on both sides of the question. As I
                    know your sentiments upon the subject, I shall close</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>it here and proceed to my narrative about <persName>threefingered
                    Jack</persName>, and as I have made it my business to collect every particular
                    relative to him, I believe I shall have it in my power to give you a
                    circumstantial account of all his actions. In fact, what I am now going to write
                    is nothing more than a copy of what I had sometime ago begun to put into a
                    regular story, out of several memoranda collected at different times. So without
                    lengthening this preamble, I thus begin:</p>
                <p><persName>Amri</persName> was a beautiful slave, the property of <persName>Mr.
                        Mornton</persName>, of <placeName>Maroons Town</placeName>. She was
                    sanguinary in her temper; for, misfortunre, or rather cruelty, had perverted a
                    heart naturally inclined to virtue. She was torn from the arms of her husband,
                    her family and friends, while in the mayday of her life, from her native
                        <placeName>Africa</placeName></p>
                <p>She had vowed to curse <ecda:persGroup>the European race</ecda:persGroup> for
                    ever; and had a son, in whose breast she never failed to nurture the baneful
                    passion of revenge</p>
                <p>She taught him to despise his groaning companions, complaining under their labor,
                    meanly submitting to the christian whip, and then pusillanimously venting their
                    griefs in half suprressed sighs</p>
                <pb/>
                <p><persName>Jack</persName> had a soul, even in infancy, superior to such whining;
                    he complained not of the daily labor heaped upon him, but of the tardiness of
                    time.</p>
                <p>Each night, when the grand luminator of the world hid his rays within the deep,
                    he threw himself on his knees, and prayed the great God of his country to ripen
                    him to manhood, that he might shake off the yoke that pressed heavy upon him,
                    and revenge the cause of his country and his parents. His youthful fiery soul
                    led him to imagine himself the destroyer of all <placeName>Europe</placeName>;
                    he saw in the warlike picture his fancy drew, the course he was to fllow, and
                    the transport of his heart was often visible by the uncommon hauteur of his
                    manners. When assured of revenge, he would grin with a smile of malice,
                    transparent on his cheek, at the overseer, while the merciless whip was
                    lacerating his back.</p>
                <p>He was of the most manly growth, nearly seven feet in height, and amazingly
                    robust; bread up to hardihood, his limbs were well shapen and athletic; he could
                    endure the most laborious, toil and would with ease perform the office of any
                    two negores within the planation. His face was rather long; his eyes black and
                    fierce; his nose was not like the generality of blacks, squat and flat, but
                    rather aquiline, and</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>his skin remarkably clear. He discovered a great deal of expression in his
                    countenance, and a very look of reproach from him would strike terror to
                        <ecda:persGroup>his fellow slaves</ecda:persGroup>. He was now two and
                    twenty years of age, and every thing <rs type="person">his fond but revengeful
                        mother</rs> could wish him.</p>
                <p>Returning from his labor to the small hovel, where he and <rs type="person">his
                        mother</rs> dwelt, after a heavy day of toil, he threw himself weary on the
                    pallet of straw where he resposed. <persName>Amri</persName> arose and claspt
                    him in her arms.</p>
                <ecda:embSN><p>"<said><rs type="person">My son</rs></said>," cried she, "<said>Now
                            is the time arrived when you should contend for the rights of yourself
                            and <rs type="person">mother</rs>. Now is the time when you should
                            revenge my cause. You are arrived to maturity, and, to inspire you to
                            revenge my injuries, I will relate the misfortunes of my
                        life</said>."</p></ecda:embSN>
                <p>Dear Charles, so much of the narrative was imparted to me by a negro, well
                    acquainted with Amri, and I can assure you, for I have seen this threefingered
                    Jack, that he was every thing in soul and person requisite for the hero. Give me
                    now a short pause. Sketch the man you would wish—a bold and daring fellow, ready
                    to undertake any thing for the good of his country, inspired by a rooted
                    revenge, on the strongest foundation villainy can fabricate, and Jack's the man
                    to a point. I must break off. Adieu!</p>
                <pb/>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <head><hi rend="all caps">Letter II</hi>.</head>
                <head><hi rend="italics">The same to the same</hi>.</head>
                <opener><salute>Dear <persName>Charles</persName></salute>, .</opener>
                <p>I resume my pen, and commence with the narrative of <persName>Amri</persName>.
                    All impatience myself, I suspect you to feel as much. I set down her own words
                    as near as memory can trace—mind that.</p>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <head><hi rend="all caps">Makro and Amri, An African Tale</hi></head>
                        <quote rend="block">I am innocent of this blood, see ye to it</quote>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
                <ecda:embSN><p>"<rs type="person">My son</rs>, your country borders on the
                            <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, and its inhabitants are distinguished
                        from all others by the name of <rs type="properAdjective">Feloops</rs>.
                        Remember that the spirit of our nation is, Never to forget an injury, but to
                        ripen in our</p><pb/>
                    <p>breasts the seeds of hate for those who betray us. We are to transmit our
                        quarrels to our posterity, and it is incumbent on a son, from a sense of
                        filial obligation, to resent the injuries done to his parents.</p>
                    <p>"You are the only son of my womb, the only offspring of the loins of Makro,
                        and you shall be his avenger.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Feruarue</persName>, the beloved of his country, lived in a hut,
                        at whose base murmured the waters of <placeName>Gambia</placeName>. I was
                        his only daughter, and his sole delight. Makro's parents were deceased, and
                        his hut adjoined ours.—He was but two years my elder; I loved him, and he
                        was the great friend of my father, so that our nuptials were soon
                        solemnized, and I removed from my father's home to live with my dear
                            <persName>Makro</persName>.</p>
                    <p>"How blest were we, <rs type="person">my son</rs>! The God of our country
                        smiled upon our stores; our herbage grew beneath our eye, and our lawful
                        traffic with the vile Europeans, sanctioned by our virtuous <seg
                            xml:id="a001" corresp="#n001">Mansa</seg>, answered our most sanguine
                        expectations. Makro constantly attended the <seg xml:id="a002"
                            corresp="#n002">Korree</seg>, and our <ecda:fauna>cattle</ecda:fauna>
                        were as fine as any our nation boasted</p>
                    <p>"One terrible day, <rs type="person">my son</rs>, our God, we thought, seemed
                        angry with us. He withheld his beams; the thunder roared above, and the
                        tremendous lightning blighted the fruits of the earth. You were then but two
                        months old within my womb. All nature at that moment seemed at variance, and
                        the storm of rain drenched the Europeans' big ship; their sails were torn by
                        the storm, and we heard them fire their terrifying guns, which we afterwards
                        understood were signals of distress. Oh! what an hour was that! I stood at
                        our cabin door and saw one great swelling wave devour their ship, and they
                        were forever hurried from my sight. At that moment, with agonizing pity, I
                        caspt my hands together, and wept their fate.</p>
                    <p>"Yes, indeed, I did weep the fate of those, whom with thee I am born to
                        curse, such was <emph>then</emph> my generous unsuspecting nature. Well, the
                        storm abated in its fury, till, at last, the waters gained their original
                        calm, and the clouds above wore a more pleasing aspect.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Makro</persName>, as was customary, was at the Koree, and, wishing
                        to know if he was well, I paced the banks of Gambia. As I looked upon the
                        waters, I beheld floating to our shore a part of the ship rent in thousand
                        twain by the merciless tempest. Lying,</p><pb/>
                    <p>"to all appearance dead, on this fragment of the wreck, were two
                            <ecda:persGroup>Europeans</ecda:persGroup>, locked in each other's
                        embrace. They were both young—one was scarely fourteen. Imagine, <rs
                            type="person">my son</rs>, the emotions of a heart, ever ready to assist
                        the distrest, on beholding such a scene.—They were
                            <ecda:persGroup>Europeans</ecda:persGroup>, and all <rs type="place"
                            >Africa</rs> trembled at their name; they were my country's foes, but
                        they were fallen; they claimed my pity, and I assisted them as though they
                        had been my country's firmest friends—my heart could not view them in their
                        real light.</p>
                    <p>"I hastened to the water's brink, and fast the fragment proceeded towards me;
                        at length it struck upon the shore, and I gave them all my aid. <rs
                            type="person">The captain</rs> of the seadevoured vessel was soon
                        recovered, and we both assisted to lead his nearly drowned <rs type="person"
                            >boy</rs> to our cabin.</p>
                    <p>"I had got a small European bottle, with some brandy, which my
                            <persName>Makro</persName> took from the despised of our nation, a <seg
                            xml:id="a003" corresp="#n003">Sonakee</seg>. <persName>Captain
                            Harrop</persName>, for so was he called, smiled upon the bottle, and
                        giving some to his servant, he was soon recovered.</p>
                    <p>"My husband soon returned from the Koree, and entered our hut, while I was in
                        the kindly<pb/> office of renovating the drooping
                            <ecda:persGroup>Europeans</ecda:persGroup>; he started back on beholding
                        them, but I related the disastrous circumstance that called my mercy to
                        their aid, and he also pitied them.</p>
                    <p>"By that time, when the glorious sun witholds his beams which are canopied
                        over by the veil of night, they were both perfectly recovered.
                            <persName>Makro</persName> invited them to take some <seg xml:id="a004"
                            corresp="#n004">kous kous</seg>, of which they ate most hartily, and
                        much admired our <seg xml:id="a005" corresp="#n005">Shea Toulou</seg>, which
                            <persName>Makro</persName> placed plentifully before them. My <rs
                            type="person">son</rs>, noble was the blood that flowed in your father's
                        veins. He was generous and humane (in person thou art his model) of manly
                        growth, of a fierce and intrepid disposition, commanding reverence from his
                        countrymen, and dreaded by his country's foe. He was active and alert in
                        times of war; lionhearted, proud and generous, he would lead his men to
                        victory, and was adored the as greatest war captain of his country. In
                        peace, he was gentle as the lamb, candid in his heart, and constantly
                        exercised his time by a shepherd's employ.</p>
                    <p>"After our guests had eat and were much refreshed, <persName>Makro</persName>
                        bid them proceed to the European settlements on the Gambia, of</p><pb/>
                    <p>which there are many, for the vile practice of purchasing slaves. I filled
                        two <seg xml:id="a006" corresp="#n006">soffroos</seg> for them, but they
                        most earnestly entreated to rest the night with us, and Makro, after some
                        hesitation, consented to my preparing a temporary <seg xml:id="a007"
                            corresp="#n007">baloon</seg> for them. We all retured to our several
                        pallets, and the next day <persName>Captain Harrop</persName>, was attacked
                        by a violent fever. I attended him, and, indeed, I did as much as lay in my
                        power to relieve his anguish.</p>
                    <p>"Oh! my <rs type="person">son</rs>, I will pass over this part of my
                        narrative : The hated remembrance of what I did for those vile white men
                        rends my heart in twain. I sang him to his slumbers; I procured him a
                        cooling drink; I added to his pallet, softened it for his weak frame, and
                        cheered him in the hour of affliction. What was my reward? What was my
                        recompense? Chains! Chains! <rs type="person">my son</rs>, and lifeclosing
                        slavery. Here it thou God of Africa, hear it! <seg xml:id="a008"
                            corresp="#n008">revenge</seg>, nerve the arm of the son of
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, and lend him thy invincibly power; echo the
                        groans of his country in his ears, and inspire him with thy malice. <pb/> I
                        have food at heart, aided by thee, to rouse his lion soul from inactivity to
                        revengeful slaughter. Then reject not a distracted mother's prayer, but make
                        him all her care torn heart can wish!</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Captain Harrop</persName> recovered but slowly; he was wasted away
                        to a mere shadow, and leaning on my arm for the benefit of the pure air, he
                        would walk out and view our herbage.—"<said>Nature! nature!</said> would he
                        cry as he inspected our fertile fields, "<said>how profuse art thou, how
                            lavish of thy bounty!</said>"</p>
                    <p>During his stay with us, he had taught me sufficient of his language to
                        understand him, and I listened to what he said. I asked him in unaffected
                        ignorance, Who was nature? "<said>The great Creator</said>," answered he;
                            "<said>He to whom you owe your being</said>." I did not rightly
                        comprehend him, but he soon gave me to understand that I worshipped a false
                        god. I looked upon him with astonishment. He told me the glorious sun was
                        but a substance created by his God, who was the great father of all. He told
                        me of the enlivening power of the sun. "<said>I</said>," cried he,
                            "<said>feel its warmth in my heart; its splendor inspires me with an
                            active spirit to fulfil the duties of this life and enjoy society. You
                            yourself</said>," applying to me, "<said>feel the same influence; the
                            sun</said></p>
                    <pb/><p><said>cheers the herbage of the field, when drooping; it sheds its
                            enlivening rays, expands the opening leaf, which soon revels in
                            prosperity. So the charitable man spreads his kindly rays around,
                            revives the deprest, becomes a father to the orphan, a husband to the
                            widow; by him are the afflicted comforted, the enlightened, and the poor
                            relieved. Oh! Amri, a charitable man is the noblest work of
                        God."</said></p>
                    <p>"I was amazed to hear him speak; I thought him all virtue: How wretchedly was
                        I deceived! Indeed, for the moment, he staggered my relief that I was doing
                        right in worshipping as he said, the servant of the real God. He made me
                        remark the setting of the sun; I was charmed with what he said, and could
                        for ever have listened to him. "<said>Behold</said>," said he, "<said>how
                            complete are his works, and observe the gradual approach of night. The
                            descent of yon bright orb is not into the sea as your imagine; it goes
                            to illumine other parts of this vast globe, which are hidden from your
                            view. And now, behold, in proportion as its beams become more faint,
                            night is spreading her grey curtain over the sky. Acknowledge the wisdom
                            of the Creator here to be infinite, as the sudden transition from light
                            to dark would not only prove hurtful to the</said></p><pb/>
                    <p><said>sight of man, but baneful to his interest, and derange the uniformity
                            of creation.</said> "<said>if,</said>" continued he, "<said>you will
                            with me observe the dawn of day, you shall contemplate the rise of the
                            sun, which will prove a fund, not only of entertainment, but of
                            instruction</said></p>
                    <p>"I readily assented, and we returned to our cabin. <persName>Makro</persName>
                        was there already, and the <rs type="person">Captain's boy</rs> was
                        instructing him in his language.</p>
                    <p>"At the approach of morning, <persName>Captain Harrop</persName> tapped at my
                        pallet's head, and besought me to rise. I did, and accompanied by
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, we ascended a height where we could have an
                        uninterrupted view of the vast expanse around.</p>
                    <p>"The grey clouds, which, the evening before, cast a gloom on the verdure, now
                        were chased away by a vivid light, which, as it approached, grew more
                        enlivening. The drops of dew that rested on the plants sparkled like so many
                        pearls. I was wwrapped in wonder and delight, for never before did I know
                        how to discover those beauties which appeared to my astonished sight, and
                        which <persName>Makro</persName> viewed with increased pleasure.How
                        beautifully green did the vale beneath appear! how did my eye wander over
                        hills, mountains, forests</p><pb/>
                    <p>and meadows, that were watered by soft murmuring rivulets!</p>
                    <p>"The clouds were tinged and variegated with the sweetest colors; the light
                        insensibily increased, till the sun rising shot his first ray across the
                        horizon; <persName>Makro</persName> clasped his hands in delight, as he
                        beheld his slow appraoch.— The eastern sky was previously clothed with
                        purple, which, as the sun approached, gradually assumed a rosy tint, and
                        gilded the hemisphere with blushing gold.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Makro</persName> fell on his face, and embraced the earth in awful
                        reverence; I followed his example; our instructor lifted us from the ground,
                        we prest him to our bosoms, and returned to our cabin, adoring the wisdom of
                            <rs type="properAdjective">the European</rs>, and earnestly entreating
                        him to never leave us.</p>
                    <p>"He smiled; I thought it the smile of satisfaction and conset, and we heaped
                        blessings on him.</p>
                    <p>"I need not add, <rs type="person">my son</rs>, that we were happy; we
                        blessed the accident that cast him on our shore, and eagerly sought every
                        thing in our power to please him.</p>
                    <p>"Day followed day, and each brought something that endeared him to us the
                        more. He was gay, lively, and would often teach me the</p><pb/>
                    <p>songs of his country, at the same time commending my retentive memory.</p>
                    <p>"In short, two months soon elapsed in company of him who could so well
                        instruct us how to adore the works of the infinite Creator of all things,
                        and each day enliven our understandings by producing something new for us to
                        admire.</p>
                    <p>"Oh! could we think it possible that the man who daily habituated our ears to
                        tales of humanity could, while he grasped our hands in seeming friendly
                        warmth, have a scheme in his head to blast our prospect of future peace, we
                        who stood forward as his saviors! we could find no such deception in our own
                        countrymen, and were not sufficiently acquainted with the character of
                            <ecda:persGroup>the Europeans</ecda:persGroup>.</p>
                    <p>"Free from suspicion, we laid ourselves open to his cursed wiles, and become
                        the dupes of our own credulity.</p>
                    <p>"Rendered more rational, we found beauties in nature which our countrymen
                        could not discover; and <persName>Makro</persName> and myself would stroll
                        far from our habitation, to again behold those scenes which he had taught us
                        to delight in.</p>
                    <p>"One day, while reclining upon a hillock, we heard the sounds of voices at a
                        little distance from us. It was the two Europeans; and
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, not understanding their language so</p><pb/>
                    <p>well as myself, imposed on me a momentary silence, that he might listen to
                        what they said; not from curiosity, for no such desire actuated our breasts,
                        (then indeed we scarcely knew what it meant) but from the pure motive of
                        learning whether we could understand them with facility</p>
                    <p>"<persName>The captain</persName>'s voice we first distinguished; his words,
                            <rs type="person">my son</rs> are forever impressed upon my memory, and
                        I can with ease relate them.</p>
                    <p>"<said><persName>William</persName>,</said>" said he to <rs type="person">his
                            boy</rs>, "<said>I never can consent to be buried in this wild
                            uncultivated spot, lost to my friends and to the world; reflect that it
                            is for their own good, as much as for my benefit, Have I not enlightened
                            them, fertilized their minds, told them of the duties of this life, and
                            how to enjoy society? What were they, when first we set foot on their
                            shore? savages, dwelling with savages: I tell you,
                                <persName>William</persName>,....."</said></p>
                    <p>"<said>Sir,</said>" interrupted <rs type="person">the boy</rs>,"<said>have
                            you a heart? but no, I am wrong, you are only trying whether the heart
                            of your poor boy is softened by humanity. I am sure it is not, it cannot
                            be your intention; I must not, I will not believe it."</said></p>
                    <p>"<said>Peace fool,</said>" resumed <persName>the captain</persName>;
                            "<said>you never know me changeable in my determination</said>."</p><pb/>
                    <p>"He ceased; we soon understood he spoke of us, and that he was about to leave
                        our country. <persName>Makro</persName> looked at me; I saw the manly tear
                        upon his cheek; he sorrowed for the intended departure of
                            <ecda:persGroup>the Europeans</ecda:persGroup>, who had gained our love,
                        and he pressed me to his heart, the palpitation of which was almost too
                        strong for our nature to support.</p>
                    <p>"They continued—</p>
                    <p>"<said>It is most fortunate</said>," rejoined the captain; "<said>the arrival
                            of one of my own ships from <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>! it favors my
                            views, and tomorrow shall see us on board</said>."</p>
                    <p>"<said>They will send their boat for us to shore, in the morning</said>,"
                        answered <persName>William</persName>.</p>
                    <p>"<said>Till then, peace</said>," added <persName>Captain Harrop</persName>;
                            "<said>a close mouth is a good safeguard</said>."</p>
                    <p>"We were both too much affected to accost them, for we expected they should
                        reside with us for ever.</p>
                    <p>"<said>Ah!</said>" sighed Makro, "<said>my dear <persName>Amri</persName> our
                            expectations were unnatural; do <emph>we</emph> not love cour country?
                            Say, could we leave it, our family and our friends? Oh! no—perhaps in
                                <placeName>European plains</placeName>, he may have a wife, who
                            loves him dearly, and, <persName>Amri</persName></said>, I judge by
                        myself, I could not leave thee."</p>
                    <p>"This was sufficient; <persName>Makro</persName> silenced with</p><pb/>
                    <p>in my breast the upbraider that accused them of ingratitude.</p>
                    <p>"We returned home; they were there before us, and soon perceived in our
                        countenance an unusual dejection.</p>
                    <p>"<said>My worthy friend</said>," cried <persName>Captain Harrop</persName>,
                        catching my hand and wiping the tear from my cheek, "<said>are you not well?
                            say, what has befallen you? Why this dejection</said>?"</p>
                    <p>"I had not power to refrain uttering the cause of my grief, and replied, at
                        the same time clasping his hand, while the tear-glistened in my eye:
                            "<said>I expected you would have resided with us for ever, and
                                <persName>Marko</persName> and myself heard you say you were about
                            to leave our country</said>."</p>
                    <p>I saw a deadly paleness overspread his countenance, (I knew not then the
                        cause) but recovering in a moment, he replied:</p>
                    <p>"<said>And does that distress you? Indeed, my gentle friends, it is essential
                            to my own happiness; I have relatives in England that think me dead; I
                            have large possessions, which, if I remain here, will fall into other
                            hands. I have also a wife and children; these are strong arguments in
                            favor of my return to a country to which I owe my birth. I am sure you
                            cannot blame me; to you I owe my life, and my wife and children are
                            bound to pray for you</said>.</p><pb/>
                    <p><said>If I idle my days here, I am of no service to them or my country, and
                            then the life which you have preserved, your invaluable gift, is
                            rendered useless</said>.</p>
                    <p>"<said>In <placeName>Europe</placeName>, we live to assist one another, to
                            share the labors of the day, and make life supportable. We barter our
                            commodities more extensively than you do here, and the great exchange is
                            diffusing round the world, like the generating sun, the rays of
                            prosperity and affluence</said>."</p>
                    <p>"<said>Since it must be so</said>," I replied, "<said>I have no other
                            altnernative; may you be happy!" and placing a <seg xml:id="a009"
                                corresp="#n009">Saphie</seg> round his neck, "may this preserve you
                            in the hour of need! its virtue will protect you from the arms of the
                            malignant, and O! when in your native country, do sometimes think of
                            poor <persName>Amri</persName> and her husband
                                <persName>Makro</persName></said>."</p>
                    <p>"I was deeply affected, and <persName>William</persName>, <persName>the
                            Captain</persName>'s servant, falling on his knees, and catching at the
                        lappet of his coat, cried: "<said>Master, have mercy</said>!"</p>
                    <p>"<said>Silence, slave</said>!" returned he stamping his</p><pb/>
                    <p>foot upon the ground and flinging him away. I saw him tremble, and his cheek
                        was crimsoned with a malignant hatred; his eyes rolled furiously, and
                        sparkled in anger.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Marko</persName> rose from his seat.</p>
                    <p>"A something ran through my veins, and my blood was cold; a faintness seized
                        my limbs, and my heart forgot its usual pulsation.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>William</persName> now regained his seat, and, hiding his face in
                        his hand, cried: "Most inhuman!" <persName>Harrop</persName> recovered
                        himself, and, placing his hand upon his forehead, declared himself unwell;
                        he embraced my husband, who stood by his side, with all the fervor of
                        friendship, and assured him he could not order it otherwise; then shaking
                        hands with his servant, begged his pardon for the harshness of his conduct.
                        We soon retired to our several pallets."</p></ecda:embSN>
                <p>Dear <persName>Charles</persName>, I must intreat a moment's patience, if my
                    story interests you; if not, you will willingly consent without any
                    intreaty.</p>
                <p>My paper is filled, my pen worn to the stump—mind flagged—fingers cramped—and my
                    little finger wears as fine a polish as an agate. Indeed, when I sat down I did
                    not think of entering so far in the narrative of Amri in this letter.</p>
                <closer><salute>Adieu!</salute><signed>George Stanford.</signed></closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <head><hi rend="all caps">Letter III</hi>.</head>
                <head><hi rend="italics">The same to the same</hi>.</head>
                <opener><salute>Dear <persName>Charles</persName></salute>, .</opener>
                <p>I again resume my pen. Think not that I mean to revile my countrymen; those are
                    not my countrymen, whose inhumanitiy is the subject of my page. They may be
                    Britons born, but are not Britons at heart, and I disclaim them. There are
                    thousands here that have hearts like rocks. Children, from their birth, tutored
                    to inhumanity, and treat our fellow creatues worse than the dogs that lick the
                    morsel beneath their table.</p>
                <p>Oh fie! fie!</p>
                <p>I shall proceed to delineate the character of <rs type="properAdjective">an
                        European Westindian</rs>, in the narrative of <persName>Amri</persName>.</p>
                <ecda:embSN><p>"In the morning, Makro would not go, as was customary to the Koree,
                        because he would witness the departure of his friend, and we took a walk for
                        the last time, accompanied by <persName>Captain Harrop</persName>, to view
                        the surrounding plain.</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>"<persName>William</persName> waited on the banks of <placeName>the
                            Gambia</placeName> for the arrival of the boat, and to give <rs
                            type="person">the Captain</rs> notice</p>
                    <p>"We arrived at the top of a hill, where we always made our observations, and
                        a withered brance of a tree lay at our feet; he made us examine it.</p>
                    <p>"<said>Look</said>," cried he; "<said>here is another subject to admire;
                            behold this tree flourishing, while an arm that was lopped from its side
                            now withers on the ground</said>.</p>
                    <p>"<said>This is a subject worthy of your minute attention. This arm, divested
                            of nourishment, withers; the falling dew cannot revive it, nor the sun
                            cheer it. Compare it to a limb torn from you or me; it needs must die,
                            receiving no succor from the body, to which it once belonged. The blood
                            that flows in your veins would no longer enliven that limb, and the
                            place from whence it was torn would soon be covered by a growing
                            skin</said>.</p>
                    <p>"<said>We eat and are eaten by creatures of the earth; thousands inhabit our
                            mortal frame, and thousands inhabit the body of that tree. That receives
                            a sustenance from the earth, and the spreading veings convey the sap of
                            life to the re-</said></p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p><said>motest leaf of the same tree. Thus you see how complete is Nature in
                            all her various performances</said>."</p>
                    <p>"This observation did but increase our agony at the idea of separation. I
                        could have loved him, adored him. Ours were not weak minds, <rs
                            type="person">my son</rs>; they were pliant as the infant's, formed for
                        instruction, gifted with retentive memory, and we looked upon <rs
                            type="properAdjective">the European</rs> as our great instructor.</p>
                    <p>"On looking in the plain beneath, we beheld a <seg xml:id="a010"
                            corresp="#n010">Caffila</seg>, mastered by seventeen <seg xml:id="a011"
                            corresp="#n011"><ecda:persGroup a-occupation="merchant" a-status="free"
                                >Slatees</ecda:persGroup></seg>, it was the most numerous I ever
                        beheld and came from a great way up the country.</p>
                    <p>"Oh! <rs type="person">my son</rs>, let pity warm your breast for the unhappy
                        fate of your poor countrymen, and let a knowledge of their sufferings teach
                        you how to revenge them!</p>
                    <p>"'Tis I would fan your bosom to a flame; 'tis I would rouse your inactive
                        soul, and heap</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>destruction on <ecda:persGroup>the christian race</ecda:persGroup>.....but I
                        will proceed in my narrative</p>
                    <p>"Each <rs type="person">Slatee</rs> had above fourteen <ecda:persGroup
                            a-status="enslaved">slaves</ecda:persGroup> to his portion; some,
                        prisoners of war; others, dragged from the bosom of their family; all
                        manacled, a rope fastened by each other by the neck, and a log of wood by
                        the ancle. Thus were they torn from their homes by the infamous
                            <ecda:persGroup a-occupation="merchant" a-status="free"
                            >Slatees</ecda:persGroup>, and obliged to travel, fatigued and hungry,
                        over sandy deserts, till they came to a proper market, where they were sold
                        like cattle, and dispersed over the world.</p>
                    <p>"Such are the scenes we daily witness in <placeName>Africa</placeName>, such
                        is the christianity of <ecda:persGroup>the Europeans</ecda:persGroup> who
                        profess humanity.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Captain Harrop</persName> was uneasy at the sight, and
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, whose honest breast glowed with indignation,
                        whose sparkling eye alone spoke the language of his heart, violently
                        exclaimed against the horrible transaction. "<said>Are we not men</said>?"
                        did he cry; "<said>men as ye are? We vary in nothing but in color; we feel
                            as you do, and are awakre to the same sense of pain; but still are we
                            disposed by and among you like cattle</said>."</p>
                    <p><persName>Captain Harrop</persName> shook his head in token of
                        dissatisfaction, and remained silent.</p>
                    <p>"By this time, the entire <ecda:persGroup>Caffila</ecda:persGroup> had
                        passed</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>"One poor <rs type="person">negro woman</rs> remained behind; she was faint
                        and could not walk, but she was mercilessly dragged along by two guides,
                        with whips in their hands, who every now and then, spirited her with a lash.
                        At length, exhausted, worn out with fatigue and bruizes, she sunk down and
                        expired in our presence.</p>
                    <p>"Her guide giving her a curse or two, accompanied by a few blows on the
                        insensible body, walked on to join the
                            <ecda:persGroup>Caffila</ecda:persGroup>, which had proceeded to some
                        distance.</p>
                    <p>"This inhuman spectacle seemed sensibly to wound the feelings of <rs
                            type="person">our European instructor</rs>, who turned away his head, as
                        we thought, in agony.</p>
                    <p>"We now silently proceeded down the hill, and were returning home, when we
                        were roused by the firing of a gun at no great distance. "<said>Thank
                            heaven! they are arrived</said>," cried <persName>Captain
                            Harrop</persName>, and we soon reached the banks of
                            <placeName>Gambia</placeName>, but a short distance from our cabin,
                        where a boat waited to bear him from our shores.</p>
                    <p>"I shrunk back with terror, on beholding so many <name>Europeans</name>, and
                        involuntarily clasped the hand of <persName>Makro</persName>.</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>"In the space of two minutes, another boat touched the shore; there were only
                        two rowers on board.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Captain Harrop</persName> took me by the hand; he trembled, he
                        attempted to address us, but his voice faultered. 'Twas the trembling and
                        faultering of a villain, and the compunction visible on his cheek, I
                        misconstrued for an agonizing glow, occasioned by our own separation. Alas!
                        I soon found how much I was mistaken.....well, well!</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Makro</persName> led me on to the boat, and <persName>Captain
                            Harrop</persName> shaking us both heartily by the hand, entered the one
                        containing the two rowers only.</p>
                    <p>"I must say I was somewhat surprised, to find two touch upon our shores to
                        carry away one man; but suspicion dwelt not within my bosom, and I did not
                        wish to account for it.</p>
                    <p>"While <persName>Makro</persName> was examining the vessel, a gun fired, and
                        on the signal being given, we were both seized, and forced into the boat. I
                        fainted away, and was easily borne aboard the vessel.
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, with reviving strength, struggled hard for
                        liberty; his cause gave him twice the power of his adversaries, and he
                        struck many to the ground. He seized a sabre from the side of one of his
                        assailants, and dealt destruction with every blow.</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>"He had laid several of <ecda:persGroup>the Europeans</ecda:persGroup>
                        powerless at his side, when one merciless and well aimed blow deprived him
                        of his senses, and he fell. The weapon dropped useless from his hand, and
                        buried itself in the streaming gore, while he, with irons round his ancles,
                        handcuffed and chained in the boat, was conveyed on board the vessel, which,
                        within an hour set said for <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>"On my first return to reason, I found myself with many other miserable
                        wretches, deprived of liberty, confined within the narrow limits of a
                        loathsome dungeon, in a vessel bearing me from my native land, from
                            <ecda:anonPers>my father</ecda:anonPers> and <ecda:persGroup>my
                            friends</ecda:persGroup>. But where was <persName>Makro</persName>?
                        surely, cried I, they have not deprived me of the only comfort their cruelty
                        could leave me? or is he dead? I called upon his name, no answer was
                        returned. Cruel! cruel! I uttered, and fell senseless on a pallet of
                        straw.</p>
                    <p>"Several days elapsed, and I became more and more debilitated; my strength
                        visibly declined, and the iron ring, which bound me by a chain to the wall
                        galled my ancles.</p>
                    <p>"I remember I asked <ecda:anonPers>the keeper</ecda:anonPers>, who brought
                        the scanty allowance to our hold, to give me a bandage in mercy, for that my
                        leg was so painful I could not support it much longer.</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>"<said>Bandage</said>!" replied he; "<said>ha, ha, ha! I say, bandage indeed!
                            may hap I may bring you a bit of salt, but it does not much signify, as
                            tomorrow you will be allowed to stay an hour or two upon deck, for the
                            benefit of the air</said>."</p>
                    <p>"Indeed, we needed it, for our prison was close to suffocation, and four of
                        our companions were already dead.</p>
                    <p>"In about an hour after, he brought some salt, with which he rubbed my ancle,
                        till over-come with excrutiating agony, I fainted.—When I recovered, I found
                        my fainting had made no alteration in the continuance of his <hi
                            rend="italic">job</hi>, for he had bound it round with a piece of brown
                        paper, and replaced the iron ring.</p>
                    <p>"The next day, we were ordered on deck; my inquiring eye looked around for
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, alas! he was not there, nor could I see the
                        perfidious Harrop.</p>
                    <p>"We had scarcely been an hour on deck, in the open air and enjoying the sea
                        breeze, when I heard a voice cry: Bring him on deck. I remembered the
                        sound—'twas he—yes, yes, 'twas he whom, when dying upon a raft, I succored.
                        'Twas he, who confessed he was indebted to me for life, and his gratitude
                        was to throw chains over me, and draf me in bondage from my native country,
                        to be made a slave.</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>"He came and examined the miserable captives; he stood before me; I could not
                        speak, but lifted up my manacled hands, and directed my eyes towards him. I
                        saw the keen reproof cut him to the heart; he turned from me, and
                            <persName>Makro</persName> was brought upon deck, chained to a broad
                        plank, with arms and legs extended. His countenance was wan and ematiated;
                        his hoolow eyes were almost bured in their sockets; they were rivetted on
                        me. I looked at him, and fast the tear rolled down his deadened cheek.</p>
                    <p>"<said>He has not eye these three days</said>," cried <ecda:anonPers>a
                            boy</ecda:anonPers>, to <rs type="person">the Captain</rs>, "<said>nor
                            will the whip compel him</said>." I soon understood it was
                            <persName>Makro</persName>'s resolve to die, and I ejaculated in heart I
                        would not survive him.</p>
                    <p>"<ecda:anonPers>The boy</ecda:anonPers>, by <rs type="person">the
                            captain</rs>'s order, brought a mess for <persName>Makro</persName>; he
                        stedfastly refused, and <ecda:anonPers>the boy</ecda:anonPers>, from his
                        birth trained to inhumanity, struck him smartly across the thighs with a
                        whip. <persName>Makro</persName> smiled contemptuously upon him. Oh! how did
                        I long to clasp this faithful husband in my arms, to unfold to his heart
                        that <persName>Amri</persName> would follow his heroic example.</p>
                    <p>"They then proceeded to new extremities with him; they forced his mouth, and
                        keeping it extended with a gag, poured the loathsome beverage down his
                        feverish throat; but</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>no sooner did they extricate him, that he spit it back, accompanied by blood;
                        for, in forcing their spoon into his mouth, they tore his throat in a most
                        human manner.</p>
                    <p>"Still he smiled and laughed to scorn their ineffectual means. This obstinacy
                        got him another severe beating. I screamed, and was borne from the deck,
                        while the operation was performing.</p>
                    <p>"The next day, when my allowance was brought, lest hunger should compel me to
                        eat, I, without hestitation, overturned the bowl.—This was observed by the
                        keeper, who beat me till blood streamed down my back, and I was deprived of
                        feeling.</p>
                    <p>"In the evening, my bowl was replenished; my tongue and lips were parched by
                        fever, and I endured an agony indescribable. I would have sacrificed every
                        thing, but my love for <persName>Makro</persName>, for something to quench
                        my immoderate thirst; but I obstinately persisted in my resolve, and again,
                        lest excess of agony, in a moment of torpitude, should tempt me to taste the
                        beverage, I overturned the bowl.</p>
                    <p>"The ensuing day, my fever raged more violent; our keeper came and, on
                        observing my allowance spilt, and me dying, cursed me</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>for my obstinancy, and went to give information to <rs type="person">the
                            Captain</rs>.</p>
                    <p>"This day, we were ordered to pass on the deck; indeed the Captain found us
                        in so debilitated and deplorable a state, that he feared he should not be
                        able to carry above half his complement to <seg xml:id="a012"
                            corresp="#n012">Jamaica</seg>, and inhumanity gave way to private
                        interest.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Makro</persName> was on deck, but so weak, that he could not
                        stand. He was now released from the plank to which he had previously been
                        bound; his legs were unshackled, and his hands only were cuffed. Alas! he
                        was so much enfeebled, that they need not fear him. I, myself, was not
                        joined with <ecda:persGroup a-status="enslaved">the chain of
                            slaves</ecda:persGroup>, but permitted to walk about, if my lacerated
                        limbs would enable me. On seeing <persName>Makro</persName>, I tried to
                        approach, but unable to support myself, I fell down. Stunned from the blow,
                        I lay senseless, till <persName>Captain Harrop</persName> himself lifted me
                        up, and led me to my husband. I expressed my gratitude in the best manner I
                        was able, and, to convince us of his generosity, he unbound us both. We fell
                        into each</p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p>other's arms; <persName>Makro</persName> pressed me, but faintly, to his
                        bosom, and I prayed heaven to let us expire enfolded as we lay. Ah! why was
                        that blessing denied us?</p>
                    <p>"Even <persName>Harrop</persName>'s flinty heart was touched; even his bosom
                        that knew not remorse dissolved for the moment, and the straying tear
                        bedewed his cheek.</p>
                    <p>"Again was the mess brought before us, accompanied by the whip;
                            <persName>Harrop</persName> found to his infinite mortification, that
                        force was of no avail, and he sought intreaty. The whip was thrown on one
                        side, and thus spoke <rs type="person">the monster</rs>, with syren voice,
                        accompanied by tears of a crocodile. Oh! had heaven stamped an avoiding mark
                        upon the forehead of dissimulation !—but I disdain to murmur; for I have a
                        son that shall revenge me.</p>
                    <p>"<said>Son of Africa</said>," he cried, "<said>live and be happy; treat me
                            not as your enemy, but look upon me rather as a friend, who strains
                            every nerve to serve you. When in your country, I stroke to inform your
                            mind; but you dwelt with heathens, and I regarded it as my duty to
                            return the obligation you conferred upon me. I found my task but half
                            complete, when I had taught you to admire the works of your Creator;
                            what then remained was to introduce you to civilized society, of
                            which</said></p>
                    <pb/>
                    <p><said>you soon will become an ornament. If I used force, in compelling you
                            from your shores, believe me, it has cost me much secret pain at heart;
                            but nothing less could be done; for, I knew it would be useless to
                            attempt to dissuade you from your native country</said>."</p>
                    <p>"Villainous depredator! could we heed his words? We were too much
                        enlightened, to become his dupes a second time.</p>
                    <p>"When <persName>Makro</persName> understood that my present debilitated state
                        proceeded from the want of sustenance, which was regularly served me, he
                        requested of me that I would eat; but I refused even him who was as dear,
                        nay dearer to me than life.</p>
                    <p>"On knowing the reason, he called for the bowl, and ate heartily, and I
                        joined him. We had now been on deck near three hours, and our extreme
                        langor, owning principally to the want of nourishment, gradually
                        decreased.—We could stand; as for me, I could walk; but
                            <persName>Makro</persName> still preserved a great faintness.</p>
                    <p>"We were remanded to our dungeons, on the approach of evening, and now I was
                        not chained by the leg as before, but by a belt which encircled my body, and
                        handcuffed as usual.</p>
                    <p>"I now, for several days, ate my food regularly. I never saw
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, who was con</p><pb/><p>fined in a separate
                        dungeon, but when we were brought on deck, and I waited in eager expectation
                        the approaching day. At length, it came; the very thought of his returning
                        to his food made me regard life, the lassitude of my limbs decreased in
                        consequence. Comparatively speaking, when I again came on deck, I was
                        perfectly recovered, and so I expected to find <persName>Makro</persName>;
                        but no; when my eyes beheld him, he was more languid than before.</p>
                    <p><persName>Harrop</persName> had us both unbound; my apperance pleased him, we
                        were left to ourselves, and enabled to converse more freely.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Makro</persName>, in a faint and dying voice, thus addressed me:
                        "Live, <persName>Amri</persName>; as you love me, live for my sake. I shall
                        never reach the place of our destination, and I do entreat you, attend to
                        the last words of your dying husband. I will no longer take aught to nourish
                        life; I am sickened by the weary load, rendered loathsome by
                            <ecda:persGroup>the vile Europeans</ecda:persGroup>. I daily receive the
                        lash for my obstinate perseverance; but I mock their cruelties, I scorn
                        their wiles, and am prepared to die. Oh! <persName>Amri</persName>, I
                        beseech you, live; live as you love me; live to revenge my death. Take this
                        girdle from my loins, and keep it in your possession. If the being to whom
                        you are to give life, be male, let him wear it from his earliest birth,
                        and</p><pb/>
                    <p>whisper in his ear, till manhood dawns, what he owes to his country. Inspire
                        his young bosom with revenge; tutor his early mind how to hate the European
                        race; teach him, in his childhood, to lisp curses on their name, and blast
                        their progeny for ever. You shall find the seeds you sow ripening as he
                        grows in years, and expand into a flame; be this your task. Say,
                            <persName>Amri</persName>, that you will do this, and I die
                        contented."</p>
                    <p>"He paused—</p>
                    <p>I clasped him to my arms; I could not bear the idea of separation, and
                        remained incapable of returning him an answer, though the necessity of my
                        living, to give birth to one who might revenge his wrongs, struck me most
                        forcibly.</p>
                    <p>"<said>Ah</said>!" rejoined he, "<said>is it possible? and can
                                <persName>Amri</persName> refuse my last request? Then, indeed,
                            death, thou art most acceptable</said>.</p>
                    <p>"<said><persName>Amri</persName>, 'tis not that I fear to live, but I have
                            resolved never to acknowledge a master. I do not seek death because I
                            fear to buffet with those Europeans, it is because I never can own a
                            superior but my Creator. Man was His noblest work, and I am a man. He
                            did not make slaves of one half of this globe, nor order the black to
                            bend subservient to the white man's yoke; nor will I, a created
                            being</said></p><pb/>
                    <p><said>like them, be bought and sold, and toil like a beast of burthen, that
                            they may enjoy the fruits of my labor. My beloved Amri, if you refuse me
                            my last request, I shall think the white men are not the only cruel
                            beings</said>."</p>
                    <p>I dried my tears, loosened the girdle from his loins, and answered:</p>
                    <p>"My beloved <persName>Makro</persName>, I will obey you in every thing: Yes,
                        may our God grant me a son to revenge your cause, and I will instill into
                        him hatred to the Europeans, and if he revenge you not, he shall receive his
                        mother's curse."</p>
                    <p><persName>Amri</persName>, overcome by her emotion, ceased her narrative, and
                            <persName>Jack</persName>, rising hastily from his seat, brought down a
                        sabre which he had concealed in the thatch, the slaves not being allowed to
                        possess arms of any description. He drew it and swore, with exulting fury,
                        to merit his Creator's curse if he revenged not the cause of his
                        parents.</p>
                </ecda:embSN>
                <p>Dear <persName>Charles</persName>, I must conclude this letter, with a promise to
                    commence early tomorrow morning. It is now near midnight, and I have been so
                    much taken up with the narrative, that I observed not how the hours fled.</p>
                <closer><salute>Adieu!</salute><signed>George Stanford.</signed></closer>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <head><hi rend="all caps">Letter IV</hi>.</head>
                <head><hi rend="italics">The same to the same</hi>.</head>
                <opener><salute>Dear <persName>Charles</persName></salute>, </opener>
                <ecda:embSN>
                    <p>Joy beamed in the eyes of Amri, as she beheld the darling of her heart, the
                        offspring of <persName>Makro</persName>, in the strength of youth, with the
                        sword of vengeance drawn in his hand. Fire shot from his eye and spoke the
                        language of his soul; how blest was the fond doting mother!</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Amri</persName> embraced him and proceeded.</p>
                    <p>"Your father was satisfied with my answer; he grasped my hand; but, exhausted
                        by too great an exertion, he sunk back, and my arms received him.</p>
                    <p>"Captain Harrop now approached; he had listened to the preceding
                        conversation, and was confounded. He entreated to be heard; he caught hold
                        of the hand of Makro, and in the most supplicating manner, begged our
                        pardon, at the same time, declaring, with the most solemn asseveration, that
                        he would grant us both liberty when we came on shore, and in—</p><pb/>
                    <p>treated <persName>Makro</persName> in the most tender manner, to receive his
                        food.</p>
                    <p>"Your father smiled upon him.</p>
                    <p>"<said>Menial inhuman wretch</said>!" he exclaimed, "<said>I am beyond thy
                            power. Hardened European, thou seest one struggling in death, who doth
                            defy thee; hadst thou a heart, thou wouldst feel how deservedly I
                            despise thee. But for myself and <persName>Amri</persName>, thou hadst
                            perished long since. Do not think I recal this to incite thee to mercy;
                            I ask it not; I scorn it. Take away thy beverage it is encompassed round
                            with slavery, and I will rather die than live a dog, and own a cursed
                            European for my master</said>."</p>
                    <p>His voice faultered; the bowl was brought him, which he threw to the other
                        side of the vessel.</p>
                    <p>"I was then divided from him; they bared his back, and stripping him to the
                        waist, he received five hundred lashes.</p>
                    <p>"The first three hundred he supported with heroic fortitude, laughed, sung,
                        and spit upon <persName>the Captain</persName> alternately, who stood near
                        him. My bosom was almost callous to feeling; I beheld the cruel affliction
                        without a sigh, till I saw his head sink upon his breast, and his limbs
                        forget their use. I would have flown to him, but the consolation of being
                        near him,</p><pb/>
                    <p>in his last moments, was denied me. He was now taken down, and brought to the
                        side of the deck. His body lay almost at my feet, but I could not go nearer
                        to him. I prayed, I supplicated the inhuman monsters, but in vain. Oh! in
                        what a mangled situation was his body; the flesh was pulverized on his back,
                        and stopped the flowing of the blood. They applied salt to his wounds, and
                        the excruciating agony for a moment revived him. He begged to be raised from
                        the ground; this was granted, and he supported himself against the main
                        mast; but, too enfeebled to stand unassisted, <ecda:anonPers>a young
                            lieutenant</ecda:anonPers>, who witnessed, with tears in his eyes, the
                        horrid transation, ran to give his aid.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Makro</persName> beckoned <persName>Harrop</persName> to come near
                        him; he did, and, seizing a pistol from the belt of the lieutenant, he shot
                        him.</p>
                    <p>"<persName>Harrop</persName> fell bathed in his blood.</p>
                    <p>"Immediately the ship was in confusion; <ecda:persGroup>the
                            negroes</ecda:persGroup> set up a loud shout; <ecda:persGroup>the
                            sailors</ecda:persGroup> ran to the assistance of their
                            <persName>Captain</persName>, and <persName>Makro</persName> clasped his
                        hands together in token of resignation, then exclaimed: "<said>God of my
                            country I come. <persName>Amri</persName>, farewell! Look to a meeting
                            in <placeName><seg xml:id="a013" corresp="#n013">Africa's
                                plains</seg></placeName></said>." He then fell</p><pb/>
                    <p>to the ground, and, lifting up his eyes to heaven expired.</p>
                    <p>"The negroes, who beheld his cruel fate, trembled with apprehension, and each
                        suspected his turn was next.</p>
                    <p>"I fell upon my knees, and humbly intreated I might be permitted to approach
                        him. Cruel barbarians; they even refused me this simple request, and we were
                        remanded to our dungeons. I resolutely refused to stir, till I was permitted
                        to embrace the lifeless body of my <persName>Makro</persName>. They applied
                        the whip to my shoulders, and in the midst of my supplications, tossed him
                        over to the ocean, and hurried me away to confinement.</p>
                    <p>"Oh! remorseless wretches! did ye possess one spark of pity in your bosoms,
                        ye could not have denied me such a demand. Each day furthered one or other
                        of us to eternity, and I fancied my time as fast approaching, but I sought
                        to cheer life, for the sake of revenge. I daily ate my allowance, and
                        endeavored to lose the remembrance of cruelties exercised on
                            <persName>Makro</persName>, since they depressed my spirits, and
                        impaired my health.</p>
                    <p>"But what of <persName>Harrop</persName> demanded the impatient
                            <persName>Jack</persName>, while a presaging anxiety distorted his
                        countenance; "<said>say, was the pistol to his heart?</said>"</p><pb/>
                    <p>"<said>Alas! he recovered</said>."</p>
                    <p>Jack dwindled from his attitude of suspense; his soul had been roused with
                        eager hope, and now was dashed with the bitterness of disappointment.</p>
                    <p>"The enfeebled arm of Makro, took but an unsteady aim; the whizzing ball shot
                        through Harrop's side," continued Amri, "and he was conveyed from the deck;
                        but he soon recovered, and, at the conclusion of our voyage, he was
                        perfectly well.</p>
                    <p>"We fast approached our destination, and a few days more landed us on the
                        shores of <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>.</p>
                </ecda:embSN>
            </div>

        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
