<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Obi;or, The history of Threefingered Jack.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Worcester: Printed by <persName>Isaiah Thomas</persName>, Jun. Sold by him, and
                    by <name>Thomas&amp;Whipple</name>, <placeName>Newburyport</placeName>.
                        <date>1804</date>.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>In a Series of Letters from a resident in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> to his
                    friend in <placeName>England</placeName></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titleBlock>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Obi;or, The history of Threefingered Jack</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
            </titleBlock>
            <div type="prefatory">
                <lg>
                    <l>Oh! ye who at your ease</l>
                    <l>Sip the blood sweetened beverage! thoughts like these</l>
                    <l>Haply ye scorn: I thank thee, gracious God!</l>
                    <l>That I do feel upon my cheek the glow</l>
                    <l>Of indignation, when beneath the rod</l>
                    <l>A sable brother writhes in silent woe.......<persName>Southey</persName>.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Hear him! ye Senates! hear this truth sublime,</l>
                    <l>He who allows oppression shares the crime.....<persName>Darwin</persName></l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prefatory">
                <head>Advertisement.</head>
                <p>I have published these letters, which accidentally fell into my hands, with a
                    view to commemorate the name of <persName>Jack</persName>, and place upon the
                    list of heroes, one who, had he shone in a higher sphere, would have proved as
                    bright a luminary as ever graced the Roman annals, or ever boldly asserted the
                    rights of a Briton. His cause was great and noble, for to private wrongs he
                    added the liberty of his countrymen, and stood alone a bold and daring defender
                    of the Rights of Man. To him who shall applaud Jack through the varied scenes of
                    his life; to him, whose heart shall sympathize in his misfortunes, who shall
                    smile upon his deeds, at the same time that he laments their cause, I dedicate
                    the following pages. <persName>W.E.J</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <pb/>
            <head>Obi, Or, The History of Threefingered Jack</head>
            <div type="letter">
                <head>
                    <emph rend="caps">Letter I.</emph>
                </head>
                <opener><salute>Dear <persName>Charles</persName></salute>,
                            <dateline><placeName>Jamaica</placeName></dateline>.</opener>
                <p>A whole week has your letter been lying open on my desk, ready for me to answer—a
                    whole week have the above two words been written, as you may perceive by the
                    difference in the shade of the ink and the cutting of my pen; for, three times
                    has the dried standish been replenished, and twenty times, at least, have I
                    dipped into it, sometimes with a new pen, sometimes with a mended one—and still
                    at this moment am I at a loss what to say to you in reply to your queries.</p>
                <p>Now, you will think that, because I have written the above long sentence, my mind
                    is wholly and exclusively engrossed by your business, and that I shall be able
                    to go on in a regular steady way; but I tell you, Charles, it is no such thing;
                    for at the end of that very sentence, I stopped a full hour, unable to
                    proceed—and now again do I stop short.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>Try what I may, it will not do—but what is the matter? you will say.
                        <persName>Jack</persName>!!! and his cursed three fingers!!!</p>
                <p>I'll tell you what, <persName>Charles</persName>—I have just read your letter for
                    the hundred and first time, and upoin my soul, cannot see that the business it
                    is about is of such great importance; so, with or without your leave, I shall
                    put off answering it, until I have eased myself of my insufferable burthen, by
                    dispatching <persName>Jack</persName>, his three fingers, and his
                        <name>Obi</name>, and all that belongs to him; for, positively, I can think
                    of nothing else.</p>
                <p>And so it is with every body in the Island; go wherever I will the name of
                        <persName>Jack</persName> is perpetually buzzed in my ears. If I meet a
                    friend in the street, it is no longer "<said>How d'ye do</said>?" but
                        "<said>Well, what news of <persName>Jack</persName></said>?" if any of my
                    neighbors, calling his servant, says,; "<said><persName>Jack</persName>, come
                        here</said>," I start and stare about, in expectation of seeing the
                    threefingered one make his appearance. Nay, there is not a thing called
                        <persName>Jack</persName>, whether a smokejack, a boot jack, or any other
                    jack, but acts as a spell upon my senses and sets me on the fret at the bare
                    mention of it. By heavens! it is too much, and I wish...</p>
                <p>Nay, I do not—I cannot find in my heart to form the same wish that most of the
                    inhab—</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>itants here express every day. Jck is a noble fellow, and in spite of every cruel
                    hard hearted planter, I shall repeat the same to the last hour of my life.
                            "<said><persName>Jack</persName> is a Negro</said>," say they.
                            "<said><persName>Jack</persName> is a Man</said>," say I.</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>"<said>He is a slave</said>."</l>
                    <l>"<said>Man cannot be a slave to Man</said>."</l>
                </lg>
            </div>

        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
