<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Obi;or, The history of Threefingered Jack.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Worcester: Printed by <persName>Isaiah Thomas</persName>, Jun. Sold by him, and
                    by <name>Thomas&amp;Whipple</name>, <placeName>Newburyport</placeName>.
                        <date>1804</date>.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>In a Series of Letters from a resident in <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> to his
                    friend in <placeName>England</placeName></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <titleBlock>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Obi;or, The history of Threefingered Jack</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
            </titleBlock>
            <div type="prefatory">
                <lg>
                    <l>Oh! ye who at your ease</l>
                    <l>Sip the blood sweetened beverage! thoughts like these</l>
                    <l>Haply ye scorn: I thank thee, gracious God!</l>
                    <l>That I do feel upon my cheek the glow</l>
                    <l>Of indignation, when beneath the rod</l>
                    <l>A sable brother writhes in silent woe.......<persName>Southey</persName>.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>Hear him! ye Senates! hear this truth sublime,</l>
                    <l>He who allows oppression shares the crime.....<persName>Darwin</persName></l>
                </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prefatory">
                <head>Advertisement.</head>
                <p>I have published these letters, which accidentally fell into my hands, with a
                    view to commemorate the name of <persName>Jack</persName>, and place upon the
                    list of heroes, one who, had he shone in a higher sphere, would have proved as
                    bright a luminary as ever graced the Roman annals, or ever boldly asserted the
                    rights of a Briton. His cause was great and noble, for to private wrongs he
                    added the liberty of his countrymen, and stood alone a bold and daring defender
                    of the Rights of Man. To him who shall applaud <persName>Jack</persName> through
                    the varied scenes of his life; to him, whose heart shall sympathize in his
                    misfortunes, who shall smile upon his deeds, at the same time that he laments
                    their cause, I dedicate the following pages. <persName>W.E.J</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <pb/>
            <head>Obi, Or, The History of Threefingered Jack</head>
            <div type="letter">
                <head>
                    <emph rend="caps">Letter I.</emph>
                </head>
                <opener><salute>Dear <persName>Charles</persName></salute>,
                            <dateline><placeName>Jamaica</placeName></dateline>.</opener>
                <p>A whole week has your letter been lying open on my desk, ready for me to answer—a
                    whole week have the above two words been written, as you may perceive by the
                    difference in the shade of the ink and the cutting of my pen; for, three times
                    has the dried standish been replenished, and twenty times, at least, have I
                    dipped into it, sometimes with a new pen, sometimes with a mended one—and still
                    at this moment am I at a loss what to say to you in reply to your queries.</p>
                <p>Now, you will think that, because I have written the above long sentence, my mind
                    is wholly and exclusively engrossed by your business, and that I shall be able
                    to go on in a regular steady way; but I tell you, <persName>Charles</persName>,
                    it is no such thing; for at the end of that very sentence, I stopped a full
                    hour, unable to proceed—and now again do I stop short.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>Try what I may, it will not do—but what is the matter? you will say.
                        <persName>Jack</persName>!!! and his cursed three fingers!!!</p>
                <p>I'll tell you what, <persName>Charles</persName>—I have just read your letter for
                    the hundred and first time, and upoin my soul, cannot see that the business it
                    is about is of such great importance; so, with or without your leave, I shall
                    put off answering it, until I have eased myself of my insufferable burthen, by
                    dispatching <persName>Jack</persName>, his three fingers, and his
                        <name>Obi</name>, and all that belongs to him; for, positively, I can think
                    of nothing else.</p>
                <p>And so it is with every body in the Island; go wherever I will the name of
                        <persName>Jack</persName> is perpetually buzzed in my ears. If I meet a
                    friend in the street, it is no longer "<said>How d'ye do</said>?" but
                        "<said>Well, what news of <persName>Jack</persName></said>?" if any of my
                    neighbors, calling his servant, says,; "<said><persName>Jack</persName>, come
                        here</said>," I start and stare about, in expectation of seeing the
                    threefingered one make his appearance. Nay, there is not a thing called
                        <persName>Jack</persName>, whether a smokejack, a boot jack, or any other
                    jack, but acts as a spell upon my senses and sets me on the fret at the bare
                    mention of it. By heavens! it is too much, and I wish...</p>
                <p>Nay, I do not—I cannot find in my heart to form the same wish that most of the
                    inhab—</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>itants here express every day. Jck is a noble fellow, and in spite of every cruel
                    hard hearted planter, I shall repeat the same to the last hour of my life.
                            "<said><persName>Jack</persName> is a Negro</said>," say they.
                            "<said><persName>Jack</persName> is a Man</said>," say I.</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>—"<said>He is a slave</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Man cannot be a slave to Man</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>He is my property</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>How did you acquire that property</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>By paying for it</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Paying! Paying whom</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Him who brought him from Africa</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>How did he get possession of him</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>He caught him there</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Caught! what? Like a wild beast</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>No, but he contrived means to convey him into his ship</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Contrived! Then he brought him without his consent</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Very likely</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>And what has become of that robber</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Robber! He is a very respectable man, who has left off trade, has
                            married the daughter of a rich planter, and now lives very comfortably,
                            after the fatigues of an industrious life</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>What! Do they hang a poor hard-laboring man, who, driven by despair
                            at the sight of his numerous family ready to starve</said></l>
                </lg>
                <pb/>
                <lg>
                    <l><said>for want of a bit of bread, takes advantage of a dark night, goes on
                            the highway and frightens teh traveller out of a few pieces of gold and
                            shall a daring ruffian, who is openly guilty of a crime more heinous in
                            its nature and baneful in its effects, get respected by every body and
                            pass his days in the peaceable enjoyment of riches acquired by such
                            infamous means</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>I don't understand you. I never heard that the traffic was infamous.
                            Is it not authorised by all the nations of Europe, Asia and America?
                            Have not regulations been made concerning it by all
                        governments</said>?"</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Very true, but that does not make it more honorable. Prostitution is
                            authorised, yes, for it is more than tolerated, by governments, many of
                            which have also made regulations concerning it, but that does make it
                            less infamous</said>."</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Nay, you are going too far, and this is widely different</said>.</l>
                    <l>—"<said>Different !—By heavens ! you will drive me mad</said>."</l>
                </lg>
                <p>And such, my dear <persName>Charles</persName>, is the daily altercation I have
                    with the greatest part of the planters here, and what you have just read is a
                    specimen of the various arguments brought on both sides of the question. As I
                    know your sentiments upon the subject, I shall close</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>it here and proceed to my narrative about <persName>threefingered
                    Jack</persName>, and as I have made it my business to collect every particular
                    relative to him, I believe I shall have it in my power to give you a
                    circumstantial account of all his actions. In fact, what I am now going to write
                    is nothing more than a copy of what I had sometime ago begun to put into a
                    regular story, out of several memoranda collected at different times. So without
                    lengthening this preamble, I thus begin:</p>
                <p><persName>Amri</persName> was a beautiful slave, the property of <persName>Mr.
                        Mornton</persName>, of <placeName>Maroons Town</placeName>. She was
                    sanguinary in her temper; for, misfortunre, or rather cruelty, had perverted a
                    heart naturally inclined to virtue. She was torn from the arms of her husband,
                    her family and friends, while in the mayday of her life, from her native
                        <placeName>Africa</placeName></p>
                <p>She had vowed to curse <rs type="persGroup">the European race</rs> for ever; and
                    had a son, in whose breast she never failed to nurture the baneful passion of
                    revenge</p>
                <p>She taught him to despise his groaning companions, complaining under their labor,
                    meanly submitting to the christian whip, and then pusillanimously venting their
                    griefs in half suprressed sighs</p>
                <pb/>
                <p><persName>Jack</persName> had a soul, even in infancy, superior to such whining;
                    he complained not of the daily labor heaped upon him, but of the tardiness of
                    time.</p>
                <p>Each night, when the grand luminator of the world hid his rays within the deep,
                    he threw himself on his knees, and prayed the great God of his country to ripen
                    him to manhood, that he might shake off the yoke that pressed heavy upon him,
                    and revenge the cause of his country and his parents. His youthful fiery soul
                    led him to imagine himself the destroyer of all <placeName>Europe</placeName>;
                    he saw in the warlike picture his fancy drew, the course he was to fllow, and
                    the transport of his heart was often visible by the uncommon hauteur of his
                    manners. When assured of revenge, he would grin with a smile of malice,
                    transparent on his cheek, at the overseer, while the merciless whip was
                    lacerating his back.</p>
                <p>He was of the most manly growth, nearly seven feet in height, and amazingly
                    robust; bread up to hardihood, his limbs were well shapen and athletic; he could
                    endure the most laborious, toil and would with ease perform the office of any
                    two negores within the planation. His face was rather long; his eyes black and
                    fierce; his nose was not like the generality of blacks, squat and flat, but
                    rather aquiline, and</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>his skin remarkably clear. He discovered a great deal of expression in his
                    countenance, and a very look of reproach from him would strike terror to <rs
                        type="persGroup">his fellow slaves</rs>. He was now two and twenty years of
                    age, and every thing <rs type="person">his fond but revengeful mother</rs> could
                    wish him.</p>
                <p>Returning from his labor to the small hovel, where he and <rs type="person">his
                        mother</rs> dwelt, after a heavy day of toil, he threw himself weary on the
                    pallet of straw where he resposed. <persName>Amri</persName> arose and claspt
                    him in her arms.</p>
                <p>"<said><rs type="person">My son</rs></said>," cried she, "<said>Now is the time
                        arrived when you should contend for the rights of yourself and <rs
                            type="person">mother</rs>. Now is the time when you should revenge my
                        cause. You are arrived to maturity, and, to inspire you to revenge my
                        injuries, I will relate the misfortunes of my life</said>."</p>
                <p>Dear Charles, so much of the narrative was imparted to me by a negro, well
                    acquainted with Amri, and I can assure you, for I have seen this threefingered
                    Jack, that he was every thing in soul and person requisite for the hero. Give me
                    now a short pause. Sketch the man you would wish—a bold and daring fellow, ready
                    to undertake any thing for the good of his country, inspired by a rooted
                    revenge, on the strongest foundation villainy can fabricate, and Jack's the man
                    to a point. I must break off. Adieu!</p>
                <pb/>

            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <head><hi rend="italics">The same to the same</hi>.</head>
                <opener><salute>Dear <persName>Charles</persName></salute>, .</opener>
                <p>I resume my pen, and commence with the narrative of <persName>Amri</persName>.
                    All impatience myself, I suspect you to feel as much. I set down her own words
                    as near as memory can trace—mind that.</p></div>

        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
