<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>NARRATIVE OF LOUIS ASA-ASA, A CAPTURED AFRICAN.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <ecda:hyperDiv>
        <ecda:notes>
           <note type="ecda">
              <interpGrp type="commType">
                 <interp xml:id="flora">plants (flora)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="fauna">animals (fauna)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="food">food and other consumable items (incl. drinks, seasonings, etc.)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="medical">medical or medicinal items (including references to folk medicine)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="textile">sartorial and textile references</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="currency">references to money or currency</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp type="productionPhase">
                 <interp xml:id="plant">planting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="cultivation">cultivation</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="harvest">harvesting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="refine">refining</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="production">production (non plant-based commodities)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="transport">transport</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="sale">sale</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="circulation">circulation of commodities, such as through gift-giving or theft</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="use">use of commodities</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp>
                 <interp xml:id="punishment">References to scenes of punishment or the enforcement of colonial rule</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="military">References to the material conditions, social institutions or actual events of warfare</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="abolition">References to the abolition of slavery or abolitionist movement</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="disease">References to ailment and disease, specifically in people</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="poison">References to poison</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="obeah">References to Obeah</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="performance">References to performance (esp. John Canoe)</interp>
              </interpGrp>
          </note>
        </ecda:notes>
     </ecda:hyperDiv>
     
     
     <front>
        <titleBlock>
           <docTitle>
              <titlePart></titlePart>
           </docTitle>
           
        </titleBlock>
     </front>
     
      <body>
         <div>
          <p>The following interesting narrative is a convenient supplement to the history of <persName ref="#mary_prince">Mary
             Prince</persName>. It is given, like hers, as nearly as possible in the narrator’s words, with only
               so much correction as was necessary to connect the story, and render it grammatical. The
               concluding passage in inverted commas, is entirely his own. While <rs type="person" ref="#mary_prince">Mary’s</rs> narrative
               shews the disgusting character of colonial slavery, this little tale explains with equal
               force the horrors in which it originates.</p>
            <p>It is necessary to explain that <persName ref="#louis_asaasa">Louis</persName> came to this country about five years ago, in a
               French vessel called the <ecda:shipName>Pearl</ecda:shipName>. She had lost her reckoning, and was driven by stress of
               weather into the port of <placeName>St. Ives</placeName>, in <placeName>Cornwall</placeName>. <persName ref="#louis_asaasa">Louis</persName> and his <ecda:persGroup>four companions</ecda:persGroup> were
               brought to <placeName>London</placeName> upon a writ of Habeas Corpus at the instance of <persName ref="#george_stephen">Mr. George Stephen</persName>;
               and, after some trifling opposition on the part of the <ecda:anonPers>master of the vessel</ecda:anonPers>, were
               discharged by <persName ref="#lord_wynford">Lord Wynford</persName>. <ecda:persGroup>Two of his unfortunate fellow-sufferers</ecda:persGroup> died of the measles
               at Hampstead; the other two returned to <placeName>Sierra Leone</placeName>; but poor <persName ref="#louis_asaasa">Louis</persName>, when offered the
               choice of going back to <placeName>Africa</placeName>, replied, "<said aloud="true" direct="true">Me no father, no mother now; me stay with
               you.</said>" And here he has ever since remained; conducting himself in a way to gain the good
               will and respect of all who know him. He is remarkably intelligent, understands our
               language perfectly, and can read and write well. The last sentences of the following
               narrative will seem almost too peculiar to be his own; but it is not the first time that
               in conversation with <persName ref="#george_stephen">Mr. George Stephen</persName>, he has made similar remarks. On one occasion in
               particular, he was heard saying to himself in the kitchen, while sitting by the fire
               apparently in deep thought, "<said aloud="true" direct="true">Me think,—me think——</said>" <ecda:anonPers>A fellow-servant</ecda:anonPers> inquired what he
               meant; and he added, "<said aloud="true" direct="true">Me think what a good thing I came to <placeName>England</placeName>! Here, I know what
               God is, and read my Bible; in my country they have no God, no Bible.</said>”</p>
            <p>How severe and just a reproof to the guilty wretches who visit his country only with
               fire and sword! How deserved a censure upon the not less guilty men, who dare to
               vindicate the state of slavery, on the lying pretext, that its victims are of an
               inferior nature! And scarcely less deserving of reprobation are those who have it in
               their power to prevent these crimes, but who remain inactive from indifference, or are
               dissuaded from throwing the shield of British power over the victim of oppression, by
               the sophistry, and the clamour, and the avarice of the oppressor. It is the reproach and
               the sin of England. May God avert from our country the ruin which this national guilt
               deserves!</p>
            <p>We lament to add, that the <ecda:shipName>Pearl</ecda:shipName> which brought <ecda:persGroup>these negroes</ecda:persGroup> to our shore, was restored
               to its owners at the instance of the <name>French Government</name>, instead of being condemned as a
               prize to <persName ref="#rye">Lieut. Rye</persName>, who, on his own responsibility, detained her, with all her manacles
               and chains and other detestable proofs of her piratical occupation on board. We trust it
               is not yet too late to demand investigation into the reasons for restoring her.</p>
      </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Negro Boy’s Narrative.</head>
            <p>My father’s name was <persName ref="#clashoquin">Clashoquin</persName>; mine is <persName ref="#louis_asaasa">Asa-Asa</persName>. He lived in a country called <placeName>Bycla</placeName>,
               near <placeName>Egie</placeName>, a large town. <rs type="place">Egie</rs> is as large as <placeName>Brighton</placeName>; it was some way from the sea. I
               had <ecda:persGroup>five brothers and sisters</ecda:persGroup>. We all lived together with <rs type="person" ref="#clashoquin">my father</rs> and <rs type="person">mother</rs>; he kept
               a horse, and was respectable, but not one of the great men. My <rs type="person" ref="#otou">uncle</rs> was one of the
               great men at <placeName>Egie</placeName>: he could make men come and work for him: his name was <persName ref="#otou">Otou</persName>. He had a
               great deal of land and cattle. <rs type="person" ref="#clashoquin">My father</rs> sometimes worked on his own land, and used to
               make <ecda:commodity>charcoal</ecda:commodity>. I was too little to work; my <rs type="person">eldest brother</rs> used to work on the land; and
               we were all very happy. A great many people, whom we called <name>Adinyés</name>, set fire to
               <placeName>Egie</placeName> in the morning before daybreak; there were some thousands of them. They killed a
               great many, and burnt all their houses. They staid two days, and then carried away all
               the people whom they did not kill.</p>
            <p>They came again every now and then for a month, as long as they could find people to
               carry away. They used to tie them by the feet, except when they were taking them off,
               and then they let them loose; but if they offered to run away, they would shoot them. I
               lost a great many friends and relations at <placeName>Egie</placeName>; about a dozen. They sold all they
               carried away, to be slaves. I know this because I afterwards saw them as slaves on the
               other side of the sea. They took away brothers, and sisters, and husbands, and wives;
               they did not care about this. They were sold for <ecda:commodity>cloth</ecda:commodity> or <ecda:commodity>gunpowder</ecda:commodity>, sometimes for <ecda:commodity>salt</ecda:commodity>
               or <ecda:commodity>guns</ecda:commodity>; sometimes they got four or five guns for a man: they were English guns, made
               like my master’s that I clean for his shooting. The <name>Adinyés</name> burnt a great many places
               besides <placeName>Egie</placeName>. They burnt all the country wherever they found villages; they used to
               shoot men, women, and children, if they ran away.</p>
            <p>They came to us about eleven o’clock one day, and directly they came they set our house
               on fire. All of us had run away. We kept together, and went into the woods, and stopped
               there two days. The <name>Adinyés</name> then went away, and we returned home and found every thing
               burnt. We tried to build a little shed, and were beginning to get comfortable again.
               We found several of <ecda:persGroup>our neighbours</ecda:persGroup> lying about wounded; they had been shot. I saw the
               bodies of <ecda:persGroup>four or five little children</ecda:persGroup> whom they had killed with blows on the head. They
               had carried away their fathers and mothers, but the children were too small for slaves,
               so they killed them. They had killed several others, but these were all that I saw. I
               saw them lying in the street like dead dogs. In about a week after we got back, the
               <name>Adinyés</name> returned, and burnt all the sheds and houses they had left standing. We all ran
               away again; we went to the woods as we had done before.—They followed us the next day.
               We went farther into the woods, and staid there about four days and nights; we were half
               starved; we only got a few potatoes. My <persName ref="#otou">uncle Otou</persName> was with us. At the end of this time,
               the <name>Adinyés</name> found us. We ran away. They called <rs type="person" ref="#otou">my uncle</rs> to go to them; but he refused,
               and they shot him immediately: they killed him. The rest of us ran on, and they did not
               get at us till the next day. I ran up into a tree: they followed me and brought me down.
               They tied my feet. I do not know if they found <rs type="person" ref="clashoquin">my father</rs> and <rs type="person">mother</rs>, and <rs type="persGroup">brothers</rs> and
               <rs type="persGroup">sisters</rs>: they had run faster than me, and were half a mile farther when I got up into
               the tree: I have never seen them since.—There was <ecda:anonPers>a man</ecda:anonPers> who ran up into the tree with
               me: I believe they shot him, for I never saw him again. They carried away about
               twenty besides me. They carried us to the sea. They did not beat us: they only killed
               <ecda:anonPers>one man</ecda:anonPers>, who was very ill and too weak to carry his load: they made all of us carry
               <ecda:food ana="animal">chickens</ecda:food> and <ecda:food>meat</ecda:food> for our food; but this poor man could not carry his load, and they ran
               him through the body with a sword.—He was a neighbour of ours. When we got to the sea
               they sold all of us, but not to the same person. They sold us for money; and I was sold
               six times over, sometimes for money, sometimes for <ecda:commodity>cloth</ecda:commodity>, and sometimes for <ecda:commodity>a gun</ecda:commodity>. I was
               about thirteen years old. It was about half a year from the time I was taken, before I
               saw the white people.</p>
            <p>We were taken in a boat from place to place, and sold at every place we stopped at. In
               about six months we got to a ship, in which we first saw <ecda:persGroup>white people</ecda:persGroup>: they were <name>French</name>.
               They bought us. We found here a great <ecda:persGroup>many other slaves</ecda:persGroup>; there were about eighty,
               including women and children. The <ecda:anonPers>Frenchmen</ecda:anonPers> sent away all but five of us into another
               very large ship. We five staid on board till we got to <placeName>England</placeName>, which was about five or
               six months. The <ecda:persGroup>slaves we saw on board</ecda:persGroup> the ship were chained together by the legs below
               deck, so close they could not move. They were flogged very cruelly: I saw one of them
               flogged till he died; we could not tell what for. They gave them enough to eat. The
               place they were confined in below deck was so hot and nasty I could not bear to be in
               it. A great many of the slaves were ill, but they were not attended to. They used to
               flog me very bad on board the ship: <rs type="person">the captain</rs> cut my head very bad one time.</p>
            <p>“<said>I am very happy to be in <placeName>England</placeName>, as far as I am very well;—but I have no friend
               belonging to me, but God, who will take care of me as he has done already. I am very
               glad I have come to <placeName>England</placeName>, to know who God is. I should like much to see my friends
               again, but I do not now wish to go back to them: for if I go back to my own <rs type="place">country</rs>,
               I might be taken as a slave again. I would rather stay here, where I am free, than go
               back to my country to be sold. I shall stay in England as long as (please God) I shall
               live. I wish the <persName ref="#william_iv">King of England</persName> could know all I have told you. I wish it that he may
               see how cruelly we are used. We had no king in our country, or he would have stopt it. I
               think the king of England might stop it, and this is why I wish him to know it all. I
               have heard say he is good; and if he is, he will stop it if he can. I am well off
               myself, for I am well taken care of, and have good bed and good clothes; but I wish my
               own people to be as comfortable.</said>”</p>
            <p>“LOUIS ASA-ASA.”</p>
            <p>"<placeName>London</placeName>, January 31, 1831.”</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      
  </text>
</TEI>
