<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memoir of the Life of Florence Hall</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <ecda:hyperDiv>
        <ecda:notes>
           <note type="ecda">
              <interpGrp type="commType">
                 <interp xml:id="flora">plants (flora)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="fauna">animals (fauna)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="food">food and other consumable items (incl. drinks, seasonings, etc.)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="medical">medical or medicinal items (including references to folk medicine)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="textile">sartorial and textile references</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="currency">references to money or currency</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp type="productionPhase">
                 <interp xml:id="plant">planting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="cultivation">cultivation</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="harvest">harvesting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="refine">refining</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="production">production (non plant-based commodities)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="transport">transport</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="sale">sale</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="circulation">circulation of commodities, such as through gift-giving or theft</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="use">use of commodities</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp>
                 <interp xml:id="punishment">References to scenes of punishment or the enforcement of colonial rule</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="military">References to the material conditions, social institutions or actual events of warfare</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="abolition">References to the abolition of slavery or abolitionist movement</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="disease">References to ailment and disease, specifically in people</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="poison">References to poison</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="obeah">References to Obeah</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="performance">References to performance (esp. John Canoe)</interp>
              </interpGrp>
          </note>
        </ecda:notes>
     </ecda:hyperDiv>
     
     
     <front>
        <titleBlock>
           <docTitle>
              <titlePart></titlePart>
           </docTitle>
           
        </titleBlock>
     </front>
     
      <body>
        
         <p><placeName>Africa</placeName> is my Country—In the Country of the <name>Eboe</name> and on the
            banks of the great_____ river, my people lived. The manner of my life before I was
            taken and sold to the white people I can scarcely remember beyond that I was still
            unclothed, sometime employed in attending our people, while engaged in Fishing, at
            other times guarding the <ecda:fauna>fowls</ecda:fauna> and <ecda:fauna>chickens</ecda:fauna> from <ecda:fauna>Hawks</ecda:fauna> or more frequently at play
            with other children. In one of those evening plays, while at a distance from our
            houses a party of the enemy came around [‘us’ is crossed out] and drove us, into an
            enclosed place, and immediately secured us—our hands were tied—in vain our cries and
            screams were raised, but raised unheard, if heard, unattended, and by force we were
            hurried along and rested not until the sun arose and marked our <unclear>[dis….?]</unclear> and distance
            from our homes. The day we lay concealed, and in the night our journey was performed.
            Day and night succeeded each other, in hunger, weariness, and grief at the end of the
            15th night our traveling was at an end and the dawn of the day shewed us the Great
            sea, and the ship, <unclear>on/to</unclear> which we were soon embarked and atonce <unclear>[another word
            beginning with a c is crossed out]</unclear> left our <rs type="place">Country</rs>, and our freedom, and consigned
            to foreigners and Slavery. The enemies of our country seized and sold us to the White
            people, for the love of drink, and from the quarrels of their chiefs—The white people
            received and stripped us of all our beads, and shells and while the naked children
            were permitted to walk about the ship, the men and women were chained and kept in
            dark[<unclear>ness?</unclear>] below [<unclear>replaced dark places</unclear>]. Our <ecda:food>food</ecda:food> was sparing, and ever bad. Our
            punishment was frequent and sever and death became so frequent an occurrence, that at
            last it <unclear>???</unclear> on, without fear on the dying, or grief on those left behind, as we
            believed that those who died, were restored to their people and Country. A long
            voyage at length brought the ship to <placeName>Jamaica</placeName> [another name seems to be crossed out,
            maybe Barbados?]. My <name>Eboe</name> name was <persName ref="#florence_hall">Akeiso</persName>. The <unclear>something</unclear> of which soon put an end
            to all [<unclear>all is added</unclear>] recollections of my people—another name—a strange language, and
            [<unclear>another, is crossed out</unclear>] a new master confused my mind, and while ignorance of each,
            made my labour more troublesome, yet the dread of punishment compelled me to work,
            [narrative ends abruptly here with the comma following work].</p>
      </body>
      
  </text>
</TEI>
