<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <ecda:hyperDiv>
        <ecda:notes>
           <note type="ecda">
              <interpGrp type="commType">
                 <interp xml:id="flora">plants (flora)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="fauna">animals (fauna)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="food">food and other consumable items (incl. drinks, seasonings, etc.)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="medical">medical or medicinal items (including references to folk medicine)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="textile">sartorial and textile references</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="currency">references to money or currency</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp type="productionPhase">
                 <interp xml:id="plant">planting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="cultivation">cultivation</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="harvest">harvesting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="refine">refining</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="production">production (non plant-based commodities)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="transport">transport</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="sale">sale</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="circulation">circulation of commodities, such as through gift-giving or theft</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="use">use of commodities</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp>
                 <interp xml:id="punishment">References to scenes of punishment or the enforcement of colonial rule</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="military">References to the material conditions, social institutions or actual events of warfare</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="abolition">References to the abolition of slavery or abolitionist movement</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="disease">References to ailment and disease, specifically in people</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="poison">References to poison</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="obeah">References to Obeah</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="performance">References to performance (esp. John Canoe)</interp>
              </interpGrp>
          </note>
        </ecda:notes>
     </ecda:hyperDiv>
     
     
     <front>
        <titleBlock>
           <docTitle>
              <titlePart></titlePart>
           </docTitle>
           
        </titleBlock>
     </front>
     
      <body>
         <div type="section">
      
         <p>I saw the OBI of the famous robber, <hi rend="italic">Three fingered JACK</hi>, the terror
            of Jamaica in 1780. The Maroons who flew him brought it to me*.
            <note>He was slain on Saturday 27th of January, 1781.</note></p>
            <p>His OBI consisted of the end of a goat's horn, filled with a
               compound of grave dirt, ashes, the blood of a black cat, and
               human fat; all mixed into a kind of paste. A cat's foot, a dried
               toad, a pig's tail, a slip of virginial parchment of kid's skin,
               with characters marked in blood on it, were also in his <hi
                  rend="italic">Obian</hi>
               bag.
            </p>
            <p>These, with a keen sabre, and two guns, like <hi
               rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe</hi>, were all his OBI; with which,
            and his courage in descending into the plains and plundering to
            supply his wants, and his skill in retreating into difficult
            fastnesses, among the mountains, commanding the only access to them,
            where none dared to follow him, he terrified the inhabitants, and
            set the civil power, and the neighbouring militia  
         <pb n="198"/>
              of that island, at defiance, for nearly two years.
            </p>
            <p>He had neither accomplice, nor associate. There were a few
               runaway negroes in the woods near Mount Lebanus, the place of his
               retreat; but he had crossed their foreheads with some of the
               magic in his horn, and they count not betray him. But he trusted
               no one. He scorned assistance. He ascended above SPARTACUS. He
               robbed alone; fought all his battles alone; and always killed his
               pursuers.
            </p>
            <p>
               By his magic, he was not only the dread of the negroes, but there
               were many white people, who believed he was possessed of some
               supernatural powers. 
            </p>
            <p>In hot climates females marry very young; and often with great
               disparity of age. Here JACK was the author of many troubles; —for
               several matches proved unhappy.</p>
            <p>
               "Give a dog an ill name, and hang him."
            </p>
            <p>
               Clamours rose on clamours against the cruel sorcerer; and every
               conjugal mishap was laid at the door of JACK'S malific spell of
               <hi rend="italic">tying the point</hi>, on the wedding day.
            </p>
            <p>GOD knows, poor JACK had sins enough of his own to carry, without
               loading him with the sins of others. He would sooner have made a
               <hi rend="italic">Mcdean</hi> cauldron for the whole island, <pb
                  n="199"/> than disturb one lady's happiness. He had many
               opportunities; and, though he had a mortal hatred to white men,
               he was never known to hurt a child, or abuse a woman.</p>
            <p>But even JACK himself was born to die.</p>
            <p>Allured by the rewards offered by Governor DALLING, in
               proclamations, dated the 12th of December, in 1780, and 13th of
               January, 1781*;<note><p>BY THE KING. A PROCLAMATION.</p><p> 
              Whereas we have been informed by our House of Assembly of this our
              Island of Jamaica, that a very desperate gang of Negro Slaves,
              headed by a Negro Man Slave called and known by the name of
              <hi rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>, hath, for many months
                  past, committed many robberies, and carried off many Negro and
                  other Slaves on the Windward roads into the woods, and hath
                  also committed several murders; and that repeated parties have
                  been fitted out and sent against the said <hi
                     rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>, and also a further
                  reward for apprehending each and every Negro Man Slave
                  belonging to the said gang, and delivering him or them to any
                  of the gaolers in this Island; And whereas, we have since
                  received another message from our said House of Assembly,
                  requesting us to offer an additional reward of <hi
                     rend="italic">Two Hundred
                  Pounds</hi>, as a further encouragement for the apprehending,
                  or bringing in the head of that daring Rebel, called <hi
                     rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>, who hath hitherto
                  eluded every attempt against him; We, having taken the same
                  into our consideration, have thought fit to issue this our
                  Royal Proclamation, hereby strictly charging and commanding,
                  and we do hereby strictly charge and command, all and every
                  our loving subjects within our said Island, to pursue and
                  apprehend, or cause to be pursued and apprehended, the body of
                  the said Negro Man named <hi rend="italic">Three-fingered
                     JACK</hi>, and also of each and every Negro Man Slave
                  belonging to the said gang, and deliver him or them to any of
                  the gaolers of this Island. And we do, at the influence of our
                  said House of Assembly, offer a reward of <hi
                     rend="italic">One Hundred Pounds</hi>, and at the like
                  instance a further reward of <hi rend="italic">Two Hundred
                     Pounds</hi>, to be paid to the person or persons who shall
                  so apprehend and take the body of the said Negro called <hi
                     rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>. And we do, at the
                  instance of our said House of Assembly, offer a further reward
                  of <hi rend="italic">Five Pounds</hi>, over and above what is
                  allowed by law, for apprending each and every Negro Man Slave
                  belonging to said gang, and delivering him or them to any of
                  the gaolers of this Island, to be dealth with according to
                  law. </p>
                  <p>Witness his Excellency, JOHN DALLING, Esquire,
                     Captain-General and Governor in Chief of our said Island of
                     Jamaica, and other the Territories thereon depending in
                     America, Chancellor and Vice-Admiral of the same, at Saint
                     Jago de la Vega, the thirteenth day of January, in the
                     twenty0first year of our reign, annoque Domini one thousand
                     seven hundred and eighty-one. </p>
                  <p>JOHN DALLING</p>
                  <p>By his Excellency's command,</p>
                  <p>R. Lewing, Sec.</p>
                  <p>GOD SAVE THE KING.</p>
            </note>
              and, by a resolution of the House of <pb n="200"/>Assembly*,
               <note>
                 <p>*HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY, 29TH DECEMBER, 1780 </p>
                 <p>RESOLVED, that, over and above the reward of one hundred
                    pounds offered by his Majesty's proclamation for taking or
                    killing the rebellious Negro called <hi
                       rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>, the further
                    reward of FREEDOM shall be given to any slave that shall
                    take or kill the said <hi
                       rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>, and that the
                    House will make good the value of such slave to the
                    proprieter thereof. And if any one of his accomplices will
                    kill the said <hi rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>,
                    and bring in his head, and hand wanting the fingers, such
                    accomplice shall be entitled to his <hi
                       rend="italic">free</hi> PARDON, and his <hi
                          rend="italic">FREEDOM</hi> as above, upon due proof
                    being made of their being the head and hand of the said <hi
                       rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi>.  </p>
                 <p>By the House, </p>
                 <p>SAMUEL HOWELL, Cl. Assem.</p>
              </note>
               which followed the first proclamation; two negroes, named
               Quashee, and <pb n="201"/> SAM (SAM was Captain Davy's son, he
               who shot a Mr. THOMPSON, the master of a London ship, at Old
               Harbour), both of <hi rend="italic">Scots Hall</hi> Maroon Town,
               with a party of their townsmen, went in search of him.</p>
            <p>QUASHEE, before he set out on the expedition, got himself
               christianed, and changed his name to JAMES REEDER.
            </p>
            <p>The expedition commenced; and the whole party had been creeping
               about in the woods, for three weeks, and bloacking, as it were,
               the deepest recesses of the most inaccessible part of the
               island, where JACK, far remote from all human society,
               resides,—but in vain.</p>
            <p>REEDER and SAM, tired with this mode of war, resolved on
               proceeding in search of his retreat; and taking him by storming
               it, or perishing in the attempt.</p>
            <p>They took with them a little boy, a proper spirit, and a good
               shot, and left the rest of the party.</p>
            <pb n="202"/>
            <p>These three, whom I well knew, had not been long separated from
               their companions, before their cunning eyes discovered, by
               impressions among the weeds and bushes, that some person must
               have lately been that way.</p>
            <p>They softly followed these impressions, making not the least
               noise. Presently they discovered a smoke.</p>
            <p>They prepared for war. They came upon JACK before he perceived
               them. He was roasting <hi rend="italic">plantains</hi>, by a
               little fire on the ground, at the mouth of a cave.</p>
            <p>This was a scene:—not where ordinary actors had a common part to
               play.</p>
            <p>JACK'S looks were fierce and terrible. He told them he would kill
               them.</p>
            <p>REEDER, instead of shooting Jack, replied, that his OBI had no
               power to hurt him; for he was christianed; and that his name was
               no longer QUASHEE.</p>
            <p>JACK new REEDER; and, as if paralyzed, he let his two guns remain
               on the ground, and took up only his cutlass.</p>
            <p>These two had a severe engagement several years before, in the
               woods; in which conflict JACK lost the two fingers, which was the
               origin of his present name; but JACK then beat REEDER, and almost
               killed him, with several <pb n="203"/> offers who assisted him,
               and they fled from JACK.</p>
            <p>To do <hi rend="italic">Three-fingered JACK</hi> justice, he
               would now have killed both REEDER and SAM; for, at first, they
               were frightened at the sight of him, and the dreadful tone of his
               voice; and well theymight: they had besides no retreat, and were
               to grapple with the bravet, and strongest man in the world.</p>
            <p>But JACK was cowed; for, he had prophesied, that <hi
               rend="italic">white</hi> OBI would get the better of him; and,
               from experience, he kenw the charm would lose none of its
               strength in the hands of REEDER. </p>
            <p>Without farther parley, JACK, with his cutlass in his hand, threw
               himself down a precipice at the back of the cave.</p>
            <p>REEDER'S gun missed fire. SAM shot him in the shoulder. REEDER,
               like an English bull-dog, never looked, but, with his cutlass in
               his hand, plunged headlong down after JACK. The descent was about
               thirty yards, and almost perpendicular. Both of them had
               preserved their cutlasses in the fall.</p>
            <p>Here was the stage,—on which two of the stoutest hearts, that
               were ever hooped with ribs, began their bloody struggle.</p>
            <pb n="204"/>
            <p>The little boy, who was ordered to keep back, out of harm's way,
               now reached the top of the precipice, and, during the fight, shot
               JACK in the belly.</p>
            <p>SAM was crafty, and cooly took a round-about way to get to the
               field of action. When he arrived at the spot where it began, JACK
               and REEDER had closed, and tumbled together down another
               precipice, on the side of the mountain, in which fall they both
               lost their weapons.</p>
            <p>SAM descended after them, who also lost his cutlass, among the
               trees and bushes in getting down.</p>
            <p>When he came to them, though without weapons, they were not idle;
               and, luckily for REEDER, JACK'S wounds were deep and desperate,
               and he was in great agony.</p>
            <p>SAM came up just time enough to save REEDER; for, JACK had caught
               him by the throat, with his giant's grasp. REEDER then was with
               his right hand almost cut off, and JACK streaming with blood from
               his shoulder and belly; both covered with gore and gashes.</p>
            <p>In this state SAM was umpire; and decided the fate of the battle.
               He knocked JACK down with a piece of a rock.</p>
            <pb n="205"/>
            <p>When the lion fell, the two tigerts got upon him, and beat his
               brains out with stones.</p>
            <p>The little boy soon after found his way to them. He had a
               cutlass, with which they cut off JACK'S head, and THREE-FINGERED
               HAND, and took them in triumph to Morant Bay.</p>
            <p>There they put their trophies into a pail of rum; and, followed
               by a vast concourse of negroes, now no longer afraid of JACK'S
               OBI, blowing their shells and horns, and firing guns in their
               rude method, they carried them to Kingston, and Spanish Town; and
               claimed the rewards offered by the King's Proclamation, and the
               House of Assembly.</p>
         </div>
      
      </body>
      
  </text>
</TEI>
