<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <ecda:hyperDiv>
        <ecda:notes>
           <note type="ecda">
              <interpGrp type="commType">
                 <interp xml:id="flora">plants (flora)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="fauna">animals (fauna)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="food">food and other consumable items (incl. drinks, seasonings, etc.)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="medical">medical or medicinal items (including references to folk medicine)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="textile">sartorial and textile references</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="currency">references to money or currency</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp type="productionPhase">
                 <interp xml:id="plant">planting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="cultivation">cultivation</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="harvest">harvesting</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="refine">refining</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="production">production (non plant-based commodities)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="transport">transport</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="sale">sale</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="circulation">circulation of commodities, such as through gift-giving or theft</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="use">use of commodities</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp>
                 <interp xml:id="punishment">References to scenes of punishment or the enforcement of colonial rule</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="military">References to the material conditions, social institutions or actual events of warfare</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="abolition">References to the abolition of slavery or abolitionist movement</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="disease">References to ailment and disease, specifically in people</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="poison">References to poison</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="obeah">References to Obeah</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="performance">References to performance (esp. John Canoe)</interp>
              </interpGrp>
           </note>
        </ecda:notes>
     </ecda:hyperDiv>
     <front>
        <titleBlock>
           <docTitle>
              <titlePart>HAMEL.</titlePart>
           </docTitle>
           
        </titleBlock>
     </front>
     
      <body>
         <head>HAMEL.</head>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb/>
            <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
            <ab type="epigraph"><lg><l>Yet hold! for oh! this prologue lets me in</l>
            <l>To a most fatal tragedy to come.</l></lg> <persName>Richard III</persName>.</ab>
            
            <p>At the close of a sultry day in the month of
            October, in the year one thousand eight hundred 
            and twenty-two; or rather at the moment when 
            the sun (whose fiery ardour had not been moderated
            in any part of his course by the least zephyr
            of the sea breeze) had just sunk behind the emerald
            summits of <placeName ref="#blue_mountains">the Blue Mountain</placeName>, and relieved 
            from his scorching rays those <rs type="persGroup">Europeans</rs> who
            toil on the northern shores of <placeName ref="#jamaica">Jamaica</placeName>; <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">a person</rs>
            who (from some circumstances about to be explained)
            appeared to be <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">a stranger</rs>, was seen
            riding along the western bank of the <placeName ref="#rio_grande">Rio Grande</placeName>,
            that clear and beautiful stream which hurrying
            
            <fw>VOL I.</fw>
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">2</fw>
            
            down from the wildernesses of the island, carries
            the torrents of its highest mountains to the
            <placeName ref="#atlantic_ocean">Atlantic</placeName>. <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">The stranger</rs> seemed to be seeking a 
            ford, and strove from time to time to prevail on 
            a sulky-looking <ecda:fauna>Spanish horse</ecda:fauna>, which bore him
            without manifesting any satisfaction at his burthen, 
            to venture through the deep and rapid 
            current; but it was evident that <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the rider</rs> and his 
            steed were of two minds on the point, and that
            the pertinacity of the latter was more than a match
            for the hesitating and undecided anxiety of the 
            former; whose timidity, arising from inexperience
            of the river, induced him not to press his beast
            into the flood against that instinct to which he
            preferred to trust his fortune on the present
            occasion.</p>
      
            <p><rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">The rider</rs> was accoutred in a black coat, cut
            straight, or it might be of a dingy grey, with
            black cloth buttons, and a waistcoat of the same.
            His trowsers were of brown holland, tucked into 
            a huge pair of spatterdashes, buttoned above his
            knee, as a defence against the bites of <ecda:fauna>musquitos</ecda:fauna>.
            He wore a large brimmed hat, slouched by
            many a tropical shower, and rendered rusty by
            constant exposure to the tropical sun, although
            at present he carried an umbrella secured in the 
            straps of a portmanteau mounted behind him on
            his <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna>'s crupper; and his great-coat, of the 
            same sombre hue as his other vestments, was fast-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">3</fw>
            
            ended upon his saddle bow. He was attended by a 
            bare-legged <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">negro boy</rs> on foot, dressed in an Osnaburgh
            frock and drawers, which, with a glazed hat
            on his head, formed the whole of his costume.
            <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">The boy</rs> hung on sometimes to his <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs>'s stirrup, 
            that he might keep pace with the <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna>; and 
            sometimes, falling into the rear, brought himself
            up by grasping the animal's long tail; a liberty
            the beast admitted with an occasional affectation
            of elevating his croupe and lowering his ears,—
            intimations that he had a right to kick (though
            he did not at present) as well understood by
            young <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> as expressed by the <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna>.</p>
            
            <p>This <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">youngster</rs>'s features scarcely harmonized 
            with those of his very demure and melancholy looking
            <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs>, whose pale and cadaverous countenance 
            indicated something more than bodily 
            mortification and fatigue. His eyes, black and
            penetrating, were shadowed by brows that had 
            once been dark as the skin of his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">follower</rs>, but
            now, with the locks that strayed in right lines
            from under his huge castor, exhibited the mingled 
            hues of black and grey; his nose was sharp and 
            aquiline; and his mouth, though rather of the 
            largest, by no means badly formed, was furnished 
            with a set of short but regular teeth, as white as
            those of <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName>, whose happy physiognomy bespoke
            the innocence and kindness of his heart,
            and relieved that of the spectator from the sym-
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">4</fw> 
            
            pathy of sadness inspired by the looks of <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the 
            white-faced traveller</rs>. Yet the gloom on the 
            cheek of this last was not attributable perhaps to 
            any dignified grief or sentimentality of disposition
            —at least his features did not augur any such 
            feeling; nor to age, for he was by some years
            short of forty. Anxiety of mind, as well as fatigue
            of body, natural irritability, and pecuniary cares,
            will impress even on a more juvenile countenance
            those lines which, visible there only, are channelled 
            by time and memory on the invisible and wasted
            heart. Whether this were the case in the present
            instance, will be seen in the course of our narrative.</p>
            
            <p><rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">The stranger</rs> and his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">footman</rs> continued their
            route for some distance beside the river, halting
            again and again to compare notes as to the fordability
            of several spots, where the latter declared
            he could see the track of <ecda:fauna>mules</ecda:fauna> and <ecda:fauna>horses</ecda:fauna>,
            which he thought had crossed from the other
            side; but his <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs> imagined them to be only
            indications of the cattle having been there to 
            drink or cool themselves, and referred the point 
            invariably to his <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna>, who, however anxious to
            drink or roll in the stream, always manifested the 
            same unwillingness to traverse it. The evening
            was closing in rapidly, and <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the traveller</rs>, impatient 
            at last of his beast's fears or obstinacy, had
            directed his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">valet</rs> to strip and try a ford, which,
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">5</fw>
            
            as he could distinguish by marks on the opposite
            side, was certainly used at times; when
            <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> who was already half across the river, 
            called to his <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs> that he could see some 
            <rs type="persGroup">Negroes</rs> coming down the hills from the interior
            towards a row of stones or rocks placed a little 
            farther up the winding current, for the convenience 
            of foot passengers, which had been hidden
            from their view by the <rs ana="flora">trees</rs> growing on its banks.</p>
            
            <p>To this rudest of rude bridges <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the traveller</rs> 
            and his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">boy</rs> advanced without delay, being anxious
            no doubt to leave the river behind them,
            and hurry to their quarters, yet at some miles 
            distance beyond it, if possible before nightfall; 
            and they had just gained the bridge in question, 
            when they were saluted by <rs type="persGroup">the Negroes</rs>, who 
            were coming down from their provision grounds 
            with <ecda:food>yams</ecda:food>, <ecda:food>cocos</ecda:food>, and various <ecda:food>fruits</ecda:food> for the 
            next day's market on their heads. There was an 
            excellent ford just above the stepping stones, 
            which the cantancrous <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna> was compelled to 
            pass, <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> still leading the way; and <rs type="persGroup">the Negroes</rs> 
            furnished them with abundant directions to the 
            settlement for which the traveller inquired, though
            accompanied with a piece of intelligence not 
            altogether so welcome, as <said direct="false">they intimated a report 
            that the said settlement had been deserted since 
            the death of its <ecda:anonPers>proprietor</ecda:anonPers>, whose <ecda:anonPers>widow</ecda:anonPers> had 
            gone down to <placeName ref="#port_antonio">Port Antonio</placeName>, while his <rs type="persGroup">slaves</rs>,
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">6</fw> 
            
            some eighteen or twenty, had run away into the 
            woods.</said></p>
            
            <p>Notwithstanding this information, <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the traveller</rs>'s 
            countenance brightened very visibly at sight
            of <rs type="persGroup">some young negro girls</rs> of the party, to each 
            of whom <said direct="false">he had something agreeable to say—some
            compliment to their persons</said>, attended with a 
            cavalier and rather equivocal expression of his 
            eyes, which raised a smile on the lips of <rs type="persGroup">the 
            sable beauties</rs>, and <said direct="false">elicited some rather diverting 
            remarks from them on the discrepancy between 
            his language and his looks</said>. One of them, who 
            <said direct="false">said she was handmaid to her mistress, observed 
            that he smelt sweet like her lady's washball</said>; and 
            <said direct="false">most of them remarked on the perfumed state of 
            his person</said>, to which it must be avowed he was not 
            inattentive: and whether they were cosmetics, or 
            preparations for the hair, or essences to gratify 
            his own olfactory nerves, which he breathed, he 
            was, in fact, <hi rend="quotes">perfumed like a milliner</hi>.</p>
            
            <p>Yet in the midst of these odours <said direct="false">he asked <rs type="persGroup">the 
            young girls</rs> whether they were married; and if 
            married, whether the ceremony had been performed 
            by a priest or a missionary, or whether 
            they were married after the African fashion. He
            enquired too about their soul's grace, their work, 
            profits, punishments:—whether they expected to 
            be free, and how many Mulatto and Quadroon 
            girls there were on their master's estate, and if 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">7</fw>
            
            his daughter were handsome; and then relapsed 
            into some rather spiritual advice, mingled with a 
            few allusions to the worm which dieth not, and 
            the fire which is not quenched.</said></p>
            
            <p><rs type="persGroup">The girls</rs> began to think him an unaccountable 
            <distinct>buckra</distinct>, and rather affected with insanity; more 
            especially as he persisted in his intention of proceeding 
            to the settlement of which they had given 
            him such an unfavourable account, and refused 
            their assurance, on the part of their master or the 
            overseer, of good quarters and hospitable entertainment 
            for the night. <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> would fain have 
            seconded their arguments, but his <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs> silenced 
            him with a gloomy frown; and after a few more 
            desultory observations to <rs type="persGroup">the women</rs>, with some 
            of whom he chose to shake hands, the head of 
            <ecda:fauna>the Spanish steed</ecda:fauna> was turned toward the mountains; 
            and <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> again seizing its tail, master and 
            man resumed their course. The short twilight 
            expired, and the shadows of night rendered still 
            more sombre the forlorn and unfrequented path 
            along which they journeyed.</p>
            
            <pb/>
            </div>
            <!-- There are pages missing in the PDF -->
            
            <div type="chapter"> <!-- Chapter 2 starts on the missing pages -->
            <fw type="pageNum">10</fw>
            
            <p>he had left, and lingered onwards most reluctantly, 
            in spite of sundry kicks bestowed on his 
            ribs by his fractious <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs>, whose impatience 
            increased with the storm which already penetrated 
            through his garments. A tropical wetting is but 
            too often precursor and cause of those baleful 
            fevers which are almost the only curse upon the 
            otherwise blissful climate of the <placeName ref="#antilles">Antilles</placeName>,—blissful 
            in the idea of the inhabitants; and our <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">traveller</rs>, 
            already initiated in the miseries of this scourge, 
            was but too full of apprehensions and forebodings, 
            as he felt the tempest invade him to the skin.</p>
            
            <p>The thoughts of a sick bed, or sickness without 
            a bed, without medicine, in an abandoned 
            dwelling in the midst of the jungle, as it was 
            represented to him, crowded fast on his perturbed 
            imagination, which now first reproached him for 
            the expedition he had undertaken, although the 
            feeling was purely selfish: however, it was of short 
            duration; the uproar of the elements increased 
            so rapidly and violently, that all apprehensions 
            for the past or the future quickly yielded to more 
            immediate fears for his present personal safety. 
            They had been for some time ascending, and had 
            now gained the summit of a steep hill, whence 
            the road began to descend as abruptly into another 
            dingle, through which they could discover, by the 
            occasional flashes of lightning, a river of more 
            importance than the many petty streams they 
           
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">11</fw>
            
            had already crossed. This was indeed the <placeName ref="#rio_grande">Rio 
            Grande</placeName> again, but little inferior in magnitude to 
            the volume of water it had presented to them 
            some miles below; and how were they to pass it? 
            or how indeed were they to reach it? The road, 
            scarcely three feet wide, wound along the side of a 
            precipice, against which the wind raged with such 
            fury, and the rain beat so spitefully, that the <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna> 
            for a long time refused to face either of them, and 
            was at last driven down into the valley by <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs> 
            and <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">man</rs> on foot, urging him with sticks, and 
            preventing him from turning round in the narrow 
            path, so slippery and precipitous that he slid 
            down the last portion of it on his hind quarters, 
            and rolled over and over into the narrow plain 
            below, bursting his girths and scattering abroad 
            his harness and the portmanteau, umbrella, and 
            great coat. These were, however, readjusted 
            with a promptitude inspired by the occasion, and 
            with a resolution which was little else than the 
            effect of despair; the river was passed in comparative 
            safety; <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName>, who led the <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna>, only 
            stumbling occasionally over the loose rocks which 
            strewed its channel. But scarcely had they 
            reached the <distinct xml:lang="la">terra firma</distinct> on the other side, when 
            <rs ref="cuffy_0001" type="person">the terrified boy</rs> cried out that the earth shook 
            beneath him, and ran up the path which they had 
            found, as if he expected the river to rise and 
            arrest him, or hurry him with its waters down its 
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">12</fw> 
               
            impetuous current. The <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna>, no less alarmed, 
            or afraid of losing his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">negro guide and friend</rs>, 
            hastened after him. Another eminence was gained, 
            from whence a track of fire was driving apparently at a 
            great distance before the wind. "Earthquakes 
            are not uncommon," thought <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the traveller</rs>; "but 
            fire—this must be produced by human means." 
            <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> thought otherwise; more especially when 
            he descried other fires in different directions, and 
            one or two now and then flashing into view at no 
            very great apparent distance. The earth shook 
            again; and the wind, as if it had still reserved 
            some of its power for an effort of desperation, 
            burst on them with such exasperated fury, that 
            it seemed impossible to make farther progress 
            against it. <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> clung to the boughs and the 
            rocks beside him; and his master being fain to 
            follow his example, the steed, with equipage, 
            was left to the mercy of the elements, from 
            which they saw him gradually recede to the 
            distance of fifty or sixty yards, like a ship 
            driving at her anchors and going bodily to leeward, 
            until he was lost in the darkness. <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName>, 
            true to his trust, abandoned his hold to keep 
            sight of his master's baggage; while his master, 
            encumbered with his spatterdashes, and fearful of 
            following the fate of his Bucephalus, encouraged 
            his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">valet</rs> to stand by the horse, and took a firmer
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">13</fw>
            
            grasp of the rocks from which he sought protecion. 
            Often and often was his voice lost in the 
            tumult of the storm, as he shouted to his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">boy</rs> for 
            some assurance of his safety. No answer reached 
            his ears—no sound but that of the elements 
            raging as if to produce a second chaos, thunder 
            and wind, the roaring of the augmented waterfalls, 
            the rumbling of the rocks which they loosed 
            from their beds, the creaking and crashing of 
            falling trees. It was in vain that the lightning at 
            every other instant illuminated the scene with its 
            partial flashes, now here, now there: it gleamed 
            only on mountains uncultivated and uninhabited, 
            (except perhaps by a few outlawed runaways who 
            lived by a predatory warfare on the wild hogs and 
            pigeons of the desart,) on naked precipices and 
            foaming torrents, or on the giant <rs ana="flora">trees</rs> of the forest 
            quivering beneath the blast of the hurricane. Then 
            came down the rain, not as in the temperate zone 
            even in its most weeping seasons, when the spectator 
            would fain imagine a second deluge; but 
            torrents, sheets of water, seemed to rush from the 
            clouds, and threaten the annihilation of all life 
            beneath the sky. The forlorn and dispirited <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">traveller</rs>, 
            still clinging to the rocks which yielded 
            him a partial and precarious kind of security, had 
            groped his way along them to a chink, in whose 
            recesses he flattered himself with an idea of 
            weathering the storm till daylight, drenched—
            
               
            <pb/> 
            <fw type="pageNum">14</fw> 
            
            nay, almost drowned—as he was by this time; but 
            even here the elementary war pursued him; a 
            stream of water began to ripple down the chink, 
            soon swelling to a torrent, augmented by another 
            which found its way through the chasms of the 
            precipice as if it had burst from some subterranean 
            reservoir. <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The traveller</rs>'s situation became 
            insupportable; he must remove or perish; yet 
            not daring to quit the crags to which he clung, 
            and availing himself of the partial lee they afforded, 
            he essayed to clamber up the face of the precipice, 
            and with much difficulty and struggling 
            reached the edge of the chink whence the torrent 
            fell. Here he found himself comparatively safe in 
            a long narrow passage or natural alley, in which 
            he was at least secured from the wind by the 
            high and inaccessible rocks on either side of it. 
            Yet as the torrent still flowed over his feet and half 
            way up his legs, he waded onwards to find a spot 
            of higher ground, or an insulated piece of rock 
            that might elevate him above the stream, and 
            with this hope pursued the course of it for above 
            a hundred yards, till he came to a chasm that 
            opened on it from another mass of rocks, between 
            which and his present station another brawling 
            cataract, at depth of fifty feet beneath him, 
            found its way towards the streams which united 
            in the <placeName ref="#rio_grande">Rio Grande</placeName> below. A fallen tree formed a 
            bridge across this fissure, on the opposite side of 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">15</fw>
            
            which the mouth of a cave might be distinguished 
            by a glare of the lightning, sufficient in appearance 
            to ensure our <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">traveller</rs> shelter and safety for 
            the night—shelter from the rain, and security from 
            the wind. It was a most perilous undertaking to 
            pass this bridge; but prompted by hope, and urged 
            by misery and fear, he ventured on its uncertain 
            surface, keeping his balance by means of a branch 
            that hung from the opposite side, which, with 
            much ado, he reached at last without accident. 
            Here he found what appeared to him steps cut by 
            human art for some height in the face of the rock: 
            he ascended them, and walked into the cave.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="chapter">
            <fw type="pageNum">16</fw>
            <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
            <ab type="epigraph">Let me wipe off this honorable dew.
            SHAKESPEARE.</ab>
            
            <p>As soon as <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the traveller</rs> found himself safe from 
            the storm, he sat down on the floor of the cave, 
            and burst into a flood of tears; and something like 
            an acknowledgment of heaven's mercy passed 
            his lips. His next thought was for his <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">boy</rs> and 
            his equipage, the <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna> and the portmanteau; 
            nor was he long in adverting to the deplorable 
            condition in which he yet found himself, drenched 
            with rain, and exhausted with the fatigue of having 
            borne up against the passion of the hurricane. 
            To sit still might be fatal to him in this state, and 
            he had even thoughts of stripping off his wet garments, 
            and parading the cave, as far as he could 
            see into it, till daylight; but was checked by the 
            idea which he could not dismiss of stepping on 
            <ecda:fauna>scorpions</ecda:fauna> or <ecda:fauna>centipedes</ecda:fauna>, or becoming an easier 
            prey to the <ecda:fauna>musquitos</ecda:fauna> which like himself had 
            here found a refuge from the weather. While he 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">17</fw>
            
            yet mused on the manner in which he was to pass 
            the hours till morning, his olfactory nerves became 
            sensible of a smell of fire,—the smoke of burning 
            wood, which evidently came from the interior of 
            the cave; and hastily concluding it to be owing to 
            one of the wandering fires he had seen abroad, he 
            explored his way through the cavern towards the 
            smell, expecting to find an outlet on the other 
            side of the mountain, through which he calculated 
            the smoke was driven perhaps from a distance. 
            The odour and its vapour increased as he proceeded; 
            and he had not made a very long or very painful 
            march, before he began to perceive a glimmering 
            of light, by which he attained an inner apartment 
            as it were of a cave, filled it is true with smoke, 
            but in some measure illuminated by the fire from 
            which it exhaled; not one of the wandering fires 
            of the wilderness, but a fire of burning brands laid 
            on the floor of the apartment too evidently by 
            human hands. "This," thought he, "is at least the 
            abode of man: runaway slave, Maroon, or robber, 
            I will yet claim his hospitality; my situation 
            cannot be worse, and what have I to lose? 
            But where is <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the tenant</rs> of the dwelling? Here 
            are <ecda:food>plantains</ecda:food> too, not long roasted, and <ecda:food>rum</ecda:food>; and 
            what are these?" he added, taking up some garments 
            that lay on the floor, a <distinct>contoo</distinct>, and an 
            instrument of music, a <distinct>bonjaw</distinct>. "Let us at least 
            summon the master of the cave. What ho! hilloh!"
            
            <fw>VOL I.</fw>
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">18</fw>
            
            The voice died away unheeded, and the traveller 
            listened to its echoes until he felt almost afraid 
            and ashamed to disturb the silence again. Yet 
            he mustered courage to exert his voice a second 
            and a third time, though as at first ineffectually. 
            Sufficiently removed from the storm without, to 
            hear no more of it than an occasional murmur 
            which stole along the vault he had penetrated, 
            too faint to cause him any farther concern, his 
            own voice was reverberated on his ears with a
            force from which he shrank within himself, so 
            painful was it to his oppressed and agitated 
            nerves. He called no more; but conforming himself 
            with a philosophical moderation to the hour 
            and the scene in which he found himself, he trimmed 
            the fire; took off his wet clothes, which he 
            wrung and disposed around it; attired himself in 
            the <distinct>contoo</distinct> of his <rs type="person">invisible host</rs>; and wrapping his 
            feet in a blanket which lay beside it, helped himself
            from the calabash of <ecda:food>rum</ecda:food>, and put some of the 
            <ecda:food>plantains</ecda:food> on the fire again to warm. He had 
            seated himself on a bundle of sticks, and as he 
            took a second taste of the <ecda:food>rum</ecda:food> calabash, surveyed 
            at his leisure, by the cheerful blaze he had made, 
            the extent and furniture of his apartment.</p>
            
            <p>It was a lofty cavern hewn by the hand of nature 
            in the otherwise solid lime-stone rock, from 
            the roof of which hung many stalactites, whose 
            points were blackened by the smoke from the fire 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">19</fw>
            
            beneath. Besides the opening by which <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the traveller</rs> 
            had entered, there were four other apertures, 
            each leading, as it seemed from the glimpse 
            he had taken of them, to the other recesses in the 
            rock, and so much resembling each other that he 
            could not now distinctly ascertain that which had 
            admitted him. Alarmed for a moment as this discovery, 
            he arose from his seat, and taking a firebrand 
            from the blazing pile, would fain have explored 
            these vomitories, into each of which he 
            walked a few paces, without however deriving the 
            information he required, or gaining any but a conviction 
            that they extended farther than he was 
            disposed at present to penetrate. He next surveyed 
            the precincts of the cave itself, and its rather 
            curious contents. In a recess stood a couple of 
            spears, one solely of hard wood, whose point was 
            rendered still harder by fire; the other was shod 
            with iron and rusted apparently with blood; a 
            bamboo rod, ten feet in length and about an inch 
            in thickness, leaned against the rock beside them, 
            carved or tattoed from end to end. In another 
            angle of the vault was a calabash filled with various 
            sorts of hair, among which it was easy to discriminate 
            that of white men, <ecda:fauna>horses</ecda:fauna>, and <ecda:fauna>dogs</ecda:fauna>. 
            These were huddled together, and crowded with 
            feathers of various <ecda:fauna>birds</ecda:fauna>, especially those of 
            <ecda:fauna>domestic poultry</ecda:fauna> and <ecda:fauna>wild parrots</ecda:fauna>, with one or 
            two of the spoils of a <ecda:fauna>macaw</ecda:fauna>. A human skull 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">20</fw>
            
            was placed beside this calabash, from which the 
            teeth were missing; but on turning it up, <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the traveller</rs> 
            found them with a quantity of broken glass 
            crammed into the cerebellum, and covered up with 
            a wad of silk cotton, to prevent them from falling 
            out. There were several other skulls in a second 
            recess, some perfect, some which had been broken 
            apparently with a sharp pointed instrument, and 
            many of them serving as calabashes or boxes to 
            hold the strange property of <rs type="person">the master of the 
            cave</rs>; one was a receptacle for gunpowder, which 
            <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the inquisitive traveller</rs> narrowly escaped inflaming; 
            a second contained bullets and shot of various 
            sizes, mixed with old nails and pieces of rag; 
            and from a third he saw with no little horror a 
            <ecda:fauna>black snake</ecda:fauna> uncoil itself the moment he touched 
            it. There were three muskets, all old and out of 
            order; a pistol and two cutlasses, disposed on different 
            ledges of the rock; a large conch-shell 
            fitted with a belt of mahoe bark, to be worn over 
            the shoulder, hung from a projection, with several 
            other pieces of rope made of similar materials, to 
            which were attached rings of wood and hollowed 
            stones, perhaps intended for amulets or charms. 
            A lamp of clay at last arrested his attention; it 
            had carved on it some rude figures and was filled 
            with oil of the <ecda:flora>Palma Christi</ecda:flora>, having a wick 
            formed of the fibres of the <ecda:flora>plantain</ecda:flora> stalk. This 
            the intruder took the liberty of illuming, to assist 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">21</fw>
            
            him more conveniently than did his flickering 
            firebrand in the farther search he seemed disposed 
            to prosecute. By the help of this he espied a 
            pair of shoepatters, a sort of coarse sandal, and a 
            red cloak resembling the South-American poncho. 
            Some <ecda:food>salted fish</ecda:food> was suspended from a part of the 
            roof, with a large calabash of <ecda:food>sugar</ecda:food>, and another of 
            coarse <ecda:food>salt</ecda:food>; and an earthen jar contained no 
            small store of <ecda:food>salted pork</ecda:food>. There were several 
            pieces of <ecda:food>jerked hog</ecda:food> hanging from a stick 
            placed across this recess, to one of which he 
            helped himself without ceremony; and thinking 
            he had made sufficient search for the present, 
            returned to the fire, on which he heaped fresh fuel, 
            raking forward the embers to cook his meat: 
            placed his lamp on a shelf of the rock full in his 
            view; and taking a <distinct>gombah</distinct> for his stool, sat down 
            very deliberately to his supper. He ate with no 
            sparing appetite; and the <ecda:food>rum</ecda:food> which he quaffed 
            as his thirst prompted him, refreshed his body 
            and composed his mind so happily and so gradually, 
            that what with that and his fatigue, the 
            solace of the fire and the fumes of his digestion, 
            he at last slipt gently from his <distinct>gombah</distinct>, which 
            now served him for a pillow, rolled himself up in 
            his blanket, and fell into a profound sleep.</p>
         </div>
         
         
         <pb/>
         <div type="chapter">
             <fw type="pageNum">22</fw>
             <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
            <ab>
               <hi rend="italics">Pye.</hi>  And you a figure-caster, a conjurer!
               <hi rend="italics">Skir.</hi> A conjurer?
               <hi rend="italics">Pye.</hi>  Let me alone, I'll instruct you, and teach you to
               deceive all eyes but the devil's.
               The Puritan
            </ab>
             <p>DEEP and leaden as were the slumbers of our 
             <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">traveller</rs>, his mind was not wholly relieved from 
             the cares of this world, for which, sleeping or 
             waking, nature seems by some perversion from 
             her original and benevolent purpose to have 
             formed this our enslaved, if not incarcerated, 
             sensorium: not but that there are dreams of all 
             denominations—visions of bliss, as well as of 
             sorrow; but the first are still dependent on terrestrial 
             objects, human interests and passions, as 
             well as the latter; and where is the mind that 
             would not, at many periods of even a short life, 
             have consented to wipe away from its tablets the 
             very memory of those, to escape the painful rememberances 
             of these? The brains of our <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">weather-
             beaten sleeper</rs> were not long idle. He fancied
             
             <pb/>
             <fw type="pageNum">23</fw>
             
             himself still contending with the elements, and 
             striving in vain to save his boy <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> from the 
             storm, or keep his own seat on his Spanish horse, 
             which succeeded in kicking his <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">master</rs> into a 
             river, whose waves were waves of fire. Then 
             again he fancied himself sauntering by moonlight on 
             the banks of another, a clear and crystal stream, 
             whence he descried at a distance the buildings of 
             a sugar estate on fire. He ran towards it. From 
             the great house (as the principal dwelling is 
             called) <ecda:anonPers>a female figure</ecda:anonPers>, young and beautiful, 
             looked out, imploring help. The passion of <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the 
             sleeper</rs> was awakended; he clambered into the 
             piazza, reconducted <ecda:anonPers>the lady</ecda:anonPers> to her chamber, assured 
             her of her safety, and in spite of her distress, 
             presumed to talk to her of his love; nay, 
             insensible to all but his own selfish feelings, attempted 
             to pollute her with his caresses. She 
             died in his arms, as he thought, curseing him for 
             his cruelty; and as he shrunk with horror from 
             her inanimate and ghastly corpse, he saw a fiend 
             arise from her bed, fix on him its eyes glaring 
             with a malignant fury, by a threatening action 
             command him to silence, and trace on 
             his forehead, in burning characters, the fearful 
             syllable death. The only sound which escaped 
             the lips of the demon was that of his own name 
             -<persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>! <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName>!-articulated in a voice of 
             mingled triumph and revenge—<persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName>!</p>
            
            <p><rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">The traveller</rs> started from his dream as if he 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">24</fw>
            
            had been roused by the sting of a <ecda:fauna>scorpion</ecda:fauna>. He 
            sat upright for an instant, and stared wildly 
            around, scarce recollecting his own identity or 
            situation; but what was his amazement, not to 
            say horror, on perceiving before him <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the very 
            figure of the demon of his dream</rs>, or a figure 
            which his fancy so quickly substituted for him, 
            that the idea of the first was as if by magic resolved 
            and condensed into that which he beheld?</p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">This figure</rs> stood before the lamp, whose rays 
            served to define the outline of his person with the 
            greatest accuracy. Of his features little or nothing 
            could be seen, except the light gleaming 
            from his eyeballs. He stood in an attitude which 
            <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the dreamer</rs>'s fears quickly determined to be the 
            menacing posture of the demon from which he 
            had shrunk; the forefinger of his right hand elevated, 
            the left hand leaning on a bamboo staff. 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">In the name of God or Devil,</said> cried <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName> impatiently, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">who or what art thou?</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">The figure</rs> relaxed from its position, lowered its 
            right hand, advanced a step forward with a gentle 
            inclination of the head, and replied in a mild and 
            almost musical tone of voice-<said rend="quotes" aloud="true"><rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">Master</rs>—what you 
            will.</said> A less experienced person than <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName> 
            might have entertained a momentary supposition 
            that the being before him, who had first excited his 
            fears to give him courage, was no other than the 
            evil spirit himself, thus come to tempt him; but 
            our <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">traveller</rs> was too much <hi rend="italics">au fait</hi> on the affairs 
            
            <fw type="pageNum">25</fw>
            of this world to expect a bow from the Enemy of 
            mankind; though scared as he had been from his 
            terrific dream, it was some moments before he 
            could thoroughly collect himself. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What you 
            please,—<rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">a Negro</rs>,</said> repeated <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the figure</rs>, as if to 
            give <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the white man</rs> time to reassure himself.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What I please, and a Negro</said>—rejoined <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName>, 
            as if unconscious of what he heard.—<said rend="quotes" aloud="true">But 
            what may be your business, and what want you 
            here? Is this your cave?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">My business,</said> replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the black man</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">is 
            sometimes to go round the lines of my <ecda:anonPers>master</ecda:anonPers>'s 
            estate, sometimes to look after <rs type="persGroup">runaway Negroes</rs>, 
            to watch the provision grounds, to hunt wild 
            hogs.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Whose cave then is this,</said> said <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the other</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">so 
            well provided with food and necessaries, and—if I 
            mistake not—with evidences of an illicit calling? 
            <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">The owner</rs> of the cave, methinks, must be a 
            wizard—is he not?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">The cave, master,</said> replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">has 
            harboured, as I have heard for long times past, 
            many <rs type="persGroup">runaway Negroes</rs>; they have their provisions 
            here.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">They have,</said> interrupted <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the other</rs>. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I found 
            a fire, and roasted plantains and rum, all 
            ready for entertainment: though I fancied from 
            what I have seen, that Obeah spells were rather 
            the business of those who frequent this cavern.</said></p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">26</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">You are at least fortunate,</said> answered <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs>, 
            seeming to pay no attention to the remark of 
            <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName> about Obeah, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">in having found shelter 
            from the storm, and food; and those to whom 
            the cave belongs, were they here, would still respect 
            the laws of hospitality, and make you welcome, 
            be what they may, to all you can require at 
            their hands. But if you have satisfied your hunger, 
            be not offended that I do the same. My 
            presence shall be no annoyance to you. Sleep 
            again, if you feel disposed. I will eat in silence, 
            and at a distance from you.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Sit down, sit down,</said> resumed <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the white 
            man</rs>, as he arose himself; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">eat and be happy. 
            I have no farther disposition to sleep: my mind 
            is too much harassed with what I have encountered 
            this night; <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">my boy</rs>, and my horse, and my 
            baggage, are lost in the storm. And where were 
            you?</said> added he, looking inquisitively in the 
            face of <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs>; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">your dress is untouched by 
            the rain.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I had taken shelter,</said> replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">in 
            another part of these caverns, which extend 
            through to the other side of the mountain, before 
            the rain began.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">To the other side of the mountain!</said> interrupted 
            <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName>. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Aye! you know by what entrance 
            I arrived here then?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I know,</said> replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs> unmoved, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">that
            
            <pb/> 
            <fw type="pageNum">27</fw>
            
            you must have entered from the side of 
            <placeName ref="#rio_grande">Rio Grande</placeName>, a fearful pass across the devil's 
            gully; over which" (he added with a submissive 
            and respectful smile) "<rs type="persGroup">the Negroes</rs> say that none 
            but the devil himself can pass, or one whom the 
            devil leads; and that in the dark.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Ha!</said> cried <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName>, a little moved by the 
            observation; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">but you have passed it?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">It was never passed by a white man before,</said> 
            replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs>, as if he had not adverted to 
            the question. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">There was once <ecda:anonPers>one</ecda:anonPers> who fled 
            towards it for refuge, not from a hurricane, but 
            from the punishment of crimes and misdeeds.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What had he committed?</said> said <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">It was told of him, but I know not how 
            truly,</said> replied the other, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">that he had set fire 
            to <ecda:anonPers>a gentlemen</ecda:anonPers>'s estate, and attempted to kill 
            his <ecda:anonPers>daughter</ecda:anonPers> in a fit of jealousy. He galloped 
            from his pursuers, and scrambled up the 
            pass you found, where they could not follow him; 
            and halting at the bridge, invoked the white 
            man's God to help him over; but he slipped, and 
            tumbled down the gully.</said></p>
            
            <p>While this conversation took place, <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs> 
            had renewed the fire, taken a piece of <ecda:food>salted 
            pork</ecda:food> from the jar, put it into an iron pot with 
            some water in it, which <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName> had overlooked 
            in his examination of the premises, and set it 
            on the fire to boil. He produced some <ecda:food>water</ecda:food> 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">28</fw>
            
            also from one of the recesses, with which he 
            mixed himself some <ecda:food>rum</ecda:food> in a small calabash; 
            and after the libation of a little on the earth, 
            drank to the health of the white man. <persName ref="roland_0001">Roland</persName> 
            was neither pleased nor surprised to see him 
            find the food and materials he required with 
            so much ease and familiarity; not doubting that 
            he was at least one of the proprietors of the cave, 
            according to his account of them. But though he 
            felt a confidence in the hospitality of one who 
            could, had he been so disposed, have taken his 
            life while he was sleeping, still he could not 
            regard him without a suspicous feeling, and watched 
            him as he moved about the cave with the same 
            anxious scrutiny as that with which an alarmed cat 
            keeps sight of a <ecda:fauna>terrier dog</ecda:fauna> who has invaded the 
            stable or loft where her offspring are concealed. 
            He had full time to remark the singularity of his 
            dress and appearance, of which it may not be 
            improper to give the reader some idea; as <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> 
            (by which name he was known) will probably 
            take a principal part in the scenes and events 
            hereafter to be described.</p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">This dealer in magic</rs>, for he was no less a personage, 
            was of a slight and elegant make, though 
            very small of stature, being considerably under 
            the middle size. His age was at least sixty; but 
            the lines which that had traced on his features 
            indicated, notwithstanding his profession, no 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">29</fw>
            
            feeling hostile to his fellow-creatures, at war with 
            human nature, or dissatisfied with himself. He 
            was attired in a South American poncho, which 
            had once been of a bright scarlet colour, fastened 
            round his waist by a thin leathern girdle; and his 
            head was decorated with a red silk handkerchief, 
            tied in the fashion of a turban. He was barefooted, 
            and without any offensive weapon; for 
            such the bamboo wand on which he had leaned 
            could hardly be denominated. He moved with 
            an elasticity uncommon for his years; and his 
            manner indicated on his part perfect confidence, 
            wholly unsuspicious of his <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">guest</rs> or his purpose. 
            Yet it was but too evident to <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>, that <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs> 
            had evaded his questions as to the magic talents 
            or qualities of some one who frequented the cave; 
            but as the use of Obeah is denounced by law, 
            however despised by <rs type="persGroup">white men</rs>, he could not 
            attach any particular consequence to such evasion, 
            nor justify himself in expecting any confession 
            on a subject of such importance to the 
            <rs type="persGroup">professors</rs> or <rs type="persGroup">participators</rs> in this blind sort of 
            necromancy, if it may be so called.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="false">Whether conjuror or not</said>, thought <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">he does justice to his food;</said> for in fact <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah 
            man</rs> had seated himself to his meal at a respectful 
            distance from his <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">guest</rs>, and feasted on his 
            humble viands with a persevereance worthy of any 
            high priest, not excepting those who presided at 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">30</fw>
            
            the slaughter of <distinct>hecatombs</distinct>. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I have not eaten,</said> 
               said he to his <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">guest</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">for twenty hours.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Why so?</said> demanded <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>: <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">have you penances 
            in your religion—fasts, mortifications?</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">The Negro</rs> shook his head and smiled. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Have 
            <hi rend="italics">you</hi>, <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">master</rs>? Do you think fasting or reading 
            prayers will compensate for injuries done to man? 
            Not that I mean to imply anything as relative to 
            yourself,</said> he added; remarking that his question 
            rather affected <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the white man</rs>. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Your religion 
            is now become that of almost all <rs type="persGroup">the slaves and 
            free people of colour</rs>; yet I never knew them 
            fast or mortify themselves.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Then wherefore have you abstained from eating 
            so long?</said> interrupted <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I have been some distance hence,</said> replied 
            <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">to a plantation that had been deserted. 
            <ecda:anonPers>The owner</ecda:anonPers> is dead; his <ecda:anonPers>wife</ecda:anonPers>, afraid to remain 
            among her <rs type="persGroup">Negroes</rs>, had taken her <rs type="persGroup">children</rs> to the 
            Bay at <placeName ref="#port_antonio">Port Antonio</placeName>; and <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">a white man</rs>, <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">a missionary 
            preaching man</rs>, was expected to come there, 
            to try if he could persuade <rs type="persGroup">the Negroes</rs> to go 
            down to the same place to be sold.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">You think he would not have succeeded?</said> 
            said <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Those who have once shaken 
            off their bonds are not likely to offer themselves 
            again as willing prisoners; besides, there is such a 
            stir making in England for the emancipation of 
            <rs type="persGroup">the slaves</rs>, that—and it is so much against the 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">31</fw>
            
            religion which <rs type="persGroup">the slave owners</rs> at least affect to 
            profess, that perhaps few people just now would 
            venture to purchase them; and they would be 
            more apt to increase their numbers from other 
            estates, which will follow their example, than 
            tamely to surrender themselves again to whips 
            and chains; nay, might they not in turn apply the 
            whips and chains to their <rs type="persGroup">oppressors</rs>?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Whips and chains!</said> said <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>, 
            with a seemingly innocent smile. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Have you not 
            whips and chains in your country yonder too? 
            How do you punish violence, incendeiaries, murderers, 
            ravishers, traitors, and rebels? Can you 
            govern <rs type="persGroup">white men</rs> with prayers and talking? You 
            have happiness and plenty of there, and no man 
            works but when he likes; why do not <rs type="persGroup">the white 
            men</rs> stay in their own country, and leave <rs type="persGroup">the Negroes</rs> 
            to themselves here?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Ah!</said> replied <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">you can never be 
            happy, at least for some years, without <rs type="persGroup">white men</rs>, 
            who shall teach your children to read, to write, 
            to pray to the only true God; the knowledge of 
            the only means of salvation. Would you wish your 
            little ones to become the prey of hell-fire? What 
            ideas will they have of a crucified Saviour? You 
            have among you, it is true, <rs type="persGroup">freemen</rs> and <rs type="persGroup">slaves</rs> who 
            can read and write, and some who have made even 
            a little progress in religion; but unfortunately those 
            who are most instructed seem to hold their reli-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">32</fw>
            
            gion lightest. In my country yonder, as you call 
            it, we are obliged to have <rs type="persGroup">priests</rs> and <rs type="persGroup">ministers</rs> of 
            religion, and <rs type="persGroup">bishops</rs> or <rs type="persGroup">elders</rs> over them, to keep 
            them from doing wrong; and without some such 
            system here you will relapse into anarchy and 
            infidelity.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Is your religion a science then,</said> said <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">that it must be taught and learned? and are 
            your chief men in it in danger of doing wrong? 
            We know our duty here already; and it were better 
            to leave us to the God who has guarded us 
            hitherto.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Your God,</said> interrupted <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">has left you 
            slaves; the Christian's God will make you free.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Ah!</said> cried <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">is it so? Will your 
            God make <rs type="persGroup">the Negroes</rs> free?</said> (He looked <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the 
            white man</rs> steadily in the face.) <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Will he leave us 
            unencumbered with white parsons? What security 
            can you give us of that? It were better I belonged 
            still to a tyrannical master, than that I was 
            subjected to a tyrannical white priest, who should 
            take from me one of my ten fingers.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Your master,</said> cried <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName> rather exultingly, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">takes the labour of all your ten fingers.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Not so,</said> rejoined <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>: <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">we work, it is true, 
            for our masters; but they feed us, clothe us, give 
            us land and houses, attend us in sickness and old 
            age, and leave our minds, our thoughts, to ourselves.</said></p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">33</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">They leave you to the Devil,</said> said <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the white 
            man</rs>. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">If you had a spark of courage, you would 
            emancipate yourselves; if you had one glimmering 
            of the greatness of our God, you would take 
            up the cross, and devote yourselves to his service.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">You are a bold man,</said> replied <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> again, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">to talk so to me; or a cunning man, and wish 
            to make me think you can and will serve my 
            countrymen.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I both can and will,</said> rejoined <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the other</rs>, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">if you are disposed to profit by the opportunity 
            that is about to occur; I am <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> 
            that was expected at your abandoned plantation.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I know it,</said> answered <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs> with a 
            polite and significant nod.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">You know it!</said> cried <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Yes, <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">master</rs>.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">But how?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Ah! master,</said> said <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">there is 
            nothing in these mountains, in this island, which 
            is concealed from me. I boast not of my secrets; 
            my business is to use them with advantage.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Know you then the real purpose for which I 
            was travelling ot the forsaken settlement?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I know it, my kind <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">master</rs>.</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The Missionary</rs> was a little amazed; but thinking 
            that <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>'s intention might be only to impose 
            on him, he demanded of him to explain what it 
            was.</p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">34</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">It is for you to explain,</said> replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the other</rs>; 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">my explanation will not profit you; I could give 
            you evidences of greater knowledge than you 
            dream of; I could tell you who and what you are.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Tell me,</said> exclaimed <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> with impatience: 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">give me some proof of your intelligence.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Here is a powder,</said> said <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>, 
            calmly taking a little phial from his girdle, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">which will satisfy many men. Will you please to 
            hold for your hand? See—it is white as the 
            snows of <placeName ref="#mount_atlas">Mount Atlas</placeName>.</said> (The Missionary stared 
            again with amazement.) <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I once placed some of it 
            in the palm of a white man, who called upon his 
            God in my presence to avouch his innocence: 
            he was accused of murder. I bid him close his 
            hand as I now close yours;—grasp it tight, press 
            your fingers to your palm;—I told him his God 
            would vouch for him: that if he were innocent, the 
            powder would still be white; if guilty, his fingers 
            would be crimsoned as with blood. Have you 
            pressed your fingers with violence?</said> <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The Missionary</rs>'s 
            heart palpitated, his teeth almost chattered, 
            and his hand trembled as he re-opened it; 
            but the powder was still white as before. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Hah!</said>
            cried <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">you dared not close your 
            hand; my charm is ineffectual, or you stand self-
            convicted.</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The Missionary</rs> breated again; if a mountain 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">35</fw>
            
            had been moved from his breast, he could not 
            have felt a greater relief. He held forth his hand 
            with the white powder in it, exclaiming, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">False—
            jugglery.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Is it false?</said> cried <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">should it have 
            taken the hue of fire? Yet is it neither falsehood 
            nor jugglery. Let me touch your fingers;—if this 
            hand</said>—(he looked on <rs ref="#roland_0001">the Missionary</rs> with an inquisitive 
            smile)—<said rend="quotes" aloud="true">has never shed innocent blood, 
            let this powder remain unchanged; but if it has 
            shed innocent blood</said>—(he rubbed the powder 
            firmly with his own finger)—<said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Lo now! look you 
            there! crimson as the sun-setting in a storm! 
            Are you satisfied? See where it flows like blood 
            even to your arm! deep—deep!</said></p>
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Damnation!</said> cried <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Methodist</rs>, shuddering 
            at the sight, and shrinking from the touch of his 
            <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">host</rs>. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Thou art in league with the fields of hell. 
            What trick is this? Am I a man to tremble beneath 
            the gaze of <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">a Negro</rs>? Thou has divined alright—
            No—no,—'tis falsehood all; thy knowledge is a 
            trick;—yet how hast thou divined? or who has 
            known me? Perdition! Dost thou not tremble 
            for the consequences of thy indiscretion? Think'st 
            thou my arm could not annihilate thee?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I fear you not,</said> modestly replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs>, 
            who had watched his emotion as a boa constrictor 
            may be supposed to watch the unhappy deer 
            he means to spring upon; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I fear you not. You 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">36</fw>
            
            have eaten of my food, and drank from my own 
            calabash; you cannot harm me, nor do I meditate 
            any evil to you; your secret is in safe keeping.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="false">If it were confined to me,</said> thought <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">it were better. Whence does he derive his knowledge? 
            Oh God! what scorpions has he awakened 
            in my bosom! Shall I be outwitted, circumvented, 
            made subservient to <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">a dealer in sorcery 
            and incantations</rs>? and for what? Yes—I will submit.</said> 
            A thousand fancies mingled in his mind, 
            which resolved themselves at last into one paramount 
            idea; namely, to mould, if he could, <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the 
            conjuror</rs> to his own purposes. <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">An arduous task, 
            it is true,</said> thought he; <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">but weightier matters 
            have been brought to bear.</said> He dreamed not that 
            perhaps <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs> entertained similar views with 
            respect to himself. He looked towards him, and 
            saw him leaning against the rock at one of the 
            entrances, absorbed in a profound contemplation, <!-- Comma unclear --> 
            which seemed to abstract him from all conviction 
            of the scene before him; his arms folded under 
            his poncho, his eyes fixed on the floor of the cave. 
            The lamp gleaming on his forehead shewed that 
            his features at least betrayed nothing of what was 
            passing in a mind of which he was so much the 
            master; yet as it lighted up his crimson head-
            dress and his ruddy garmet, whose shadows were 
            deepened by the gloom behind them, it gave to 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">37</fw>
            
            his appearance something of the demon with 
            which <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName> was yet fain to associate him; it 
            is true he could not avoid the idea. In a few 
            moments he moved from his position, put himself 
            for an instant in the attitude of one listening to 
            catch a distant sound, and suddenly hurried from 
            the cave.</p>
            </div>
         
         <pb/>
         <fw type="pageNum">38</fw>
         
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
            <ab>Apparel vice like virtue's harbinger; 
            Bear a fair presence, though your heart be tainted; 
            Teach sin the carriage of a holy saint: 
            Be secret—false. 
            Comedy of Errors</ab>
            
            <p>THE blast of a conch, a faint and but just audible 
            sound, moaned through the rocky galleries that 
            opened into the cave where <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>, 
            <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>, had just left his agitated and disconcerted 
            <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">guest</rs>. He paced the cave with an irritation almost 
            amounting to frenzy; now cursing his own 
            untoward fortune, now venting imprecations on 
            <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs> whose singular penetration had unravelled 
            at least one circumstance of his (<rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs>'s) 
            life. Yet gloomy and meloncholy as 
            the event to which the spell seemed to relate, it 
            was perhaps one which his recollection had almost 
            represented as venial, in comparison with other 
            deeds which preyed on his memory. Misfortune 
            and guilt might have claimed an equal share in 
            that: passion and remorse had been the cause 
            and consequence of these, which had as yet escaped 
            detection; as had indeed the first alluded to—
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">39</fw>
            
            known, as <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName> had imagined, to himself 
            alone. Yet <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> had only charged him with 
            shedding blood. The particulars of the circumstance 
            might be a mystery to him still; or he 
            might have made a vague charge on the suggestion 
            solely of his own fancy, taking the chance of 
            getting credit for displaying a supernatural power, 
            to acquire a natural one over the mind of a white 
            man, whose business at any rate he seemed to 
            understand; whose business, if discovered to the 
            authorities of the island, would be death. Death! 
            <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The Missionary</rs>'s mind glowed with the thought, 
            and his heart died almost within him, as the conviction 
            sank upon it. <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">Death! an ignominious 
            death!</said> Yet what assurance had he that <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">this vile 
            Negro</rs> knew his business? He had said nought 
            of it. <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The Missionary</rs>'s feelings had betrayed 
            him into an avowal of guilt of some kind, an 
            avowal of which <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs> would not fail to 
            profit: and then—and then!—"<rs type="persGroup">These Negroes</rs> are 
            not such dolts as <rs type="persGroup">the white men</rs> give out to one 
            another, but cunning and secret. Who would have 
            dreamed of such a cave as this, so tenanted, in 
            such a wilderness? Let it be <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>'s business at 
            least to try if he cannot make it and its <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">tenant</rs> 
            useful to his own purposes."</p>
            
            <p>While these reflections, half muttered to himself, 
            half mental, allowed the agitation of his mind 
            to subside, like a boisterous ocean rocking itself 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">40</fw>
            
            into repose after a storm, <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> had laid 
            aside <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs>'s blanket and contoo, in which he 
            had been enveloped, and resumed his own more 
            appropriate dress. He trimmed the lamp, and fed 
            the fire, as if not altogether in charity with darkness; 
            and seeing by his watch that it must needs 
            be daylight abraod, began to explore the passage 
            from the cave by which <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> had so suddenly 
            disappeared: for he had made his own ingress; 
            nor is to be supposed that he was ambitious of 
            again passing over that awful gully, by the bridge 
            which, according to <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>'s account, 
            the Enemy of mankind had constructed, and reserved 
            for his own particular friends. However, 
            his fortune did not favour him here; a few yards 
            in darkness brought him to a spot whence he 
            could feel two or three currents of air, evidently 
            issuing from as many passages in the rock; and 
            the sounds of his feet, now equipped with his 
            iron-heeled boots, echoed along these galleries 
            in so many directions, that he became afraid of 
            trusting himself beyond the extent of the spot at 
            which he had halted. The lamp was portable, 
            and might assist him in unravelling the labyrinth; 
            without it he must, as he thought, be lost. He 
            returned to possess himself of it' and as he reentered 
            the cave by the same apeture as that by 
            which he had quitted it, he saw <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs> 
            <!-- GO BACK & FIX RS SO ONLY ONE REFERENCE FOR A PARTICULAR NICKNAME PER PARAGRAPH 
            OR GO BACK AND PUT SOME BACK IN? CHECK IN WITH LIZ/FORUM. -->
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">41</fw>
            
            likewise re-entering it by another of the passages, 
            followed by <rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">a tall athletic Negro</rs>, in whose presence 
            the other seemed to dwindle almost into 
            insignificance. The light flashed on his face, and 
            exhibited his features to the gaze of the Missionary, 
            as he stepped into the chief apartment of the 
            cavern; features which were but too well known 
            to him, although the sight of them here, and 
            under such circumstances, was anything but welcome 
            to <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What do you here?</said> cried he to <rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">the Negro</rs>. 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Merciful heaven! are you a confederate with <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">this 
            juggling wizard</rs>, and have you betrayed—</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">The Negro</rs> drew himself up to his full height 
            with a resolved and haughty dignity, and answered 
            instantly—<said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I have betrayed nothing, 
            no man's business, no man's name. <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> 
            has a power as well as yourself—a greater 
            power than yours; I should be a fool to overlook 
            it.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What!</said> cried <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Methodist</rs>, with an amazement 
            bordering on horror, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">are you too leagued 
            with the Prince of Darkness? Is it for this you 
            have been baptized, and made a member of 
            the church of Christ? Have you redeemed your 
            soul from hell, to cast it headlong into the bottomless 
            pit again? And have you faith even in Obeah 
            spells, philtres, and charms? Or are these to be the 
            medicaments of your weak and sickly power in its 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">42</fw>
            
            infancy? Perish the thought! The curse of God 
            shall wait upon your hopes, annihilate your 
            schemes, and bring down death and ruin on your 
            devoted head—on all your followers. I quit you; 
            I renounce you; lead me from the cave; let me 
            leap into one of your abysses; hurl me down the 
            rocks; kill, murder me. My soul shall never 
            testify to such abominations, nor my efforts for 
            your temporal and eternal salvation be blasted by 
            the breath of those who tamper with the Devil.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">We do not tamper with the Devil,</said> said <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the 
            Obeah man</rs>, very modestly interrupting him; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">we 
            known no Devil with whom we have any power: 
            it were well if we did.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">How!</said> cried <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> again; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">it were 
            well—well to prostrate your souls at the feet 
            of Moloch? But you are nought. <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName>!</said>
            (<rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">The tall Negro</rs> made a sign of acknowledgment 
            as to his name.) <said rend="quotes" aloud="true"><persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName>! you have taken the 
            cross of God; you have sworn to renounce the 
            devil and his works; keep to your oath, so shall 
            God prosper you: fail in it, and the care of 
            heaven shall fail you too.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Master <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>,</said> said <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>, interposing, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">we say nothing against your religion, nor your 
            God; we had a religion before we knew yours; 
            such as it was, it is. You have had proof 
            of knowledge we possess, and even <hi rend="italics">I</hi> may 
            help to further the scheme you have in view.</said></p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">43</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Said you not,</said> replied <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>, addressing himself 
            to <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">that you had not betrayed me? 
            He that is false to his God, does not long keep his 
            faith with man.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">He has not betrayed you,</said> reajoined <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah 
            man</rs>: <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">his secrets, like yours, are no mysteries 
            to me. Have not I vowed to make him king? 
            You too have promised your aid; but I have 
            vowed.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What are your vows?</said> cried <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs>, 
            with some little amazement.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">My vows,</said> said <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the other</rs>, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">are his destiny; 
            I have read that in his face, in his forehead, in the 
            stars; it is his spell—I know it, I have divined it, 
            see it!</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">And mine too, have you read that in your 
            visions?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Master <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>,</said> replied <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs> again, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">if I knew your fate, you would still doubt me, 
            though I told you what it might be; nor would 
            you believe that my art could make manifest what 
            is in the womb of time, independent of me, and 
            of the power which you say I derive from a being 
            inimical to your God who rules all things.</said></p>
            
            <p>Notwithstanding this remark, <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> 
            would have been curious to hear his supposed 
            destiny, even from the lips of <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">a man</rs> he affected 
            to despise: the specimen he had seen of <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the 
            wizard</rs>'s influence and knowledge, doubtful and 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">44</fw>
            
            suspicious as it yet seemed, had made no trifling 
            impression on the superstitious mind of a man 
            bewildered with crimes and intrigues; and he 
            would have been contented to submit himself to 
            the guidance of <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> in any other case wherein 
            his own reputation was not at stake, as in this. 
            For he would do all religiously; and with that 
            feeling consigned in his own mind the wizard and 
            all his influence to the devil, whenever the conviction 
            of it crossed his recollection. In the 
            midst of this debate, if such it may be called, <rs ref="#combah_0001">the 
            other Negro</rs>, <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName>, interposed his good offices, 
            to make peace between his two friends, whom he 
            naturally enough wished to make the stepping-
            stones to a power which he had the hardhihood 
            to covet—no less than the office of king.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Master <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName>,</said> he said, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true"><rs type="persGroup">The white men</rs> 
            believe in you, <rs type="persGroup">the Mulattos</rs> and <rs type="persGroup">Quadroons</rs> too; 
            but <rs type="persGroup">the Negroes</rs> fear <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName>. When we shall have 
            made them free, they will be also free to choose 
            what prayers they like; and if you can shew them 
            such wondrous things as <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> has shewn to me, 
            you will have the same chance, at least, of succeeding 
            with them.</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">The Obeah man</rs> smiled; but <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs>'s 
            features expressed only rage and mortification at 
            this suggestion, heightened by the recollection of 
            <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs>'s trick just practised on himself, and 
            the conviction of the mean figure he must cut in 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">45</fw>
            
            the eyes of both, if <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName> should have been 
            made acquainted with that circumstance. Heated 
            with this indignant feeling, he traversed the cave 
            with an impatient step, as if intent on quitting 
            it, and looking alternately into the various openings 
            which led from it, as if determined to try his 
            fortune, and explore a way though one of them 
            even in the dark. It was in vain that <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName> 
            tried to pacify him; his passion seemed to augment 
            with the concessions of the others; and he 
            continued to denounce <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs> as an agent of 
            hell, while he blundered along one of the galleries, 
            until he was scared back again by the <ecda:fauna>bats</ecda:fauna> flying 
            about him as they returned from the light of the 
            sun to pass their holidays here. Ashamed of his 
            fears, and amazed at the tranquillity he observed 
            on the features of <rs type="persGroup">the two Negroes</rs>, he caught up 
            a machet, and made another sally through a different 
            opening, along which <rs type="persGroup">the tenants</rs> of the 
            cave could hear him groping and stumbling, now 
            shouting, then grumbling again; hacking the 
            rock as he cut at the <ecda:fauna>bats</ecda:fauna>, and cursing these as 
            fiends who inhabited this den of his <rs ref="hamel_0001" type="person">evil genius</rs>, 
            if such a being could exist. His mental and 
            secret determination was to denounce <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah 
            man</rs>, whom he was resolved to bring to justice; 
            but of this nought escaped his lips even in 
            murmurs. Thus blundering on, he reached at 
            last the daylight, and beheld the chasm which 
            he had entered the previous night.</p>
         </div>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">46</fw>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI</head>
               <ab>Come on, sir; here's the place. Stand still: how fearful 
               And dizzy 'tis to cast one's eyes so low!
               SHAKESPEARE.</ab>
            <p>THE way was long enough and close enough, with 
            the exercise of slashing at the <ecda:fauna>bats</ecda:fauna>, to cover the 
            person of <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> with a good tropical 
            perspiration, by the time he arrived at the exit 
            from this cave of abomination, as he had sirnamed 
            it in his mind; so that he stood for some time at 
            the mouth of the gallery, inhaling the fresh breeze, 
            and feasting his eyes with the light of heaven, 
            before he adverted to his particular situation, or 
            to the consideration of any means by which he 
            could descend from that which, had he been 
            covered with feathers, (having only two legs,) 
            might have been called his Alpine perch. A spectator 
            from below would have imagined that nothing 
            less than feathers, or the leathery wings usually 
            and fancifully given to personifications of Satan, 
            could have elevated any animated thing to such a 
            pinnacle as that on which master <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName> stood 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">47</fw>
            
            surveying the scene before him,—not of course like 
            the Devil looking over Lincoln, nor as a black carrion 
            crow vulture elongating his telescopic vision 
            to assure himself of the spot from which his dilated 
            nostril snuffed the carcass;—but as what he 
            really was, a pious adventurer at a stand-still from 
            necessity, inhaling the breath of life to give him 
            strength and confidence to proceed in his vocation.</p>
               
            <p>The illuminated azure of the sky above him 
            was yet stained with fleecy clouds sailing gently 
            to the westward. They might be compared to 
            wounded stragglers in the rear of a victorious 
            army; the followers of the storm; harmless, impotent 
            indications of the violence which had preceded 
            them. The distant sea sparkled in the sun, 
            while its huge waves still retained the elasticity 
            which the hurricane had imparted to them, their 
            summits flashing with white spray, hurried along 
            by the wind, like tears chased from the sunny
            cheeks of youth by hope:—but let us leave metaphors. 
            A considerable plain lay beneath the eyes 
            of <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Methodist</rs>, between the sea and the woods 
            which he immediately overlooked to the eastward. 
            It was here that he could trace the progress of the 
            fires which had alarmed him the previous night. 
            The had raged through a great extent of long 
            <ecda:flora>grass</ecda:flora>, withered by the dry season, and kindled by 
            the negligence of <rs type="persGroup">runaway Negroes</rs>; and although
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">48</fw>
            
            the rain had now quenched their flames, it was 
            very apparent, by the blackened acres they had 
            left, and the smoke yet reeking from them, that 
            their fury must have been uncontrollable except 
            by nature's own efforts; and that, once within 
            their influence, all escape from them would have 
            been impossible to any human being. <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The Missionary</rs>'s 
            course lay across a part of this plain, as 
            he thought, where he contemplated only dust and 
            ashes; and willing to see everything that related 
            to himself in the best light possible, he was fain 
            to attribute the storm he had weathered to the 
            providence of heaven interposing to save the life 
            of one so valuable to <rs type="persGroup">the unchristian Negroes</rs> 
            whom he yet meant to enlighten metaphysically 
            and spiritually. Every stream was yet swollen, 
            and the <placeName ref="#rio_grande">Rio Grande</placeName> rolled among a mass of foam 
            which marked its course high above its usual and 
            natural banks; while fragments of rock and 
            broken <ecda:flora>trees</ecda:flora>, to the euthusiast's imagination, rose 
            and fell as the waves hurled and tossed them 
            about, like condemned spirits tossing on the restless 
            billows of Hades. He felt a sort of pride in 
            the idea, and looked around, bewildered for a moment, 
            in search of some more or less pious fellow-
            creature who might applaud or envy him for the 
            conceit: but his own safety diverted his attention 
            to other objects. He stood at the mouth of the 
            gallery, as we have stated, where the face of the 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">49</fw>
            
            perpendicular rock beneath was cut into some 
            shallow steps leading to a narrow ledge, whence a 
            tree hung over that frightful chasm called the 
            Devil's Gully; a chasm not more than fifteen feet 
            across, but apparently of an immense profundity; 
            for, owing to his present position, <rs ref="roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> 
            could not see down to the current of water which had 
            perhaps formed and now occupied it as its channel 
            to the <placeName ref="#rio_grande">Rio Grande</placeName>. Another <ecda:flora>tree</ecda:flora> lay across the 
            gully; but though he had passed this bridge in the 
            dark, it was too awful to be encountered in the light, 
            which served only to make manifest the danger he 
            had escaped; nay, so terrible did the very descent 
            to it appear down the face of the rock, that he 
            had not hardihood enough to attempt it, urged as he 
            was by horror and disgust of the abominations he 
            had seen in <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs>'s cavern, by his ambition 
            to denounce <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>, and his anxiety to 
            regain the habitations of civilized life, for more 
            than one purpose which he had at heart. It was in 
            vain that he strained his neck in every direction, 
            to spy out some hope for effecting his escape, 
            some human being who might come to his assistance; 
            in vain he searched with his eyes every 
            <ecda:flora>bush</ecda:flora> beneath him for his boy <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName>, and his 
            <ecda:fauna>Spanish horse</ecda:fauna>, and all his moveables. The 
            mountain path was not visible from his eyrie, 
            and the jungle concealed everything that could 
            have consoled him, encouraged him, or given 
            
            <fw>VOL. I</fw>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">50</fw>
            
            him a hope of emancipation from <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah 
            man</rs>'s abode and power. Hour after hour 
            elapsed as <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> still contemplated the 
            scene before him; and he began to feel again the 
            calls of hunger, as well as to entertain some little 
            surprise that neither <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> nor <persName ref="combah_0001">Combah</persName> interfered 
            with or even followed him. What could 
            be their motive for thus neglecting him? Did they 
            calculate on starving  him into submission to their 
            plans, knowing the almost insurmountable difficulties 
            he must encounter in attempting to descend 
            the rocks? His life was in their power, 
            but that was not worth their taking; moreover 
            <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName> depended much on him for his influence 
            with the Christian part of the population; and 
            <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName> was a Christian. If <hi rend="italics">he</hi> could be prevailed 
            on, <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the wizard</rs> might be kept in check; nay, was it 
            not prudent after all to give or appear to give way 
            to <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>, who had such a strange and perverse 
            power over the minds of <rs type="persGroup">the Blacks</rs>? The 
            point once gained, the rebellion in vigour, <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> 
            might be outwitted, anyhow disposed of; it were 
            no sin to slay an accomplice of the devil, or 
            to launch him from his fastness into the dingles 
            below. <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">Indeed,</said> thought he, as the reflection 
            gained on him, <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">it were perhaps an act of piety 
            and just retribution, and one which <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName> 
            himself might be induced to put in force.</said></p>
               
            <p><persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName> determined to return into the cavern; in 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">51</fw>
            
            fact, any longer stay in his present position was 
            evidently absurd, as he was utterly afraid to attempt 
            a descent; and happen what might, he must return 
            through <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>'s apartment, before he 
            could regain the abode<unclear>s</unclear> of <rs type="persGroup">white men</rs>. There 
            was <ecda:anonPers>a lady</ecda:anonPers> too in the case; a young person on 
            whom he had set his affections, whom he desired 
            ardently to revisit, as soon as he should have 
            effected the purpose for which he had undertaken 
            his journey to the abandoned settlement noticed 
            in a previous part of this narrative. Without the 
            help of <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName>, he knew not how to assure himself 
            of any success with this young person; for she 
            had not as yet returned his love, nor any acknowledgment 
            of it or for it. She would neither listen 
            to nor even look on him, if she could avoid it; and 
            she had been heard to express no less horror of 
            him and his misplaced affection, than that which 
            <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> himself had felt for <persName ref="#hamel_0001">Hamel</persName> and 
            his office. This feeling had incensed <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Methodist</rs> 
            without at all diminishing his love, which 
            was of a nature more passionate perhaps than 
            refined. It wounded him besides in the tenderest 
            part of his spirituality, his vanity; for he knew 
            that she preferred <ecda:anonPers>another one</ecda:anonPers>, whom he was 
            accustomed to regard as a worthless, irreligious, 
            profane, and at the same time daring adventurer, 
            who had scoffed at him and his <hi rend="italics">religion</hi>, and 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">52</fw>
            
            denounced him publicly as a cheat and an impostor. 
            To circumvent <ecda:anonPers>this youth</ecda:anonPers>, and to gain possession 
            of <ecda:anonPers>the lady</ecda:anonPers>, had been the first motives for 
            his league with <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName>. In the confusion of 
            a revolt, successful or unsuccessful, an opportunity 
            would be contrived by the <rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">would-be king</rs> 
            and his followers for <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">the Missionary</rs> to seize and 
            carry off his prize; at least he had so bargained 
            with <rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">his majesty</rs>. Once his, for ever his, thought 
            he; fraud, violence, would be compensated by the 
            offer of his hand; and his character was in too high 
            esteem among all ranks who knew him by name 
            and by his preaching, to suffer anything from the 
            breath of slander. This was his idea, supposing 
            the revolt to fail. If it succeeded, he 
            became the right-hand man of <rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">the king</rs>, viceroy 
            over him, as <persName ref="#trinculo_0001">Trinculo</persName> happily observes; the 
            keeper of his conscience, high priest, pope protestant 
            of the island, with a beautiful girl for 
            his wife. <rs ref="#roland_0001" type="person">The enthusiast</rs>'s ambition was not so 
            immoderate as to extend farther than a desire for 
            dominion over the consciences of all <rs type="persGroup">the inhabitants</rs> 
            and their <rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">monarch</rs>; but the monarch, it 
            seemed, had already revolted from his spiritual 
            prostration, in listening to and expressing his wish 
            to profit by the spells of <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">an infidel dabbler in 
            magic</rs>, or <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">a pretended dabbler</rs>; for <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName> was 
            undecided as to the opinion he ought to adopt 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">53</fw>
            
            about him, not being altogether persuaded of the 
            possibility of enlisting fiends and demons into 
            human service.</p>
               
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="false">Well,</said> thought he, turning round to retrace 
            his steps, <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">something must be done; I shall not 
            be the first who has held a candle to the D—.</said>
            The very thought made him shudder. <said rend="quotes" aloud="false">If argument 
            fail, cunning, manoeuvering, may do it; at 
            any rate I must get out of this infernal abode, cost 
            what it will; inquire for <rs ref="#cuffy_0001" type="person">my servant</rs> and my <ecda:fauna>horse</ecda:fauna>; 
            and if the rivers admit of it, pursue my course to 
            that plantation of misery where <rs type="persGroup">the revolted 
            Negroes</rs> await me.</said></p>
               
            <p>With this idea he recomposed his features, and 
            recommenced his battle with the <ecda:fauna>bats</ecda:fauna>, returning 
            with much deliberation and more confidence to 
            the interior of the cave. Here let us for the present 
            leave him, and adjourn to a different scene 
            and subject, of no less importance, to the reader 
            at least, than <rs type="persGroup">the trio of persons</rs> whom we quit 
            for the purpose of introducing the young and 
            beautiful, the amiable and innocent <persName ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001">Joanna</persName>.</p>
            <!-- PUT JOANNA IN PERSONOGRAPHY SHEET -->
            </div>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">54</fw>
         
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
            <ab> —Cytheres, <!-- long dash -->
            How bravely thou becom'st thy bed, fresh lily!
            And whiter than the sheets—that I might touch!
            But kiss; one kiss!
            SHAKESPEARE</ab>
            
            <p>THE storm of the preceding night, whose violence 
            we have commemorated, had wrecked, no doubt, 
            many a gallant vessel and many a wayworn bark, 
            whose <rs type="persGroup">crews</rs>, sinking into the waves which ingulphed 
            them, sank likewise into oblivion, as far 
            at least as all knowledge or certainty of their fate 
            has been rendered evident. Others, dead in 
            nature, may yet live in history for a year or two; 
            and vice versâ, the <rs type="persGroup">survivors</rs> in nature are all dead <!-- symbol above a on versa = use circumflex -->
            in history, with the exception of a few miserables 
            whom fortune rescued from the deep to be recorded 
            in these pages.</p>
            
            <p>It was near midnight, and the storm was 
            at its height, and every house in the island which 
            had such means of defence barricadoed to resist it, 
            when <ecda:persGroup>a rather motley group of persons</ecda:persGroup>, eight or 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">55</fw>
            
            ten in number, knocked at the house of <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">a gentleman</rs> 
            in the parish of St Mary, and demanded the 
            rights of hospitality. This house was situated 
            within half a mile of the sea, at <!-- long dash --> Bay, and 
            <rs type="persGroup">the strangers</rs> said they had been wrecked in a 
            large canoe, with which they had crossed from 
            <placeName ref="cuba">Cuba</placeName>; where, as they farther stated, they had 
            been detained as prisoners by a party of <rs type="persGroup">pirates</rs>. 
            <rs type="persGroup">The inhabitants</rs> of the house were more surprised 
            at their being able to reach it, although to leeward 
            of the spot where they had been cast on 
            shore, than at their request to be received and entertained 
            in it; an indulgence to which all persons 
            in the island, in case of need at least, would have 
            fancied themselves entitled under any circumstances; 
            I should say all <ecda:persGroup><!-- hi rend="italics" -->white persons</ecda:persGroup>. A window 
            of the piazza was opened, and the party 
            reconnoitred, with the help of a lanthorn, by <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">an 
            old gentleman</rs> from within; for being <ecda:persGroup>strangers</ecda:persGroup> 
            and from another island, they were liable to a 
            little suspicion; and the mention of the word pirates 
            perhaps gave birth to an idea of the possibility 
            of their being themselves of that calling. They presented 
            themselves to the old gentleman's gaze in 
            succession; and the opened window being on the 
            lee side of the house, he could examine their features 
            with some little attention, and make what 
            enquiries he thought fit to put to them, so 
            as to be heard and answered; but the vio-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">56</fw>
            
            lence of the storm threatening to burst in the 
            shutters on the weather-side of the piazza, it became 
            necessary, as a security in case of such an 
            accident, to shut the aforesaid window; for if the 
            gale should once gain passage through the house, 
            the building would inevitably go to pieces, and 
            its <ecda:persGroup>inhabitants</ecda:persGroup> might be blown away with the rest 
            of its contents; a circumstance that has occurred 
            more than once in this part of the globe. <ecda:persGroup>The 
            shipwrecked men</ecda:persGroup> were therefore admitted, after a 
            mutilated set of interrogatories through the piazza 
            window, which was closed and again barricadoed, 
            for fear the wind might shift; and all hands immediately 
            repaired, as if by instinct, to that portion 
            of the building which was more directly 
            threatened. Here <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">the owner</rs> of the mansion 
            resumed the labours he had evidently left but a 
            few minutes before, which consisted in pulling to 
            pieces a bedstead, with the materials of which he 
            was adding to his stauncheons and barricadoes; 
            almost heedless of his <ecda:persGroup>guests</ecda:persGroup>, whom he had commended 
            to the care of <ecda:anonPers>a Negro butler</ecda:anonPers>, desiring he 
            would furnish them from the beaufet with <ecda:commodity>rum</ecda:commodity> or 
            any <ecda:commodity>liqueurs</ecda:commodity> they might like: food was for the 
            present out of the question all the offices of the 
            house being detached, and consequently unattaineable 
            except by quitting the mansion. But the 
            new guests, too sensible of the danger which 
            menaced them, repaired at once to his assist-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">57</fw>
            ance, and secured the bed-posts against the 
            shutters and doors, before they attended to any of 
            the other directions of their <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">host</rs>, or adverted to 
            the rest of the <ecda:persGroup>inmates</ecda:persGroup> of the dwelling, whose 
            situation seemed yet to require some attention, 
            after all measures of security had been completed. 
            It was then that one of the party, looking into a 
            chamber whose window opened upon the piazza, 
            beheld a <rs type="person">lady</rs> pale and almost insensible, supported 
            in an arm chair by <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">a <distinct>Quadroon</distinct> soubrette</rs>, 
            who applied a smelling bottle of some essence to 
            her nostrils with one hand, while with the other 
            she chafed her <rs type="person">mistress</rs>'s temples. It was but a 
            momentary glance in which <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the stranger</rs> indulged 
            —a feeling of delicacy prevented him from gazing 
            with too much curiosity; but it sufficed to convince 
            him that <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">the soubrette</rs> was a very beautiful 
            girl, and that the lady herself was no ordinary 
            person; she looked but little turned of thirty 
            years of age, for her complexion was smooth, 
            clear, and bright, as if she had never known a tropical 
            climate; but it was the whiteness almost of 
            alabaster, without a tinge of blood in her cheek; 
            and as she lay in the arm chair so languid and 
            pale, her dark hair disheveled, a litle on her 
            brows, assumed a deeper hue, perhaps by so glaring 
            a contrast. She opened her eyes at the moment 
            that this stranger removed from his position; 
            and seeing a man in the piazza whom she neither 
            knew nor recollected to have seen before, uttered 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">58</fw>
            
            a faint and half-stifled cry as she clung to the 
            arms of <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">the Quadroon</rs>.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Leave me not, <persName ref="#michal_0001">Michal</persName>,</said> she said; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">leave me 
            not. What man is that? Is the house on fire? 
            Where is <persName ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001">Joanna</persName>?</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">The stranger</rs> looked round on hearing this exclamation, 
            which did not escape the notice of his 
            <ecda:persGroup>comrades</ecda:persGroup>, who crowded towards the window; and 
            at the same moment <persName ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001">Joanna</persName> herself appeared, in 
            answer to her <rs type="person">mother</rs>'s interrogatory, from a contiguous 
            apartment; but as she approached the arm 
            chair, she started at the sight of so many black 
            and brown faces starting into the chamber, and 
            would have retired again, in evident alarm, had 
            not the stranger who had first beheld her mother, 
            called to her in a gentle and assuring voice, that 
            she had nothing to fear. <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">The lord of the mansion</rs> 
            had left his barricades for an instant; but the howling 
            of the storm recalled him quickly to his post, 
            whither the stranger directed his <ecda:persGroup>companions</ecda:persGroup> to 
            attend him again, while he himself, fixed by the 
            appearance of <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">the young lady</rs>, delayed for a moment 
            or two joining them.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Who and what are you?</said> said <persName ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001">Joanna</persName>, in a 
            timid voice.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">We are <ecda:persGroup>shipwrecked men</ecda:persGroup>,</said> replied <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the 
            stranger</rs>; <said rend="quotes">profiting by your hospitality.</said></p>
            
            <p>If <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">the young lady</rs> was startled in the first instance, 
            she was even yet surprised to hear <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">a man 
            with a mulatto skin</rs> speak in a dialect so very far 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">59</fw>
            
            removed from that of <ecda:persGroup>the Negroes</ecda:persGroup>; and he appeared 
            to be a little confounded at the sight of 
            this <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">beautiful creature</rs>. her complexion was 
            nearly similar to that of her <rs type="person">mother</rs>, pale and delicate; 
            but her figure was firm and elastic, not 
            withstanding her alarm; and the scanty portion 
            of clothes in which she was clad, concealed but 
            little of its elegant outline. Her paleness might 
            be attributed to her apprehensions, for the colour 
            had even fled from her lips, or at least there was 
            but enough of the rose left there to characterize 
            her as an animated creature of this earth, who might 
            otherwise have been almost fancied a being 
            of another world. She was as fair as pale, with 
            large blue eyes, from which her terror had but 
            just chased her tears, as was but too evident from 
            the expression of grief still upon her features; and 
            with her hair partly bound round her head in 
            braids, partly disordered on her shoulders, and 
            waiving in the current of the wind, she wanted 
            only the chaplet of <ecda:flora>flowers</ecda:flora> which the painter has 
            given to <persName ref="#proserpina_0001">Proserpine</persName>, to have formed the type, if 
            not the model, for that beautiful production of the 
            pencil of Schiavoni, where Pluto, with the air and 
            hue of a stout Sambo, is carrying off his prize 
            from her pastoral diversions to the realms of Tartarus. 
            But the figure of Pluto would not correspond 
            with that of <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the spectator</rs>, who still fixed his 
            eyes on her as by a kind of fascination; for the
            
            <!-- Mark this as reference to outside stories? Mark up the names? -->
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">60</fw>
            
            king of Erebus, according to the artist, is short, 
            thick, and clumsy; whereas this <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">sambo-coloured 
            man</rs> was tall and well proportioned, of a most dignified 
            and commanding manner, open and undisguised, 
            with nothing in his appearance indicative 
            of the robber or ravisher. He sighed as he looked 
            at her again, and quickly removed his gaze to his 
            <ecda:persGroup>companions</ecda:persGroup>, who were yet labouring for their 
            <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">host</rs> to secure the very spars of the roof, lest the 
            hurricane should tear that shelter from their heads. 
            <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">The young lady</rs> turned to her <rs type="person">mother</rs> with a view 
            to assist <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">the soubrette</rs> in her attentions; and <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">the 
            old gentleman</rs>, working like a <persName ref="#hercules_0001">Hercules</persName>, from time 
            to time thanked his <ecda:persGroup>guests</ecda:persGroup> for their assistance, 
            without which his house and household would 
            have been, as he said, in but a very indifferent 
            plight; for <ecda:persGroup>the Negroes</ecda:persGroup> belonging to the estate, 
            in confirmation of the truth that charity begins at 
            home, had all abandoned their <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">master</rs>'s abode, to 
            guard each his own dwelling. At any other time, 
            at least upon a less serious occasion, his costume 
            and appearance would have excited a smile even 
            on the negro faces which were now turned on 
            him; for both almost bordered on the ludicrous. 
            In the hurry of quitting his chamber at the commencement 
            of the storm, he had put on a long 
            dressing gown of chintz or dark-figured cotton, 
            two-thirds of which had been since torn off by his 
            efforts and struggles in contending against the 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">61</fw>
            
            elements, so that it had become a sort of spencer, 
            which gave to view a pair of black silk breeches, 
            with large Spanish silver knee-buckles, matched, 
            though scarcely surpassed by another pair of the 
            same metal on his shoes. He was some fifty years 
            of age; and his hair, a mixture of brown and grey, 
            was combed from off his face with such accuracy 
            and perseverance to form a queue, tied close up 
            to his occiput, that it seemed to drag with it all 
            the muscular part and power of his cheeks, forehead, 
            nose, and mouth; so that many of his acquaintance 
            were accustomed to fancy he never 
            could shut his eyes without letting go his pigtail. 
            Indeed by the same rule he could never open them 
            to their full capability of extension; for the corners 
            were drawn forcibly towards his temples, resembling 
            in figure and effect those of the cayman; and 
            all he could do as to motion with these his half 
            opened window-lights, was to wink them once or 
            twice a day. Superadded to this rather droll 
            part of his physiognomy, one of the aforesaid eyes 
            was gifted with a most ominous cast in its vision, 
            and appeared to the spectator on whom it was intended 
            to be turned (under influence fo any 
            passion) to be contemplating the starts, or reading 
            calculations, (written by the imagination of which 
            it was the light,) in the penetralia of the brains 
            behind it. With all this singularity his materiel, 
            he displayed a most pompous though inof-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">62</fw>
            
            fensive solemnity in his march, manners, deportment, 
            and address, which extended to the 
            language in which he sometimes buried rather than 
            clothed his thoughts. He had likewise a taste 
            for ornamenting his discourse with quotations from 
            <ecda:persGroup>the Latin authors</ecda:persGroup>; and though he understood or 
            appeared to understand the application and translation 
            of these elegancies, his <ecda:persGroup>hearers</ecda:persGroup> were not 
            always so fortunate, owing to some peculiarities 
            to which he was attached of now and then altering 
            the cases and genders of adjectives and articles. 
            Things are not expected to be exactly 
            similar in the old and new world. <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName> <!-- Add Guthrie to Personography Spreadsheet when I decide if he 
                                                                                                         gets a first name or not -->
            knew nothing but by hear-say of the first, having 
            never been off the island of <placeName ref="#jamaica">Jamaica</placeName> but once in 
            his life, and that only a few years back, when he 
            was taken by a boat's crew from a log of mahogany 
            of which he was making prize in the 
            ocean (having seen it with a glass from his piazza 
            window.) He had no sooner seen than he desired 
            to possess it; ordered out his boats and <ecda:persGroup>Negroes</ecda:persGroup>, 
            came up with and was himself securing it, when 
            a strange sail, which had been skulking under the 
            rocks, sprung out upon him like a lion on his 
            prey; and before his <ecda:persGroup>Negroes</ecda:persGroup> could disengage him 
            from the log, he was a prisoner. Indeed he bid 
            them seek their own safety, for (his presence of 
            mind not forsaking him) he calculated on the expense 
            of redeemign half a dozen slaves as well as 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">63</fw>
            
            himself, and had nearly lost his life for his prudence 
            or parsimony; <ecda:persGroup>the pirates</ecda:persGroup> threatening to 
            fling him into the sea, until he persuaded them 
            that <ecda:persGroup>the Negroes</ecda:persGroup> had rowed off from their own 
            fears. However, they carried him away; but being 
            happily taken into <placeName ref="#guadeloupe">Guadaloupe</placeName> by a French 
            cruizer, they were disposed of according to law; 
            and he, having proved his innocence, was dismissed 
            with great courtesy, and sent home. Upon 
            his arrival however, he found he had cause to regret 
            his absence; some of his buildings had been 
            burnt, it was supposed maliciously; and he had 
            found his <rs type="person">wife</rs> in a state of melancholy and ill 
            health, owing, as was said, to her alarm respecting 
            him, in the first place; and in the second, to 
            her terrors occasioned by the fire, from which to 
            this hour she had not recovered. These terrors 
            were revived on the present occasion. The combustion 
            of the elements, the earthquake which 
            had convulsed the house, the wind and the lightning, 
            however frequent in the island, all raging in 
            unison, had filled her with physical alarm, as well 
            as superstitious apprehensions, to which her state 
            of mind had left her but too subject. It was to 
            no purpose that her <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">husband</rs> argued with her on 
            the folly of such fancies; in vain that her <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">daughter</rs> 
            sought and practised every means of consoling 
            her. Though not insensible, she appeared to be 
            indifferent to both, to everything that had hitherto 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">64</fw>
            
            given her any sort of consolation or interest. She 
            even preferred, or seemed to prefer, the absence of 
            her <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">daughter</rs>, as if the sight of  this her only child 
            increased her agitations, and as if those attentions 
            which <persName ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001">Joanna</persName> too fondly paid her, excited only 
            painful recollections. So, in the midst of her present 
            alarms, she had in a manner banished her 
            daughter to her own chamber, and accepted the 
            services of <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">the soubrette</rs>; and hence the tears 
            and distress of the former, for whose presence 
            she had only called at the sight of <ecda:persGroup>the strange 
            guests</ecda:persGroup> with whom the storm had accommodated 
            them, and then only from an apprehension for her 
            personal safety.</p>
         </div>
         
         <pb/>
         <fw type="pageNum">65</fw>
         
         <div type="chapter">
            <head> CHAPTER VIII.</head>
            <ab>This tempest will not give me leave to ponder
            On things would hurt me more.              SHAKSPEARE</ab>
            
            <p>WE left <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>, and his <ecda:persGroup>black and brown 
            guests</ecda:persGroup>, still engaged in the defence of his chateau 
            against the attacks of the hurricane. Their arrival 
            had been extremely apropose, and their services 
            actually saved the dwelling from being blown to 
            pieces; but as they had come with a very different 
            purpose from that which they had executed, 
            it may not be amiss to acquaint the reader with 
            the actual primary intention of this <ecda:persGroup>band of worthies</ecda:persGroup>, 
            which was no less than robbery.</p>
            
            <p>It was no less than robbery; but that was to 
            have been the secondary object at which they 
            aimed; the first being to make prize of the fair 
            <persName ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001">Joanna</persName>—for her advancement, it is true, as the 
            royal-minded <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName> designed to make her queen 
            of the island. <rs ref="#combah_0001" type="person">His majesty</rs> had rightly calculated 
            that it would be too late to make any attempt on 
            this his <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">bride</rs> elect, after the island should have 
            been alarmed; as many would take to the ships, 
            and all who did not would crowd into the towns
            
            <fw>VOL. I.</fw>
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">66</fw>
            
            for security in such an event; and it would be a 
            business of great difficulty to get possession of 
            her under the circumstances that would attend the 
            latter case; and next to impossible, if her <ecda:persGroup>parents</ecda:persGroup> 
            should once get her off the island. It were better 
            to take time by the forelock, can secure <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">the young 
            lady</rs> before a fear or suspicion of a revolt should 
            affect the minds of <ecda:persGroup>the inhabitants</ecda:persGroup>. With this 
            feeling a canoe had been provided, whose <ecda:persGroup>crew</ecda:persGroup> 
            were to hover on the coast, sometimes at sea, 
            sometimes on shore, as occasion might require. 
            They were to watch to windward for a certain 
            signal, at the signt of which they were, if necessary, 
            to attack the house of <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>; at any 
            rate to seize the young lady, hurry her away to 
            the canoe, and bring her, not to the abandoned 
            settlement behind <placeName ref="#port_antonio">Port Antonio</placeName>, but to the cave 
            of <rs ref="#hamel_0001" type="person">the Obeah man</rs>. This signal was to be the 
            kindling of three fires on one of the ridges of the 
            <placeName ref="#blue_mountains">Blue Mountain</placeName>; and we have seen how it 
            happened that on the night in question <persName ref="#roland_0001">Roland</persName> 
            and his boy <persName ref="#cuffy_0001">Cuffy</persName> had looked with no little terror 
            on as many if not more of these wandering flames; 
            which, although they had been accidentally 
            kindled by <ecda:persGroup>runaway Negroes</ecda:persGroup>, had carried a conviction 
            to the minds of <persName ref="#combah_0001">Combah</persName>'s delegates, that 
            this was their signal, and that now was the moment 
            for going to work. But the storm had run 
            their canoe on the rocks, damaged it, and, as they 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">67</fw>
            
            feared, almost beaten it to pieces. It was not without 
            difficulty that they saved their lives; and 
            to escape from the hurricane, they had ultimately 
            been obliged to ask hospitality at the very dwelling 
            against whose inmates they had meditated 
            such horrible violence. Their plan therefore (at 
            least for the present) was suspended, if not frustrated; 
            for although they might have carried off 
            <persName ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001">Joanna</persName> by sea, it would be worse than madness 
            to attempt such a scheme by land; nay, it would 
            be impossible, except the whole country were in 
            open revolt; and even then it would be no easy 
            matter to persuade <ecda:persGroup><persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>'s Negroes</ecda:persGroup> to 
            suffer such violence to be done to him on any pretence. 
            These were ideas which had been commmunicated 
            among <ecda:persGroup>the party</ecda:persGroup> as they groped their 
            way in the storm to the mansion where we have 
            introduced them. Once within it, they had little 
            opportunity of comparing notes or hatching any 
            fresh schemes, or even of mutual converse: they 
            were occupied with <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">the master of the house</rs> in 
            counteracting the fury of the wind; and although 
            they had had a sight of <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">the fair creature</rs> who had 
            been marked for their prey, there was but one of 
            them who had been allowed more than a momentary 
            look at her; and he, strange to say, had 
            turned them aside from the contemplation of a 
            person whom they had in some sort hired him to 
            steal, or to assist in stealing. <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">This stranger</rs> they 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">68</fw>
            
            had brought from the south side of <placeName ref="#cuba">Cuba</placeName>, where 
            he described himself to have fled from the cruelty 
            and oppression of <ecda:anonPers>a white man</ecda:anonPers> who wished to 
            make property of him. His story might be true 
            or false; but at any rate he had ingratiated himself 
            so far in their good opinion, as to have learnt 
            the purpose for which they were bound to <placeName ref="#jamaica">Jamaica</placeName>; 
            and on the plea of avenging himself on <ecda:anonPers>the 
            tyrant</ecda:anonPers> who had oppressed him, he had been permitted, 
            and finally encouraged, to take part with 
            them in their enterprise; more particularly, as he 
            gave them reason to see that he was acquainted 
            with the part of the island in which the scene of 
            their affair was to be laid, and with the house in 
            question; although he owned no knowledge of its 
            inmates. <hi rend="italics">He</hi> was to assist in carrying off <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">the 
            young lady</rs>; <hi rend="italics">they</hi> to further his views of 
            vengeance on the unjust and inhuman tyrant 
            who had practised against his liberty and independence. 
            But let us return to <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>.</p>
            
            <p>This <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">unsuspecting gentleman</rs>, occupied more 
            with the danger which had threatened his mansion 
            from the fury of the elements, than with the 
            fears and fancies of his wife, to which time had a 
            little hardened him, succeeded eventually, with 
            the assistance of his <ecda:persGroup>guests</ecda:persGroup>, in securing his doors 
            and windows, and the spars of his house; and, in 
            short, enabled it to weather the gale, which abated, 
            as we have seen, towards morning, and had 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">69</fw>
            
            so far subsided by daylight, as to admit of the 
            defences being withdrawn for the purposes of 
            ingress and egress.</p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">The old gentleman</rs>'s gratitude as well as hospitality, 
            begun now to manifest themselves more 
            visibly in his wishes and offers of rewards and 
            refreshments, for the services he had received 
            from his <ecda:persGroup>strange guests</ecda:persGroup>; offers which he, with 
            apparent difficulty only, could prevail on them to 
            accept—that is, as to the rewards. The refreshments 
            they declined; not thinking it advisable 
            perhaps to continue under the roof of one to 
            whom they had meditated so deep an injury, especailly 
            as his <ecda:persGroup>Negroes</ecda:persGroup> began to assemble about 
            the premises, and learnt with some feeling of 
            shame and surprise, that their <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">master</rs> owed the 
            preservation of his house to a band of <ecda:persGroup>strange 
            people of colour</ecda:persGroup>. Nay, <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName> spared no 
            pains to encrease their shame, in vaunting to them 
            the noble and disinterested endeavours of these 
            <ecda:persGroup>good men</ecda:persGroup>, as he called them, who had so fortunately 
            come to his assistance, when his own 
            <ecda:persGroup>Negroes</ecda:persGroup> had left him to the mercy of the storm.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">I tell you,</said> cried he, (feeling for the skirts of 
            his dressing gown,) <said rend="quotes">that you have entailed a 
            lasting disgrace on yourselves and your posterity; 
            you are as bad as <ecda:persGroup>the white people in England</ecda:persGroup>; you 
            left your master and mistress, and your young mistress—
            your benefactors—your natural lord, my-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">70</fw>
            
            self—to perish in the wind: what could <ecda:persGroup>the white 
            varlets</ecda:persGroup> in England do worse? You think yourselves 
            better than they are; <persName ref="#roland_0001">Mr Roland</persName> tells you 
            that you are, and I used to think he was right. 
            I only wonder you did not profit by the occasion 
            to thieve; but I suppose you were too busy with 
            your own <ecda:fauna>cocks</ecda:fauna> and <ecda:fauna>hens</ecda:fauna>, and your <ecda:fauna>pigs</ecda:fauna>, your 
            <ecda:flora>plantains</ecda:flora>, your furniture, your houses, your find 
            clothes, your doubloons, and your dollars; and 
            now perhaps you are only come to see whether 
            the storm has not left something for you to plunder, 
            or blown something away from the stores of 
            which you may make prize. Are not you ashamed 
            that I should owe my safety to <ecda:persGroup>strangers</ecda:persGroup>? Why, 
            I suppose it would have been the same if we had 
            been attacked by <ecda:persGroup>pirates</ecda:persGroup> or <ecda:persGroup>runaway Negroes</ecda:persGroup>. 
            You would have left us to our fate; we might 
            have been robbed, murdered, and flung in the sea, 
            before you would have come to our help.</said></p>
            
            <p>This harangue was made from the steps of the 
            piazza, where <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>, heated, exhausted, 
            indignant, adn enraged, gave vent to his passion in 
            thus stigmatizing the feelings of his <ecda:persGroup>slaves</ecda:persGroup> for attending 
            to their own affairs in the late emergency, 
            instead of sacrificing them to their concern for 
            his. If his figure and appearance were ludicrous 
            by the lamp light of the preceding night, they 
            were scarcely less than diverting even to his 
            <ecda:persGroup>Negroes</ecda:persGroup> by day. In feeling for the skirts of his 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">71</fw>
            
            dressing gown, which had now been restored to 
            him by <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">the soubrette</rs>, he had discovered a woful 
            gash in his silk breeches, over which he hung 
            the fragments he had received, in the manner of 
            a petticoat. His features were disfigured with 
            perspiration, dust and dirt; and his hands, which 
            he displayed in suiting the action to the word, 
            were as black nearly as those of the sable gentry 
            he addressed. So laughable indeed was his appearance 
            altogether, that <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the brown stranger</rs> in 
            whose praise he was speaking (the person who 
            had appeared to possess an influence over his 
            comrades) could scarcely retain his gravity, in 
            spite of the more serious ideas which we may 
            suppose were fermenting in his brains, whenever
            the sinister eye of his host was diverted from him 
            to the multitude he anathematized. As for the 
            rest of the chosen few who had merited the eulogy 
            of <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>, they had begun some time since 
            to effect a retreat towards the shore, on pretence 
            of examining their boat, and securing what effects 
            the sea might have spared them from it:—not 
            altogether a pretence, although there was perhaps 
            a no less important consideration which affected 
            them in thus withdrawing themselves; namely, 
            the apprehension of being suspected, recognised 
            by any of the multitude, detected, and secured. 
            Nay, one of them had overheard an old black 
            woman, surnamed <ecda:anonPers>the White Fairy</ecda:anonPers>, (because she 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">72</fw>
            
            was as black as pitch,) muttering beneath the 
            piazza window, that her master need not brag so 
            much of his new friends, who, bad as they looked, 
            ("fit only for the John-crows,") still looked better 
            than they were in reality; and, as the listener 
            seemed to wince a little on hearing her oracular 
            inuendo, she had begun to assume a bolder tone, 
            and called out for the sailor's paper, a word significative 
            of passport. The paper, sure enough, 
            had been prepared; but there was no immediate 
            occasion, according to their ideas, of submitting 
            it to inspection and scrutiny; and they judged 
            it better to remove to the sea-shore, for the purposes 
            above-mentioned. Thither they proceeded 
            without delay; leaving their <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">comrade</rs> with the 
            <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">master of the house</rs>, to answer all interrogatories, 
            and make any reconnoissance he should think 
            proper for the furthering of the scheme which was 
            the subject of their expedition.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName> saw them depart, without making 
            any remark, supposing their intention to be such 
            as they represented; but as soon as his passion 
            thus vented on his <ecda:persGroup>slaves</ecda:persGroup> had in some meausure 
            abated, he began to pay a little attention to this 
            more important-looking personage; of whom, 
            considering his colour, he felt authorized to ask 
            his name and lineage, at the same time that he 
            begged his acceptance of a doubloon, in testimony 
            of the services he wished to acknowledge. This 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">73</fw>
            
            <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the Mulatto-man</rs> decidedly renounced, as well as 
            all claim to it; declaring, that he and his comrades 
            were no less indebted to <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>, than 
            he to them; but if there were to be obligation on 
            either part, it would be of a nature very different 
            from any hiterto thought or spoken of; 
            and perhaps he might have it in his power, without 
            however claiming any acknowledgment for it, 
            to render his liberal host some really essential 
            benefit.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Hah!</said> cried <rs ref="#guthrie_0001">the lord of the house</rs>, with a 
            most solemn inclination of his head, at the same 
            time stretching his dirty face, to expand his eyeballs; 
            <said rend="quotes">an essential benefit! This is an enigma 
            in which you are pleased to indulge, friend. 
            What may be your means of serving one who 
            certainly had as little title as expectation to receive 
            assistance already at your hands? But I 
            have no right to ask questions, whether you may 
            or may not be disposed to gratify my curiosity. 
            Still are your words the words of mystery; and 
            we know we have much to fear just now from the 
            abominably impudent and shameless opinions 
            about liberty, forsooth, which our <ecda:persGroup>transatlantic 
            cousins</ecda:persGroup>, in the old stupid world, are foisting 
            upon the better-informed, better-educated, more 
            liberal and enlightened people of the great <placeName rend="#antilles">Antilles</placeName>. 
            Are we to hae a revolt? Come, you may 
            be in the secret?</said></p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">74</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">God forbid,</said> replied <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the Mulatto</rs>, <said rend="quotes">that you 
            should fear even a revolt. Nor can I detail the 
            ideas which I may entertain of being useful to 
            you; you would not credit <hi rend="italics">me</hi>, a stranger, and a 
            man of colour.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Why, faith!</said> rejoined Mr Guthrie, <said rend="quotes">you are 
            a man of a common colour, but of no common 
            speech; nor can I think that you have African 
            blood in your veins, despite your colour. Let me 
            see, you told us last night that you came from 
            Cuba, where you had been detained by pirates. 
            Are you a free man? Yes," he continued, "I think 
            I may answer that question myself.</said></p>
            
            <p><rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">The Mulatto</rs> bowed.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Those who brought me from Cuba,</said> replied 
            he, <said rend="quotes">assured me that they were free; that they 
            keep or kept a canoe, with which they carried 
            passengers, and sometimes goods, from <placeName>Montego 
            bay</placeName> to <placeName>St. Lucie</placeName>.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">And you believe their story,</said> demanded the 
            other?</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">I do not.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">But you can see their tale is true, as to the 
            mischief they have suffered.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Yonder is their bark, which they have hauled 
            beyond the reach of the waves and spray; and, as 
            you may distinguish, even without your glass, 
            they are endeavouring to repair it.</said></p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">75</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">I will at least send them tools and assistance,</said> 
            observed <placeName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</placeName>, looking at them 
            through his telescope; <said rend="quotes">and a carpenter or two, 
            and anything else you think they may be in need 
            of.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">At your pleasure, sir</said> replied the Mulatto; 
            <said rend="quotes">and it is time that I should also retire to them.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">No! no!</said> interrupted <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>; <said rend="quotes">sit you 
            down here; you shall be taken care of, at least. 
            <ecda:persGroup>The Negroes</ecda:persGroup> will give your <ecda:persGroup>companions</ecda:persGroup> wherewithal 
            to make a breakfast. You shall be entertained 
            here, while I go to dress myself. Sit 
            down.</said></p>
            
            <p>It was in vain that <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the Mulatto</rs> protested against 
            such an honour as breakfasting in the piazza of 
            <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">the white man</rs>: his bows either were not sufficiently 
            disqualifying, or there was something in his 
            physiognomy which excited the pertinacity of the 
            buckra. At any rate, he allowed himself to be 
            prevailed on, and took his station, as desired: 
            while <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName>, having given the orders he had 
            proposed, and sent down the assistance and provisions 
            he designed for his <ecda:persGroup>late guests</ecda:persGroup>, betook 
            himself to his own room, to depurate his person, 
            as he termed the act of ablution; and left <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the 
            Mulatto-man</rs> alone in the hall of his mansion.</p>
            
            <p>The hall opened into the piazza, and several 
            bed-chambers communicated with the hall. 
            The Mulatto had not been doomed to his own 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">76</fw>
            
            company many minutes before he saw one of the 
            doors gently open, and a pair of black eyes peep 
            on him from a face, the rest of which was concealed 
            behind the door. There could be nothing 
            repulsive in his exterior; for the aforesaid eyes, as 
            far as he divined, expressed an increasing curiosity; 
            and the face, after a sufficient stare, gradually 
            elongating itself from its concealment, displayed 
            the pretty features of <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">the soubrette</rs>. This 
            <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">young beauty</rs> had not failed to take notice of <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the 
            stranger</rs>'s figure and appearance the previous 
            night; and if she was pleased, or rather not displeased, 
            with them under the circumstances of 
            that time, and the calamity that attended it, there 
            was no reason why she should not indulge herself 
            with a second, a daylight perusal of them. So,
            having heard the finale of the dialogue in the 
            piazza, and her <rs ref="#joanna_guthrie_0001" type="person">young mistress</rs> being by this time 
            attired, and after having made the above-mentioned 
            observaion of the premises, she stepped fearlessly 
            out of the chamber, and shutting the door 
            behind her, beckoned with a familiar smile to the 
            stranger to follow her to the further end of the 
            piazza; where she made a halt, and turning 
            round upon him suddenly, took advantage of the 
            full glare of the daylight to examine his features 
            to her heart's content.</p>
            
            <p>We have before remarked, in mentioning the 
            picture of Schiavoni, that <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">this Mulatto</rs> was a tall, 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">77</fw>
            
            athletic, personable man. <persName ref="#michal_0001">Michal</persName> <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">the soubrette</rs>, 
            surveying him from head to foot, was speedily 
            convinced of this; and had his skin been white 
            instead of tawny, she had taken him to be a very 
            handsome <distinct>buckra</distinct>. <ecda:persGroup><distinct>Quadroon</distinct> damsels</ecda:persGroup> do not 
            look for beauty in the youth of their own colour; 
            their first ideas of admiration or love are devoted 
            to the genuine white breed, either native or imported, 
            to which they are themselves indebted, 
            as they think, for the charms of their own persons, 
            and all the favour they find in the eyes of 
            those who sigh for their affections. Therefore, 
            however natural the desire she might have to appear 
            to advantage, even before a young Mulatto-
            man, nothing was farther from her thoughts than 
            to inspire him with anything like that confidence 
            which prompted him, after he had tenderly squeezed 
            the hand unconsciously held out to him, to imprint 
            a kiss upon her lips. Nothing was more 
            unexpected, and few things had more astonished 
            her. She snatched away her hand, and tore herself 
            from his embrace as if she had been in the 
            folds of such a serpent as that which stopped 
            the march of <ecda:persGroup>the Roman army</ecda:persGroup>; and though her tongue 
            refused to express the feelings which this insult 
            had roused, her black eyes flashed with so much 
            anger and indignation, that the heart of <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the Mulatto</rs> 
            for a moment sunk within him, and he felt 
            the necessity, by looks as well as words of sup-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">78</fw>
            
            plication, to apologize for the liberty he had 
            taken. There is a natural grace in the manners 
            of persons colour (nay, even in those of <ecda:persGroup>Negroes</ecda:persGroup>;)
            so that the apology to which she listened, 
            however elegantly worded and delivered, seemed 
            only what she might have expected; but the tone 
            of voice was in no wise creole; and <persName ref="#michal_0001">Michal</persName>, as 
            she set him down in her mind for an impudent 
            fellow, concluded he had acquired his gentility 
            with his free and easy manners in other countries, 
            and in pursuit of his business, whatever it might 
            be. However, as her resentment began to abate 
            with the manifestation of his repentance, she gave 
            way to the more natural kindness of her disposition, 
            and told him with a smile, that he was no 
            <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">guest</rs> for her <rs ref="#guthrie_0001" type="person">master</rs> and <rs type="person">mistress</rs>, but must come 
            and breakfast at her house, not twenty yards from 
            the back piazza; where her <ecda:anonPers>mother</ecda:anonPers> would give 
            him plenty of coffee and roasted <ecda:flora>plantains</ecda:flora>, which 
            were now waiting his pleasure. As she spoke 
            this, she descended the piazza steps; and <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">the 
            Mulatto</rs>, convinced by her expression, and his own 
            reflections, that she was in the right, followed her 
            not unwillingly to the abode which she had 
            pointed out, where he was indulged with the seat 
            of honour, and regaled with an excellent breakfast: 
            while at the same time he feasted his eyes 
            with gazing on those, and the many other charms 
            of the pretty and amiable <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">soubrette</rs>.</p>
         </div>
         
         <pb/>
         <fw type="pageNum">79</fw>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
            <ab>The purest treasure mortal times afford, 
            Is spotless reputation;—that away, 
            Men are but gilded loom or painted clay.
            SHAKSPEARE.</ab>
            
            <p>THE mother of <persName ref="#michal_0001">Michal</persName>, <ecda:anonPers>a mulatto woman of some 
            forty years of age</ecda:anonPers>, had no sooner supplied her 
            daughter's <rs ref="#sebastian_0001" type="person">guest</rs> with all he desired, than she left
            him to attend her sick <rs type="person">mistress</rs>, who was too 
            unwell to quit her bed; she left him however with 
            her <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">daughter</rs>; and this latter took the first opportunity 
            of her mother's absence to ask by what 
            name she was to call him, and why he had not 
            given <persName ref="#guthrie_0001">Mr Guthrie</persName> an answer to his question on 
            the same subject.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Why, <rs ref="#michal_0001" type="person">my pretty mistress</rs>,</said>said he, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">did <hi rend="italics">you</hi>
            listen to all we talked of?</said> (A nod admitted the 
            fact.) <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">My name is, at least my companions called
            me, <persName ref="#sebastian_0001">Sebastian</persName> or <persName ref="#sebastian_0001">Sebastiano</persName>; but you shall call 
            me what you please; I should like that you 
            would find me a name, so it gave me a title to 
            your kind thoughts.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">No, no,</said> replied the soubrette; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">you are too 
            rude and too bold; I shall give you no name; you 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">80</fw>
            
            are as impudent as if you were a white man, and 
            an old ugly one too—for such are always the first 
            to take liberties. I have seen now and then a 
            young gentleman modest and timid, and almost 
            afraid to speak to the Mulatto and Quadroon 
            girls; but an old fellow no sooner comes into the 
            house, than he begins winking his eyes at us 
            almost before my mistress's face; and if her back 
            is turned for a moment, he has some impertinent 
            thing to say, if he has not the rudeness to lay his 
            hands on us.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Well, pretty mistress,</said> rejoined the Mulatto
            looking steadily in her face, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">there is some motive
            for their presumption, if no excuse; and you ought 
            not to grieve on such occasions, where even the 
            the insolence of white men is still a tribute of admiration, 
            in some shape or other, to the charms 
            of your face and person.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Indeed! indeed!</said> cried the Quadroon, looking 
            more and more earnestly at him. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Why, 
            Mr Sebastian, you have a fine smooth tongue, 
            and you talk indeed quite like—I know not what 
            —like the parson on a Sunday, or like Mr Roland 
            the missionary, who preaches ever day.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Does Mr Roland preach every day then?</said>
            replied Sebastian. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Where is he?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">He went to windward yesterday,</said> said the 
            soubrette, a little surprised to hear her guest 
            speak of Mr Roland as if he knew him.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">And for what purpose?</said> rejoined the other.</p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">81</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Oh, for no good!</said> said the Quadroon; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">but 
            for what he only knows himself. I am sure I 
            wish he may never come back; but how do you 
            happen to know him, Mr Sebastian? I thought 
            you came from Cuba with those ill-looking Negroes 
            that you brought here. Where did you 
            ever see Mr Roland?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Ah, Michal! Miss Michal!</said> replied the 
            Mulatto; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">I have seen him in this island, and 
            I have too much cause to know him; but tell me, 
            why does he come here every day to preach? Is 
            it your master, or your mistress, or your young 
            mistress, that encourages him?</said></p>
            
            <p><said>My master!</said> answered the girl with a smile, 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">my master! he detests him; and my mistress—
            poor mistress!—she can hardly bear the sight of 
            him; and Miss Joanna won't have him for a busband, 
            although he teazes her and poor mistress 
            every day.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">And why will not your young lady marry 
            him?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Oh!</said> said Michal, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">he is nothing—a poor
            preacher; and Miss Joanna likes somebody else 
            better—a fine young gentleman she saw in England 
            or France.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">And does Roland know this?</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Yes, yes; Mr Roland knows it, because 
            mistress told him.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">And what said he?</said></p>
            <fw>VOL. I</fw>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">82</fw>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What said he?</said> repeated the soubrette. <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">He
            said that Mr Fairfax was a villain; one who believed 
            in neither God nor devil; that he had committed 
            a murder, and that he robbed upon the 
            sea.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Indeed! indeed!</said> ejaculated the Mulatto.
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Bravo, my prince of missionaries!</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">But do not imagine that Miss Joanna believes 
            it all,</said> continued Michal.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Not all of it, I dare say.</said> replied the other.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">No, no, Mr Sebastian; she told her father—for
            I heard her—that Mr Fairfax was an honourable 
            young gentleman, and never could be guilty of 
            such crimes; but yet my master hates the name 
            of Fairfax, and told her that this very young 
            gentleman would be his bitterest enemy, and 
            laughed at all she had to say of him, and told her
            never to think about him again; for she never 
            would perhaps see him, or if she did, it would be 
            in the character of a robber, come to despoil <hi rend="italics">him</hi>
            of all he had yet to lose in this world. This is no 
            secret here,</said> continued the soubrette; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">and as 
            you know, Mr Roland, I do not mind telling you 
            everything about him; and my master, who cannot 
            bear him for preaching to the Negroes, would 
            send him away from here whenever he comes; but 
            my mistress begs he may allowed to stay; yet 
            she is so unhappy when he does come, that it 
            makes my heart almost break to see her; and 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">83</fw>
            
            there is some mystery between them that nobody 
            else knows. Now tell me, Mr Sebastian,</said>—(the 
            maid looked at him with a mingled expression of 
            archness and tenderness)—<said rend="quotes" aloud="true">what you are thinking
            about, that you do not seem to attend to me? 
            Some pretty girl you have left in Cuba? You 
            are the captain of your canoe, are you not?</said></p>
            
            <p>The Mulatto smiled, or forced a smile for her in 
            return, and assured her that the only pretty girl 
            he was thinking of was herself; and he regretted 
            his dark skin must lower him so much in her 
            eyes, that he could gain nothing in her esteem 
            by expressing the kind of feelings with which she 
            inspired him. The Quadroon smiled in earnest 
            at this parade of words, which after all seemed 
            yet in character with the manners of the speaker; 
            but it was a smile of unaffected goodnature and 
            simplicity; and she told her guest with a very 
            ingenuous air, and in a no less ingenuous tone of 
            voice, that notwithstanding his dark skin, she had 
            never before seen such a Mulatto-man as himself; 
            and she could not but wonder where he, who was so 
            young, had learned to talk so prettily, and so like 
            what she fancied of a fine gentleman. She thought 
            he must have been educated in England; perhaps 
            by Mr. W—? He shook his head.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Indeed, my pretty mistress, I was educated 
            in England, and have been in France; and what 
            is more, I have been acquainted with the gentle-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">84</fw>
            
            man you speak of. Mr Fairfax is not unknown to 
            me; I have attended, I may say served him.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Have you, really?</said> demanded the soubrette.
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Why did not you tell me so before? How happy 
            will Miss Joanna be to hear something of him! 
            But is he what Mr Roland calls him? He is not 
            a buccaneer, is he? nor one who will not believe 
            in God? I know he is a handsome young man, 
            and brave, and rich; and honourable. Well! well! 
            one day he must marry my young mistress, and 
            then perhaps, Mr Sebastian, I may see you again 
            sometimes.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">Ah Michal!</said> replied he; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">the sight of your 
            pretty face will always cheer my heart; I could 
            love you for having been always near the object 
            which Mr Fairfax so much prizes.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">You could love me, Mr Sebastian?</said>interrupted 
            the Quadroon; <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">you could love me! If 
            we were in England perhaps. Who knows what 
            may be our fate one of these days, by and bye? 
            Indeed you may deserve a more honourable love 
            than mine; you are a free man, and I am a 
            slave.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes" aloud="true">You shall be free, Michal, if you will be faithful.</said></p>
            
            <p>Michal shook her head, <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">What would my 
            mistress say, and my mother?</said> she added laughing. 
            <said rend="quotes" aloud="true">No, no; do not talk about love to me; 
            come and tell Miss Joanna about Mr Fairfax, or 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">85</fw>
            
            tell me something for her, if you please; for Mr 
            Guthrie will be too much on his guard, or too 
            fanciful, to give you an opportunity of speaking 
            with her alone; and we shall have Mr Roland 
            coming here again by and bye. Yonder is his house, 
            by the coco-nut trees, half way down to the bay. 
            I have seen him sometimes for an hour together 
            spying into the piazza at my master's with his 
            glass.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Spying here also I should think sometimes—
            does he not, Michal? <hi rend="italics">I</hi> should, I fear, if I dwelt 
            yonder; or what would you think of me if I did 
            not? At least since you allow me to fancy there 
            may be something in my brown face that is not 
            altogether horrible to you. You would find me, 
            Michal—you <hi rend="italics">will</hi> find me, I hope, a faithful—</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">A faithful what? A faithful how much, 
            Mr. Sailor? By the virtue of my conscience, and 
            Miss Michal's too, making love to the Quadroon!
            Why, though naughty flirt! It was for this that 
            you took away Mr What's-his-name to breakfast 
            with you. Why did you not,</said> continued 
            Mr Guthrie, addressing himself to the Mulatto, 
            <said rend="quotes">why did you not stay to breakfast with me, where 
            I had left you?</said></p>
            
            <p>The Mulatto bowed, and expressed his sense of 
            the honour his host had intended him; adding, 
            <said rend="quotes">that he could not consider himself entitled to it; 
            that he knew, or thought he knew, his proper place,
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">86</fw>
            
            which was here, at Miss Michal's invitation; not 
            that he had presumed to speak to her in any 
            terms of gallantry.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Why, what was it then,</said> said the white gentleman, 
            <said rend="quotes">that I heard? Mister—Mister—</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Sebastian is  his name,</said> interrupted Michal.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">Mister Sebastian! a fine Spanish title or designation 
            indeed! Mr Sebastian,</said> continued he, 
            <said rend="quotes">you are a very extraordinary personage, to say 
            the least of you: did you acquire that nomenclature 
            in Cuba? Your language and manners have 
            nothing in common with those of your associates, 
            and little in common with those of persons of 
            your colour in general. I can with difficulty persuade 
            myself that I have understood aright all 
            you have told me yourself.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">There will be little cause for suspicion at my 
            language or manners,</said> replied the Mulatto, 
            <said rend="quotes">when you are informed, that although I have a 
            brown complexion, I have spent the chief part of 
            my life in Europe—in England, in France, in 
            Italy, and in other countries; where I have had 
            an opportunity of improving myself, by which I 
            might have profited to a much greater extent than 
            my appearance indicates.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">He has been with Mr Fairfax,</said> said the pretty 
            Quadroon, interposing.</p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">With Fairfax!</said> echoed Mr Guthrie, opening 
            his eyes to their widest; <said rend="quotes">with Fairfax! What 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">87</fw>
            
            do I hear?</said> A crowd of ideas seemed to rush 
            into his mind, as far at least as the incarcerated 
            muscles of his face allowed his auditors to divine 
            from the little motion of which it was capable. 
            <said rend="quotes">You the companion of Mr Fairfax? What 
            could have brought you here? By heaven, you 
            are spies! No fortune can have led you to this 
            spot, it must have been design, a scheme concerted, 
            premeditation; yet what had you to gain? 
            Does my daughter know that this man comes 
            from Mr. Fairfax? Michal speak.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">How can she know?</said> replied the maid. <said rend="quotes">She
            has not seen him; and it is not five minutes since 
            I learned it myself.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">What do you know of him?</said> said Mr Guthrie, 
            again addressing the Mulatto. <said rend="quotes">Describe me his 
            person—but stay; come with me to the house: 
            I wish even that vermin Roland was here. Let 
            Miss Guthrie see you, and hear from you what 
            sort of a being is this Fairfax who is to chase us 
            from our inheritance, at least from a great part of 
            it, as he threatens, and yet has the assurance (or has 
            had) to think of aspiring to her affections. If we 
            may believe Roland (which heaven forbid!) Mr 
            Fairfax is a very singular person, and one who does 
            not stick at trifles: indeed this very argument is 
            proof of it; and Roland says he makes nothing of 
            cutting throats either by land or water.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">How should Mr Roland know this?</said> ob-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">88</fw>
            
            served the Mulatto. <said rend="quotes">Has he witnessed any of 
            his exploits? But let me tell you, Mr Guthrie, 
            once for all, <hi rend="italics">I</hi> am no spy at least, and have no 
            design against your peace or happiness.</said></p>
            
            <p><said rend="quotes">No, I'll be sworn!</said> replied the white man. 
            <said rend="quotes">I can trust your features, and believe you are 
            nought but what you appear. Nay, never flinch, 
            man: Roland has denounced your Mr Fairfax as 
            a pirate, and waits his coming to the island to 
            cause his arrest. He says he has half a dozen 
            Negroes to prove what he asserts, if their evidence 
            were to be admitted. But come: Michal, go 
            call Joanna. Sebastian, or whatever may be 
            your name, I shall forget neither the services you 
            have rendered me, nor what the laws of hospitality 
            demand of me in your behalf. I ask as a 
            favour only, that you return with me to the house, 
            and let my daughter question you, if she has any 
            such desire, about your friend, or master, or companion, 
            or whatever else he may be, Mr Oliver 
            Fairfax.</said></p>
         </div>
               
         
         
      </body>
      
  </text>
</TEI>
