<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <front>
        <titleBlock>
           <docTitle>
              <titlePart>HAMEL.</titlePart>
           </docTitle>
           
        </titleBlock>
     </front>
     
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
            <epigraph> Yet hold! for oh! this prologue lets me in
            To a most fatal tragedy to come. Richard III.</epigraph>
            
            <p>At the close of a sultry day in the month of
            October, in the year one thousand eight hundred 
            and twenty-two; or rather at the moment when 
            the sun (whose fiery ardour had not been moderated
            in any part of his course by the least zephyr
            of the sea breeze) had just sunk behind the emerald
            summits of the Blue Mountain, and relieved 
            from his scorching rays those Europeans who
            toil on the northern shores of Jamaica; a person
            who (from some circumstances about to be explained)
            appeared to be a stranger, was seen
            riding along hte western bank fo the Rio Grande,
            that clear and beautiful stream which hurrying
            
            VOL I.
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pagNum">2</fw> <head>HAMEL.</head> 
               <!-- double check how to do headers -->
            down from the wildernesses of the island, carries
            the torrents of its highest mountains to the
            Atlantic. The stranger seemed to be seeking a 
            ford, and strove from time to time to prevail on 
            a sulky-looking Spanish horse, which bore him
            without manifesting any satisfaction at his burthen, 
            to venture through the deep and rapid 
            current; but it was evident that the rider and his 
            steed were of two minds on the point, and that
            the pertinacity of the latter was more than a match
            for the hesitating and undecided anxiety of the 
            former; whose timidity, arising from inexperience
            of the river, induced him not to press his beast
            into the flood against that instinct to which he
            preferred to trust his fortune on the present
            occasion.</p>
      
            <p>The rider was accoutred in a black coat, cut
            straight, or it might be of a dingy grey, with
            black cloth buttons, and a waistcoat of the same.
            His trowsers were of brown holland, tucked into 
            a huge pair of spatterdashes, buttoned above his
            knee, as a defence against the bites of musquitos.
            He wore a large brimmed hat, slouched by
            many a tropical shower, and rendered rusty by
            constant exposure to the tropical sun, although
            at present he carried an umbrella secured in the 
            straps of a portmanteau mounted behind him on
            his horse's crupper; and his great-coat, of the 
            same sombre hue as his other vestments, was fast-
            <pb/>
            
            <head>HAMEL</head> <fw type="pagNum">3</fw>
            ended upon his saddle bow. He was attended by a 
            bare-legged negro boy on foot, dressed in an Osnaburgh
            frock and drawers, which, with a glzed hat
            on his head, formed the whole of his costume.
            The boy hung on sometimes to his master's stirrup, 
            that he might keep pace with the horse; and 
            sometimes, falling into the rear, brought himself
            up by grasping the animal's long tail; a liberty
            the beast admitted with an occasional affectation
            of elevating his croupe and lowering his ears, - 
            intimations that he had a right to kick (though
            he did not at present) as well understood by
            young Cuffy as expressed by the horse.</p>
            
            <p>This youngster's features scarcely harmonized 
            with those of his very demure and melancholy looking
            master, whose pale and cadaverous countenance 
            indicated something more than bodily 
            mortification and fatigue. His eyes, black and
            penetrating, were shadowed by brows that had 
            once been dark as the skin of his follower, but
            now, with the locks that strayed in right lines
            from under his huge castor, exhibited the mingled 
            hues of black and grey; his nose was sharp and 
            aquiline; and his mouth, though rather of the 
            largest, by no means badly formed, was furnished 
            with a set of short but regular teeth, as white as
            those of Cuffy, whose happy physiognomy bespoke
            the innocence and kindness of his heart,
            and relieved that of the spectator from the sym-
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pagNum">4</fw> <head>HAMEL.</head>
            
            pathy of sadness inspired by the looks of the 
            white-faced traveller. Yet the gloom on the 
            cheek of this last was not attributable perhaps to 
            any dignified grief or sentimentality of disposition
            -at least his features did not augur any such 
            feeling; nor to age, for he was by some years
            short of forty. Anxiety of mind, as well as fatigue
            of body, natural irritability, and pecuniary cares,
            will impress even on a more juvenile countenance
            those lines which, visible there only, are channelled 
            by time and memory on the invisible and wasted
            heart. Whether this were the case in the present
            instance, will be seen in the course of our narrative.</p>
            
            <p>The stranger and his footman continued their
            route for some distance beside the river, halting
            again and again to compare notes as to teh fordability
            of several spots, where the latter declared
            he could see the track of mules and horses,
            which he thought had crossed from the other
            side; but his master imagined them to be only
            indications of the cattle having been there to 
            drink or cool themselves, and referred the point 
            invariably to his horse, who, however anxious to
            drink or roll in the stream, always manifested the 
            same unwillingness to traverse it. The evening
            was closing in rapidly, and the traveller, impatient 
            at last of his beast's fears or obstinacy, had
            directed his valet to strip and try a ford, which,
            <pb/>
            
            <head>HAMEL.</head> <fw type="pagNum">5</fw>
            
            as he could distinguish by marks on the opposite
            side, was certainly used at times; when
            Cuffy who was already half across the river, 
            called to his master that he could see some 
            Negroes coming down the hills from the interior
            towards a row of stones or rocks placed a little 
            farther up the winding current, for the convenience 
            of foot passengers, which had been hidden
            from their view by the trees growing on its banks.</p>
            
            <p>To this rudest of rude bridges the traveller 
            and his boy advanced without delay, being anxious
            no doubt to leave the river behind them,
            and hurry to their quarters, yet at some miles 
            distance beyond it, if possible before nightfall; 
            and they had just gained the bridge in question, 
            when they were saluted by the Negroes, who 
            were coming down from their provision grounds 
            with yams, cocos, and various fruits for the 
            next day's market on their heads. There was an 
            excellent ford jsut above the stepping stones, 
            which the cantancrous horse was compelled to 
            pass, Cuffy still leading the way; and the Negroes 
            furnished them with abundant directions to the 
            settlement for which the traveller inquired, though
            accompanied with a piece of intelligence not 
            altogether so welcome, as they intimated a report 
            that the said settlement had been deserted since 
            the death of its proprietor, whose wido had 
            gone down to Port Antonio, while his slaves,
            
            <fw type="pagNum">6</fw> <head>HAMEL.</head>
            
            some eighteen or twenty, had run away into the 
            woods.</p>
         </div>
      
      </body>
      
  </text>
</TEI>
