<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/ecda.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <front>
        <titleBlock>
           <docTitle>
              <titlePart>HAMEL.</titlePart>
           </docTitle>
           
        </titleBlock>
     </front>
     
      <body>
         <head>HAMEL.</head>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb/>
            <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
            <ab type="epigraph"><lg><l>Yet hold! for oh! this prologue lets me in</l>
            <l>To a most fatal tragedy to come.</l></lg> <persName>Richard III</persName>.</ab>
            
            <p>At the close of a sultry day in the month of
            October, in the year one thousand eight hundred 
            and twenty-two; or rather at the moment when 
            the sun (whose fiery ardour had not been moderated
            in any part of his course by the least zephyr
            of the sea breeze) had just sunk behind the emerald
            summits of the Blue Mountain, and relieved 
            from his scorching rays those Europeans who
            toil on the northern shores of Jamaica; a person
            who (from some circumstances about to be explained)
            appeared to be a stranger, was seen
            riding along the western bank of the Rio Grande,
            that clear and beautiful stream which hurrying
            
            <fw>VOL I.</fw>
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">2</fw>
            down from the wildernesses of the island, carries
            the torrents of its highest mountains to the
            Atlantic. The stranger seemed to be seeking a 
            ford, and strove from time to time to prevail on 
            a sulky-looking Spanish horse, which bore him
            without manifesting any satisfaction at his burthen, 
            to venture through the deep and rapid 
            current; but it was evident that the rider and his 
            steed were of two minds on the point, and that
            the pertinacity of the latter was more than a match
            for the hesitating and undecided anxiety of the 
            former; whose timidity, arising from inexperience
            of the river, induced him not to press his beast
            into the flood against that instinct to which he
            preferred to trust his fortune on the present
            occasion.</p>
      
            <p>The rider was accoutred in a black coat, cut
            straight, or it might be of a dingy grey, with
            black cloth buttons, and a waistcoat of the same.
            His trowsers were of brown holland, tucked into 
            a huge pair of spatterdashes, buttoned above his
            knee, as a defence against the bites of musquitos.
            He wore a large brimmed hat, slouched by
            many a tropical shower, and rendered rusty by
            constant exposure to the tropical sun, although
            at present he carried an umbrella secured in the 
            straps of a portmanteau mounted behind him on
            his horse's crupper; and his great-coat, of the 
            same sombre hue as his other vestments, was fast-
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">3</fw>
            ended upon his saddle bow. He was attended by a 
            bare-legged negro boy on foot, dressed in an Osnaburgh
            frock and drawers, which, with a glazed hat
            on his head, formed the whole of his costume.
            The boy hung on sometimes to his master's stirrup, 
            that he might keep pace with the horse; and 
            sometimes, falling into the rear, brought himself
            up by grasping the animal's long tail; a liberty
            the beast admitted with an occasional affectation
            of elevating his croupe and lowering his ears, - 
            intimations that he had a right to kick (though
            he did not at present) as well understood by
            young Cuffy as expressed by the horse.</p>
            
            <p>This youngster's features scarcely harmonized 
            with those of his very demure and melancholy looking
            master, whose pale and cadaverous countenance 
            indicated something more than bodily 
            mortification and fatigue. His eyes, black and
            penetrating, were shadowed by brows that had 
            once been dark as the skin of his follower, but
            now, with the locks that strayed in right lines
            from under his huge castor, exhibited the mingled 
            hues of black and grey; his nose was sharp and 
            aquiline; and his mouth, though rather of the 
            largest, by no means badly formed, was furnished 
            with a set of short but regular teeth, as white as
            those of Cuffy, whose happy physiognomy bespoke
            the innocence and kindness of his heart,
            and relieved that of the spectator from the sym-
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">4</fw> 
            
            pathy of sadness inspired by the looks of the 
            white-faced traveller. Yet the gloom on the 
            cheek of this last was not attributable perhaps to 
            any dignified grief or sentimentality of disposition
            -at least his features did not augur any such 
            feeling; nor to age, for he was by some years
            short of forty. Anxiety of mind, as well as fatigue
            of body, natural irritability, and pecuniary cares,
            will impress even on a more juvenile countenance
            those lines which, visible there only, are channelled 
            by time and memory on the invisible and wasted
            heart. Whether this were the case in the present
            instance, will be seen in the course of our narrative.</p>
            
            <p>The stranger and his footman continued their
            route for some distance beside the river, halting
            again and again to compare notes as to the fordability
            of several spots, where the latter declared
            he could see the track of mules and horses,
            which he thought had crossed from the other
            side; but his master imagined them to be only
            indications of the cattle having been there to 
            drink or cool themselves, and referred the point 
            invariably to his horse, who, however anxious to
            drink or roll in the stream, always manifested the 
            same unwillingness to traverse it. The evening
            was closing in rapidly, and the traveller, impatient 
            at last of his beast's fears or obstinacy, had
            directed his valet to strip and try a ford, which,
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">5</fw>
            
            as he could distinguish by marks on the opposite
            side, was certainly used at times; when
            Cuffy who was already half across the river, 
            called to his master that he could see some 
            Negroes coming down the hills from the interior
            towards a row of stones or rocks placed a little 
            farther up the winding current, for the convenience 
            of foot passengers, which had been hidden
            from their view by the trees growing on its banks.</p>
            
            <p>To this rudest of rude bridges the traveller 
            and his boy advanced without delay, being anxious
            no doubt to leave the river behind them,
            and hurry to their quarters, yet at some miles 
            distance beyond it, if possible before nightfall; 
            and they had just gained the bridge in question, 
            when they were saluted by the Negroes, who 
            were coming down from their provision grounds 
            with yams, cocos, and various fruits for the 
            next day's market on their heads. There was an 
            excellent ford just above the stepping stones, 
            which the cantancrous horse was compelled to 
            pass, Cuffy still leading the way; and the Negroes 
            furnished them with abundant directions to the 
            settlement for which the traveller inquired, though
            accompanied with a piece of intelligence not 
            altogether so welcome, as they intimated a report 
            that the said settlement had been deserted since 
            the death of its proprietor, whose widow had 
            gone down to Port Antonio, while his slaves,
            
            <fw type="pageNum">6</fw> 
            
            some eighteen or twenty, had run away into the 
            woods.</p>
            
            <p>Notwithstanding this information, the traveller's 
            countenance brightened very visibly at sight
            of some young negro girls of the party, to each 
            of whom he had something agreeable to say - some
            compliment to their persons, attended with a 
            cavalier and rather equivocal expression of his 
            eyes, which raised a smile on the lips of the 
            sable beauties, and elicited some rather diverting 
            remarks from them on the discrepancy between 
            his language and his looks. One of them, who 
            said she was handmaid to her mistress, observed 
            that he smelt sweet like her lady's washball; and 
            most of them remarked on the perfumed state of 
            his person, to which it must be avowed he was not 
            inattentive: and whether they were cosmetics, or 
            preparations for the hair, or essences to gratify 
            his own olfactory nerves, which he breathed, he 
            was, in fact, "perfumed like a milliner."</p>
            
            <p>Yet in the midst of these odours he asked the 
            young girls whether they were married; and if 
            married, whether the ceremony had been performed 
            by a priest or a missionary, or whether 
            they were married after the African fashion. He
            enquired too about their soul's grace, their work, 
            profits, punishments: - whether they expected to 
            be free, and how many Mulatto and Quadroon 
            girls there were on their master's estate, and if 
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">7</fw>
            
            his daughter were handsome; and then relapsed 
            into some rather spiritual advice, mingled with a 
            few allusions to the worm which dieth not, and 
            the fire which is not quenched.</p>
            
            <p>The girls began to think him an unaccountable 
            buckra, and rather affected with insanity; more 
            especially as he persisted in his intention of proceeding 
            to the settlement of which they had given 
            him such an unfavourable account, and refused 
            their assurance, on the part of their master or the 
            overseer, of good quarters and hospitable entertainment 
            for the night. Cuffy would fain have 
            seconded their arguments, but his master silenced 
            him with a gloomy frown; and after a few more 
            desultory observations to the women, with some 
            of whom he chose to shake hands, the head of 
            the Spanish steed was turned toward the mountains; 
            and Cuffy again seizing its tail, master and 
            man resumed their course. The short twilight 
            expired, and the shadows of night rendered still 
            more sombre the forlorn and unfrequented path 
            along which they journeyed.</p>
            <pb/>
            </div>
            <!-- There are pages missing in the PDF -->
            
            <div type="chapter"> <!-- Chapter 2 starts on the missing pages -->
            <fw type="pageNum">10</fw>
            
            <p>he had left, and lingered onwards most reluctantly, 
            in spite of sundry kicks bestowed on his 
            ribs by his fractious master, whose impatience 
            increased with the storm which already penetrated 
            through his garments. A tropical wetting is but 
            too often precursor and cause of those baleful 
            fevers which are almost the only curse upon the 
            otherwise blissful climate of the Antilles, - blissful 
            in the idea of the inhabitants; and our traveller, 
            already initiated in the miseries of this scourge, 
            was but too full of apprehensions and forebodings, 
            as he felt the tempest invade him to the skin.</p>
            
            <p>The thoughts of a sick bed, or sickness without 
            a bed, without medicine, in an abandoned 
            dwelling in the midst of the jungle, as it was 
            represented to him, crowded fast on his perturbed 
            imagination, which now first reproached him for 
            the expedition he had undertaken, although the 
            feeling was purely selfish: however, it was of short 
            duration; the uproar of the elements increased 
            so rapidly and violently, that all apprehensions 
            for the past or the future quickly yielded to more 
            immediate fears for his present personal safety. 
            They had been for some time ascending, and had 
            now gained the summit of a steep hill, whence 
            the road began to descend as abruptly into another 
            dingle, through which they could discover, by the 
            occasional flashes of lightning, a river of more 
            importance than the many petty streams they 
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">11</fw>
            
            had already crossed. This was indeed the Rio 
            Grande again, but little inferior in magnitude to 
            the volume of water it had presented to them 
            some miles below; and how were they to pass it? 
            or how indeed were they to reach it? The road, 
            scarcely three feet wide, wound along the side of a 
            precipice, against which the wind raged with such 
            fury, and the rain beat so spitefully, that the horse 
            for a long time refused to face either of them, and 
            was at last driven down into the valley by master 
            and man on foot, urging him with sticks, and 
            preventing him from turning round in the narrow 
            path, so slippery and precipitous that he slid 
            down the last portion of it on his hind quarters, 
            and rolled over and over into the narrow plain 
            below, bursting his girths and scattering abroad 
            his harness and the portmanteau, umbrella, and 
            great coat. These were, however, readjusted 
            with a promptitude inspired by the occasion, and 
            with a resolution which was little else than the 
            effect of despair; the river was passed in comparative 
            safety; Cuffy, who led the horse, only 
            stumbling occasionally over the loose rocks which 
            strewed its channel. But scarcely had they 
            reached the terra firma on the other side, when 
            the terrified boy cried out that the earth shook 
            beneath him, and ran up the path which they had 
            found, as if he expected the river to rise and 
            arrest him, or hurry him with its waters down its 
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">12</fw> 
               
            impetuous current. The horse, no less alarmed, 
            or afraid of losing his negro guide and friend, 
            hastened after him. Another eminence was gained, 
            from whence a track of fire was driving apparently at a 
            great distance before the wind. "Earthquakes 
            are not uncommon," thought the traveller; "but 
            fire - this must be produced by human means." 
            Cuffy thought otherwise; more especially when 
            he descried other fires in different directions, and 
            one or two now and then flashing into view at no 
            very great apparent distance. The earth shook 
            again; and the wind, as if it had still reserved 
            some of its power for an effort of desperation, 
            burst on them with such exasperated fury, that 
            it seemed impossible to make farther progress 
            against it. Cuffy clung to the boughs and the 
            rocks beside him; and his master being fain to 
            follow his example, the steed, with equipage, 
            was left to the mercy of the elements, from 
            which they saw him gradually recede to the 
            distance of fifty or sixty yards, like a ship 
            driving at her anchors and going bodily to leeward, 
            until he was lost in the darkness. Cuffy, 
            true to his trust, abandoned his hold to keep 
            sight of his master's baggage; while his master, 
            encumbered with his spatterdashes, and fearful of 
            following the fate of his Bucephalus, encouraged 
            his valet to stand by the horse, and took a firmer
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">13</fw>
            
            grasp of the rocks from which he sought protecion. 
            Often and often was his voice lost in the 
            tumult of the storm, as he shouted to his boy for 
            some assurance of his safety. No answer reached 
            his ears - no sound but that of the elements 
            raging as if to produce a second chaos, thunder 
            and wind, the roaring of the augmented waterfalls, 
            the rumbling of the rocks which they loosed 
            from their beds, the creaking and crashing of 
            falling trees. It was in vain that the lightning at 
            every other instant illuminated the scene with its 
            partial flashes, now here, now there: it gleamed 
            only on mountains uncultivated and uninhabited, 
            (except perhaps by a few outlawed runaways who 
            lived by a predatory warfare on the wild hogs and 
            pigeons of the desart,) on naked precipices and 
            foaming torrents, or on the giant trees of the forest 
            quivering beneath the blast of the hurricane. Then 
            came down the rain, not as in the temperate zone 
            even in its most weeping seasons, when the spectator 
            would fain imagine a second deluge; but 
            torrents, sheets of water, seemed to rush from the 
            clouds, and threaten the annihilation of all life 
            beneath the sky. The forlorn and dispirited traveller, 
            still clinging to the rocks which yielded 
            him a partial and precarious kind of security, had 
            groped his way along them to a chink, in whose 
            recesses he flattered himself with an idea of 
            weathering the storm till daylight, drenched - 
            
               
            <pb/> 
            <fw type="pageNum">14</fw> 
            
            nay, almost drowned - as he was by this time; but 
            even here the elementary war pursued him; a 
            stream of water began to ripple down the chink, 
            soon swelling to a torrent, augmented by another 
            which found its way through the chasms of the 
            precipice as if it had burst from some subterranean 
            reservoir. The traveller's situation became 
            insupportable; he must remove or perish; yet 
            not daring to quit the crags to which he clung, 
            and availing himself of the partial lee they afforded, 
            he essayed to clamber up the face of the precipice, 
            and with much difficulty and struggling 
            reached the edge of the chink whence the torrent 
            fell. Here he found himself comparatively safe in 
            a long narrow passage or natural alley, in which 
            he was at least secured from the wind by the 
            high and inaccessible rocks on either side of it. 
            Yet as the torrent still flowed over his feet and half 
            way up his legs, he waded onwards to find a spot 
            of higher ground, or an insulated piece of rock 
            that might elevate him above the stream, and 
            with this hope pursued the course of it for above 
            a hundred yards, till he came to a chasm that 
            opened on it from another mass of rocks, between 
            which and his present station another brawling 
            cataract, at depth of fifty feet beneath him, 
            found its way towards the streams which united 
            in the Rio Grande below. A fallen tree formed a 
            bridge across this fissure, on the opposite side of 
            
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">15</fw>
            
            which the mouth of a cave might be distinguished 
            by a glare of the lightning, sufficient in appearance 
            to ensure our traveller shelter and safety for 
            the night - shelter from the rain, and security from 
            the wind. It was a most perilous undertaking to 
            pass this bridge; but prompted by hope, and urged 
            by misery and fear, he ventured on its uncertain 
            surface, keeping his balance by means of a branch 
            that hung from the opposite side, which, with 
            much ado, he reached at last without accident. 
            Here he found what appeared to him steps cut by 
            human art for some height in the face of the rock: 
            he ascended them, and walked into the cave.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="chapter">
            <fw type="pageNum">16</fw>
            <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
            <ab type="epigraph">Let me wipe off this honorable dew.
            SHAKESPEARE.</ab>
            
            <p>As soon as the traveller found himself safe from 
            the storm, he sat down on the floor of the cave, 
            and burst into a flood of tears; and something like 
            an acknowledgment of heaven's mercy passed 
            his lips. His next thought was for his boy and 
            his equipage, the horse and the portmanteau; 
            nor was he long in adverting to the deplorable 
            condition in which he yet found himself, drenched 
            with rain, and exhausted with the fatigue of having 
            borne up against the passion of the hurricane. 
            To sit still might be fatal to him in this state, and 
            he had even thoughts of stripping off his wet garments, 
            and parading the cave, as far as he could 
            see into it, till daylight; but was checked by the 
            idea which he could not dismiss of stepping on 
            scorpions or centipedes, or becoming an easier 
            prey to the musquitos which like himself had 
            here found a refuge from the weather. While he 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">17</fw>
            
            yet mused on the manner in which he was to pass 
            the hours till morning, his olfactory nerves became 
            sensible of a smell of fire, - the smoke of burning 
            wood, which evidently came from the interior of 
            the cave; and hastily concluding it to be owing to 
            one of the wandering fires he had seen abroad, he 
            explored his way through the cavern towards the 
            smell, expecting to find an outlet on the other 
            side of the mountain, through which he calculated 
            the smoke was driven perhaps from a distance. 
            The odour and its vapour increased as he proceeded; 
            and he had not made a very long or very painful 
            march, before he began to perceive a glimmering 
            of light, by which he attained an inner apartment 
            as it were of a cave, filled it is true with smoke, 
            but in some measure illuminated by the fire from 
            which it exhaled; not one of the wandering fires 
            of the wilderness, but a fire of burning brands laid 
            on the floor of the apartment too evidently by 
            human hands. "This," thought he, "is at least the 
            abode of man: runaway slave, Maroon, or robber, 
            I will yet claim his hospitality; my situation 
            cannot be worse, and what have I to lose? 
            But where is the tenant of the dwelling? Here 
            are plantains too, not long roasted, and rum; and 
            what are these?" he added, taking up some garments 
            that lay on the floor, a contoo, and an 
            instrument of music, a bonjaw. "Let us at least 
            summon the master of the cave. What ho! hilloh!"
            
            <fw>VOL I.</fw>
            <pb/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum">18</fw>
            
            The voice died away unheeded, and the traveller 
            listened to its echoes until he felt almost afraid 
            and ashamed to disturb the silence again. Yet 
            he mustered courage to exert his voice a second 
            and a third time, though as at first ineffectually. 
            Sufficiently removed from the storm without, to 
            hear no more of it than an occasional murmur 
            which stole along the vault he had penetrated, 
            too faint to cause him any farther concern, his 
            own voice was reverberated on his ears with a
            force from which he shrank within himself, so 
            painful was it to his oppressed and agitated 
            nerves. He called no more; but conforming himself 
            with a philosophical moderation to the hour 
            and the scene in which he found himself, he trimmed 
            the fire; took off his wet clothes, which he 
            wrung and disposed around it; attired himself in 
            the contoo of his invisible host; and wrapping his 
            feet in a blanket which lay beside it, helped himself
            from the calabash of rum, and put some of the 
            plantains on the fire again to warm. He had 
            seated himself on a bundle of sticks, and as he 
            took a second taste of the rum calabash, surveyed 
            at his leisure, by the cheerful blaze he had made, 
            the extent and furniture of his apartment.</p>
            
            <p>It was a lofty cavern hewn by the hand of nature 
            in the otherwise solid lime-stone rock, from 
            the roof of which hung many stalactites, whose 
            points were blackened by the smoke from the fire 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">19</fw>
            
            beneath. Besides the opening by which the traveller 
            had entered, there were four other apertures, 
            each leading, as it seemed from the glimpse 
            he had taken of them, to the other recesses in the 
            rock, and so much resembling each other that he 
            could not now distinctly ascertain that which had 
            admitted him. Alarmed for a moment as this discovery, 
            he arose from his seat, and taking a firebrand 
            from the blazing pile, would fain have explored 
            these vomitories, into each of which he 
            walked a few paces, without however deriving the 
            information he required, or gaining any but a conviction 
            that they extended farther than he was 
            disposed at present to penetrate. He next surveyed 
            the precincts of the cave itself, and its rather 
            curious contents. In a recess stood a couple of 
            spears, one solely of hard wood, whose point was 
            rendered still harder by fire; the other was shod 
            with iron and rusted apparently with blood; a 
            bamboo rod, ten feet in length and about an inch 
            in thickness, leaned against the rock beside them, 
            carved or tattoed from end to end. In another 
            angle of the vault was a calabash filled with various 
            sorts of hair, among which it was easy to discriminate 
            that of white men, horses, and dogs. 
            These were huddled together, and crowded with 
            feathers of various birds, especially those of 
            domestic poultry and wild parrots, with one or 
            two of the spoils of a macaw. A human skull 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">20</fw>
            
            was placed beside this calabash, from which the 
            teeth were missing; but on turning it up, the traveller 
            found them with a quantity of broken glass 
            crammed into the cerebellum, and covered up with 
            a wad of silk cotton, to prevent them from falling 
            out. There were several other skulls in a second 
            recess, some perfect, some which had been broken 
            apparently with a sharp pointed instrument, and 
            many of them serving as calabashes or boxes to 
            hold the strange property of the master of the 
            cave; one was a receptacle for gunpowder, which 
            the inquisitive traveller narrowly escaped inflaming; 
            a second contained bullets and shot of various 
            sizes, mixed with old nails and pieces of rag; 
            and from a third he saw with no little horror a 
            black snake uncoil itself the moment he touched 
            it. There were three muskets, all old and out of 
            order; a pistol and two cutlasses, disposed on different 
            ledges of the rock; a large conch-shell 
            fitted with a belt of mahoe bark, to be worn over 
            the shoulder, hung from a projection, with several 
            other pieces of rope made of similar materials, to 
            which were attached rings of wood and hollowed 
            stones, perhaps intended for amulets or charms. 
            A lamp of clay at last arrested his attention; it 
            had carved on it some rude figures and was filled 
            with oil of the Palma Christi, having a wick 
            formed of the fibres of the plantain stalk. This 
            the intruder took the liberty of illuming, to assist 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">21</fw>
            
            him more conveniently than did his flickering 
            firebrand in the farther search he seemed disposed 
            to prosecute. By the help of this he espied a 
            pair of shoepatters, a sort of coarse sandal, and a 
            red cloak resembling the South-American poncho. 
            Some salted fish was suspended from a part of the 
            roof, with a large calabash of sugar, and another of 
            coarse salt; and an earthen jar contained no 
            small store of salted pork. There were several 
            pieces of jerked hog hanging from a stick 
            placed across this recess, to one of which he 
            helped himself without ceremony; and thinking 
            he had made sufficient search for the present, 
            returned to the fire, on which he heaped fresh fuel, 
            raking forward the embers to cook his meat: 
            placed his lamp on a shelf of the rock full in his 
            view; and taking a gombah for his stool, sat down 
            very deliberately to his supper. He ate with no 
            sparing appetite; and the rum which he quaffed 
            as his thirst prompted him, refreshed his body 
            and composed his mind so happily and so gradually, 
            that what with that and his fatigue, the 
            solace of the fire and the fumes of his digestion, 
            he at last slipt gently from his gombah, which 
            now served him for a pillow, rolled himself up in 
            his blanket, and fell into a profound sleep.</p>
         </div>
         
         
         <pb/>
         <div type="chapter">
             <fw type="pageNum">22</fw>
             <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
            <ab>
               <hi rend="italics">Pye.</hi>  And you a figure-caster, a conjurer!
               <hi rend="italics">Skir.</hi> A conjurer?
               <hi rend="italics">Pye.</hi>  Let me alone, I'll instruct you, and teach you to
               deceive all eyes but the devil's.
               The Puritan
            </ab>
             <p>DEEP and leaden as were the slumbers of our 
             traveller, his mind was not wholly relieved from 
             the cares of this world, for which, sleeping or 
             waking, nature seems by some perversion from 
             her original and benevolent purpose to have 
             formed this our enslaved, if not incarcerated, 
             sensorium: not but that there are dreams of all 
             denominations - visions of bliss, as well as of 
             sorrow; but the first are still dependent on terrestrial 
             objects, human interests and passions, as 
             well as the latter; and where is the mind that 
             would not, at many periods of even a short life, 
             have consented to wipe away from its tablets the 
             very memory of those, to escape the painful rememberances 
             of these? The brains of our weather-
             beaten sleeper were not long idle. He fancied
             
             <pb/>
             <fw type="pageNum">23</fw>
             
             himself still contending with the elements, and 
             striving in vain to save his boy Cuffy from the 
             storm, or keep his own seat on his Spanish horse, 
             which succeeded in kicking his master into a 
             river, whose waves were waves of fire. Then 
             again he fancied himself sauntering by moonlight on 
             the banks of another, a clear and crystal stream, 
             whence he descried at a distance the buildings of 
             a sugar estate on fire. He ran towards it. From 
             the great house (as the principal dwelling is 
             called) a female figure, young and beautiful, 
             looked out, imploring help. The passion of the 
             sleeper was awakended; he clambered into the 
             piazza, reconducted the lady to her chamber, assured 
             her of her safety, and in spite of her distress, 
             presumed to talk to her of his love; nay, 
             insensible to all but his own selfish feelings, attempted 
             to pollute her with his caresses. She 
             died in his arms, as he thought, curseing him for 
             his cruelty; and as he shrunk with horror from 
             her inanimate and ghastly corpse, he saw a fiend 
             arise from her bed, fix on him its eyes glaring 
             with a malignant fury, by a threatening action 
             command him to silence, and trace on 
             his forehead, in burning characters, the fearful 
             syllable death. The only sound which escaped 
             the lips of the demon was that of his own name 
             -Roland! Roland!-articulated in a voice of 
             mingled triumph and revenge - Roland!</p>
            
            <p>The traveller started from his dream as if he 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">24</fw>
            
            had been roused by the sting of a scorpion. He 
            sat upright for an instant, and stared wildly 
            around, scarce recollecting his own identity or 
            situation; but what was his amazement, not to 
            say horror, on perceiving before him the very 
            figure of the demon of his dream, or a figure 
            which his fancy so quickly substituted for him, 
            that the idea of the first was as if by magic resolved 
            and condensed into that which he beheld?</p>
            
            <p>This figure stood before the lamp, whose rays 
            served to define the outline of his person with the 
            greatest accuracy. Of his features little or nothing 
            could be seen, except the light gleaming 
            from his eyeballs. He stood in an attitude which 
            the dreamer's fears quickly determined to be the 
            menacing posture of the demon from which he 
            had shrunk; the forefinger of his right hand elevated, 
            the left hand leaning on a bamboo staff. 
            "In the name of God or Devil," cried Roland impatiently, 
            "who or what art thou?"</p>
            
            <p>The figure relaxed from its position, lowered its 
            right hand, advanced a step forward with a gentle 
            inclination of the head, and replied in a mild and 
            almost musical tone of voice-"Master - what you 
            will." A less experienced person than Roland 
            might have entertained a momentary supposition 
            that the being before him, who had first excited his 
            fears to give him courage, was no other than the 
            evil spirit himself, thus come to tempt him; but 
            our traveller was too much <hi rend="italics">au fait</hi> on the affairs 
            
            <fw type="pageNum">25</fw>
            of this world to expect a bow from the Enemy of 
            mankind; though scared as he had been from his 
            terrific dream, it was some moments before he 
            could thoroughly collect himself. "What you 
            please, - a Negro," repeated the figure, as if to 
            give the white man time to reassure himself.</p>
            
            <p>"What I please, and a Negro" - rejoined Roland, 
            as if unconscious of what he heard. - "But 
            what may be your business, and what want you 
            here? Is this your cave?"</p>
            
            <p>"My business," replied the black man, "is 
            sometimes to go round the lines of my master's 
            estate, sometimes to look after runaway Negroes, 
            to watch the provision grounds, to hunt wild 
            hogs."</p>
            
            <p>"Whose cave then is this," said the other, "so 
            well provided with food and necessaries, and - if I 
            mistake not - with evidences of an illicit calling? 
            The owner of the cave, methinks, must be a 
            wizard - is he not?"</p>
            
            <p>The cave, master," replied the Negro, "has 
            harboured, as I have heard for long times past, 
            many runaway Negroes; they have their provisions 
            here."</p>
            
            <p>"They have," interrupted the other. "I found 
            a fire, and roasted plantains and rum, all 
            ready for entertainment: though I fancied from 
            what I have seen, that Obeah spells were rather 
            the business of those who frequent this cavern."</p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">26</fw>
            
            <p>"You are at least fortunate," answered the Negro, 
            seeming to pay no attention to the remark of 
            Roland about Obeah, "in having found shelter 
            from the storm, and food; and those to whom 
            the cave belongs, were they here, would still respect 
            the laws of hospitality, and make you welcome, 
            be what they may, to all you can require at 
            their hands. But if you have satisfied your hunger, 
            be not offended that I do the same. My 
            presence shall be no annoyance to you. Sleep 
            again, if you feel disposed. I will eat in silence, 
            and at a distance from you."</p>
            
            <p>"Sit down, sit down," resumed the white 
            man, as he arose himself; "eat and be happy. 
            I have no farther disposition to sleep: my mind 
            is too much harassed with what I have encountered 
            this night; my boy, and my horse, and my 
            baggage, are lost in the storm. And where were 
            you?" added he, looking inquisitively in the 
            face of the Negro; "your dress is untouched by 
            the rain."</p>
            
            <p>"I had taken shelter," replied the Negro, "in 
            another part of these caverns, which extend 
            through to the other side of the mountain, before 
            the rain began."</p>
            
            <p>"To the other side of the mountain!" interrupted 
            Roland. "Aye! you know by what entrance 
            I arrived here then?"</p>
            
            <p>"I know," replied the Negro unmoved, "that
            
            <pb/> 
            <fw type="pageNum">27</fw>
            
            you must have entered from the side of 
            Rio Grande, a fearful pass across the devil's 
            gully; over which" (he added with a submissive 
            and respectful smile) "the Negroes say that none 
            but the devil himself can pass, or one whom the 
            devil leads; and that in the dark."</p>
            
            <p>"Ha!" cried Roland, a little moved by the 
            observation; "but you have passed it?"</p>
            
            <p>"It was never passed by a white man before," 
            replied the Negro, as if he had not adverted to 
            the question. "There was once one who fled 
            towards it for refuge, not from a hurricane, but 
            from the punishment of crimes and misdeeds."</p>
            
            <p>"What had he committed?" said Roland</p>
            
            <p>"It was told of him, but I know not how 
            truly," replied the other, "that he had set fire 
            to a gentlemen's estate, and attempted to kill 
            his daughter in a fit of jealousy. He galloped 
            from his pursuers, and scrambled up the 
            pass you found, where they could not follow him; 
            and halting at the bridge, invoked the white 
            man's God to help him over; but he slipped, and 
            tumbled down the gully."</p>
            
            <p>While this conversation took place, the Negro 
            had renewed the fire, taken a piece of salted 
            pork from the jar, put it into an iron pot with 
            some water in it, which Roland had overlooked 
            in his examination of the premises, and set it 
            on the fire to boil. He produced some water 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">28</fw>
            
            also from one of the recesses, with which he 
            mixed himself some rum in a small calabash; 
            and after the libation of a little on the earth, 
            drank to the health of the white man. Roland 
            was neither pleased nor surprised to see him 
            find the food and materials he required with 
            so much ease and familiarity; not doubting that 
            he was at least one of the proprietors of the cave, 
            according to his account of them. But though he 
            felt a confidence in the hospitality of one who 
            could, had he been so disposed, have taken his 
            life while he was sleeping, still he could not 
            regard him without a suspicous feeling, and watched 
            him as he moved about the cave with the same 
            anxious scrutiny as that with which an alarmed cat 
            keeps sight of a terrier dog who has invaded the 
            stable or loft where her offspring are concealed. 
            He had full time to remark the singularity of his 
            dress and appearance, of which it may not be 
            improper to give the reader some idea; as Hamel 
            (by which name he was known) will probably 
            take a principal part in the scenes and events 
            hereafter to be described.</p>
            
            <p>This dealer in magic, for he was no less a personage, 
            was of a slight and elegant make, though 
            very small of stature, being considerably under 
            the middle size. His age was at least sixty; but 
            the lines which that had traced on his features 
            indicated, notwithstanding his profession, no 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">29</fw>
            
            feeling hostile to his fellow-creatures, at war with 
            human nature, or dissatisfied with himself. He 
            was attired in a South American poncho, which 
            had once been of a bright scarlet colour, fastened 
            round his waist by a thin leathern girdle; and his 
            head was decorated with a red silk handkerchief, 
            tied in the fashion of a turban. He was barefooted, 
            and without any offensive weapon; for 
            such the bamboo wand on which he had leaned 
            could hardly be denominated. He moved with 
            an elasticity uncommon for his years; and his 
            manner indicated on his part perfect confidence, 
            wholly unsuspicious of his guest or his purpose. 
            Yet it was but too evident to Roland, that the Negro 
            had evaded his questions as to the magic talents 
            or qualities of some one who frequented the cave; 
            but as the use of Obeah is denounced by law, 
            however despised by white men, he could not 
            attach any particular consequence to such evasion, 
            nor justify himself in expecting any confession 
            on a subject of such importance to the 
            professors or participators in this blind sort of 
            necromancy, if it may be so called.</p>
            
            <p>"Whether conjuror or not," thought Roland, 
            "he does justice to his food;" for in fact the Obeah 
            man had seated himself to his meal at a respectful 
            distance from his guest, and feasted on his 
            humble viands with a persevereance worthy of any 
            high priest, not excepting those who presided at 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">30</fw>
            
            the slaughter of hecatombs. "I have not eaten," 
            said he to his guest, "for twenty hours."</p>
            
            <p>"Why so?" demanded Roland: "have you penances 
            in your religion - fasts, mortifications?"</p>
            
            <p>The Negro shook his head and smiled. "Have 
            <hi rend="italics">you</hi>, master? Do you think fasting or reading 
            prayers will compensate for injuries done to man? 
            Not that I mean to imply anything as relative to 
            yourself," he added; remarking that his question 
            rather affected the white man. "Your religion 
            is now become that of almost all the slaves and 
            free people of colour; yet I never knew them 
            fast or mortify themselves."</p>
            
            <p>"Then wherefore have you abstained from eating 
            so long?" interrupted Roland.</p>
            
            <p>"I have been some distance hence," replied 
            Hamel, "to a plantation that had been deserted. 
            The owner is dead; his wife, afraid to remain 
            among her Negroes, had taken her children to the 
            Bay at Port Antonio; and a white man, a missionary 
            preaching man, was expected to come there, 
            to try if he could persuade the Negroes to go 
            down to the same place to be sold."</p>
            
            <p>"You think he would not have succeeded?" 
            said Roland. "Those who have once shaken 
            off their bonds are not likely to offer themselves 
            again as willing prisoners; besides, there is such a 
            stir making in England for the emancipation of 
            the slaves, that - and it is so much against the 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">31</fw>
            
            religion which the slave owners at least affect to 
            profess, that perhaps few people just now would 
            venture to purchase them; and they would be 
            more apt to increase their numbers from other 
            estates, which will follow their example, than 
            tamely to surrender themselves again to whips 
            and chains; nay, might they not in turn apply the 
            whips and chains to their oppressors?"</p>
            
            <p>"Whips and chains!" said the Obeah man, 
            with a seemingly innocent smile. "Have you not 
            whips and chains in your country yonder too? 
            How do you punish violence, incendeiaries, murderers, 
            ravishers, traitors, and rebels? Can you 
            govern white men with prayers and talking? You 
            have happiness and plenty of there, and no man 
            works but when he likes; why do not the white 
            men stay in their own country, and leave the Negroes 
            to themselves here?"</p>
            
            <p>"Ah!" replied Roland, "you can never be 
            happy, at least for some years, without white men, 
            who shall teach your children to read, to write, 
            to pray to the only true God; the knowledge of 
            the only means of salvation. Would you wish your 
            little ones to become the prey of hell-fire? What 
            ideas will they have of a crucified Saviour? You 
            have among you, it is true, freemen and slaves who 
            can read and write, and some who have made even 
            a little progress in religion; but unfortunately those 
            who are most instructed seem to hold their reli-
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">32</fw>
            
            gion lightest. In my country yonder, as you call 
            it, we are obliged to have priests and ministers of 
            religion, and bishops or elders over them, to keep 
            them from doing wrong; and without some such 
            system here you will relapse into anarchy and 
            infidelity."</p>
            
            <p>"Is your religion a science then," said Hamel, 
            "that it must be taught and learned? and are 
            your chief men in it in danger of doing wrong? 
            We know our duty here already; and it were better 
            to leave us to the God who has guarded us 
            hitherto."</p>
            
            <p>Your God," interrupted Roland, "has left you 
            slaves; the Christian's God will make you free."</p>
            
            <p>"Ah!" cried the wizard, "is it so? Will your 
            God make the Negroes free?" (He looked the 
            white man steadily in the face.) "Will he leave us 
            unencumbered with white parsons? What security 
            can you give us of that? It were better I belonged 
            still to a tyrannical master, than that I was 
            subjected to a tyrannical white priest, who should 
            take from me one of my ten fingers."</p>
            
            <p>"Your master," cried Roland rather exultingly, 
            "takes the labour of all your ten fingers."</p>
            
            <p>"Not so," rejoined Hamel: "we work, it is true, 
            for our masters; but they feed us, clothe us, give 
            us land and houses, attend us in sickness and old 
            age, and leave our minds, our thoughts, to ourselves."</p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">33</fw>
            
            <p>"They leave you to the Devil," said the white 
            man. "If you had a spark of courage, you would 
            emancipate yourselves; if you had one glimmering 
            of the greatness of our God, you would take 
            up the cross, and devote yourselves to his service."</p>
            
            <p>"You are a bold man," replied Hamel again, 
            "to talk so to me; or a cunning man, and wish 
            to make me think you can and will serve my 
            countrymen."</p>
            
            <p>"I both can and will," rejoined the other, 
            "if you are disposed to profit by the opportunity 
            that is about to occur; I am the Missionary 
            that was expected at your abandoned plantation."</p>
            
            <p>"I know it," answered the Obeah man with a 
            polite and significant nod.</p>
            
            <p>"You know it!" cried Roland.</p>
            
            <p>"Yes, master."</p>
            
            <p>"But how?"</p>
            
            <p>"Ah! master," said the Obeah man, "there is 
            nothing in these mountains, in this island, which 
            is concealed from me. I boast not of my secrets; 
            my business is to use them with advantage."</p>
            
            <p>"Know you then the real purpose for which I 
            was travelling ot the forsaken settlement?"</p>
            
            <p>"I know it, my kind master."</p>
            
            <p>The Missionary was a little amazed; but thinking 
            that Hamel's intention might be only to impose 
            on him, he demanded of him to explain what it 
            was.</p>
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">34</fw>
            
            <p>"It is for you to explain," replied the other; 
            "my explanation will not profit you; I could give 
            you evidences of greater knowledge than you 
            dream of; I could tell you who and what you are."</p>
            
            <p>"Tell me," exclaimed the Missionary with impatience: 
            "give me some proof of your intelligence."</p>
            
            <p>"Here is a powder," said the Obeah man, 
            calmly taking a little phial from his girdle, 
            "which will satisfy many men. Will you please to 
            hold for your hand? See - it is white as the 
            snows of Mount Atlas." (The Missionary stared 
            again with amazement.) "I once placed some of it 
            in the palm of a white man, who called upon his 
            God in my presence to avouch his innocence: 
            he was accused of murder. I bid him close his 
            hand as I now close yours; - grasp it tight, press 
            your fingers to your palm; - I told him his God 
            would vouch for him: that if he were innocent, the 
            powder would still be white; if guilty, his fingers 
            would be crimsoned as with blood. Have you 
            pressed your fingers with violence?" The Missionary's 
            heart palpitated, his teeth almost chattered, 
            and his hand trembled as he re-opened it; 
            but the powder was still white as before. "Hah!"
            cried the wizard, "you dared not close your 
            hand; my charm is ineffectual, or you stand self-
            convicted."</p>
            
            <p>The Missionary breated again; if a mountain 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">35</fw>
            
            had been moved from his breast, he could not 
            have felt a greater relief. He held forth his hand 
            with the white powder in it, exclaiming, "False - 
            jugglery."</p>
            
            <p>"Is it false?" cried Hamel; "should it have 
            taken the hue of fire? Yet is it neither falsehood 
            nor jugglery. Let me touch your fingers; - if this 
            hand" - (he looked on the Missionary with an inquisitive 
            smile) - "has never shed innocent blood, 
            let this powder remain unchanged; but if it has 
            shed innocent blood" - (he rubbed the powder 
            firmly with his own finger) - "Lo now! look you 
            there! crimson as the sun-setting in a storm! 
            Are you satisfied? See where it flows like blood 
            even to your arm! deep - deep!"</p>
            
            <p>"Damnation!" cried the Methodist, shuddering 
            at the sight, and shrinking from the touch of his 
            host. "Thou art in league with the fields of hell. 
            What trick is this? Am I a man to tremble beneath 
            the gaze of a Negro? Thou has divined alright - 
            No - no, - 'tis falsehood all; thy knowledge is a 
            trick; - yet how hast thou divined? or who has 
            known me? Perdition! Dost thou not tremble 
            for the consequences of thy indiscretion? Think'st 
            thou my arm could not annihilate thee?"</p>
            
            <p>"I fear you not," modestly replied the wizard, 
            who had watched his emotion as a boa constrictor 
            may be supposed to watch the unhappy deer 
            he means to spring upon; "I fear you not. You 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">36</fw>
            
            have eaten of my food, and drank from my own 
            calabash; you cannot harm me, nor do I meditate 
            any evil to you; your secret is in safe keeping."</p>
            
            <p>"If it were confined to me," thought Roland, 
            "it were better. Whence does he derive his knowledge? 
            Oh God! what scorpions has he awakened 
            in my bosom! Shall I be outwitted, circumvented, 
            made subservient to a dealer in sorcery 
            and incantations? and for what? Yes - I will submit." 
            A thousand fancies mingled in his mind, 
            which resolved themselves at last into one paramount 
            idea; namely, to mould, if he could, the 
            conjuror to his own purposes. "An arduous task, 
            it is true," thought he; "but weightier matters 
            have been brought to bear." He dreamed not that 
            perhaps the wizard entertained similar views with 
            respect to himself. He looked towards him, and 
            saw him leaning against the rock at one of the 
            entrances, absorbed in a profound contemplation, <!-- Comma unclear --> 
            which seemed to abstract him from all conviction 
            of the scene before him; his arms folded under 
            his poncho, his eyes fixed on the floor of the cave. 
            The lamp gleaming on his forehead shewed that 
            his features at least betrayed nothing of what was 
            passing in a mind of which he was so much the 
            master; yet as it lighted up his crimson head-
            dress and his ruddy garmet, whose shadows were 
            deepened by the gloom behind them, it gave to 
            
            <pb/>
            <fw type="pageNum">37</fw>
            
            his appearance something of the demon with 
            which Roland was yet fain to associate him; it 
            is true he could not avoid the idea. In a few 
            moments he moved from his position, put himself 
            for an instant in the attitude of one listening to 
            catch a distant sound, and suddenly hurried from 
            the cave.</p>
            </div>
         
         <pb/>
         <fw type="pageNum">38</fw>
         
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
            
         </div>
      </body>
      
  </text>
</TEI>
